Announcer: Monday, Monday, Monday, open wide dev fans yet ready to stuff your face with JavaScript CSS node modules, barbecue tip workflow breakdancing, soft skill web development hasty as crazy as tasty as web development treats coming in hot here is Sarah CUDA, Bob and Scott L. Totally ski.
Scott Tolinski: Oh, welcome to syntax and this Monday hasty treat. We're gonna be talking all about time block planning, what it is, how it can help you and how it's helped. Well, at least myself, and I don't know if Wes has been doing it. But we're gonna be talking all about the opportunities there that you can get some sweet productivity gains while keeping yourself sane. My name is Scott Tolinksi. I'm a full stack developer from Denver, Colorado, and with me, as always, is the West boss.
Wes Bos: Hey, everybody, I'm excited to hear about this. I don't think I've done time block planning before. But when you kind of mentioned what it was, I said, Yes, I would like to learn about that.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, it's tough to learn about in Cal newports books. He's a big, big proponent of it. So this episode is sponsored by century and century allows you to see your errors in blocks, though, you can throw your errors onto your time block planning schedule, and try to approach them in a more structured way. Now the cool thing about this is that you could just click a button directly from that issue and have it scoot on over to your GitHub issue, even assign it to a specific user directly from Sentry. That way you can make sure all of your issues are accounted for, head on over to sentry.io and sign up using the coupon code at tasty treat all lowercase all one word and get two months for free. Thank you so much for centuries for sponsoring this episode. So, Wes, let's talk about time block planning. Now specifically, let's talk about maybe some of the situations where this thing could come into handy. We'll talk a little bit about what it is how to how to utilize it effectively how to what are some warning signs that you're not utilizing it correctly. So for me personally, I don't know about you. But things have gotten tougher lately, with with planning our time, Courtney has gone back to work full time, I'm kind of working full time. And what that means is that neither of us are actually getting a 40 Hour Workweek, even though we both require it. So it's been kind of a struggle situation for us to figure out how to make the most of whatever these 20 hours that we end up kind of getting our if you guys been seeing a similar sort of struggle. I know we've talked a little bit about this before.
Wes Bos: Yeah, I'm still getting, I would say probably 32 hours in a week, certainly not my full, full 40. So not not nearly as bad as you have it. But we are seeing a bit of a pinch because like my wife is still trying to work. She's squeezing in Saturday mornings before. Well, taking breaks. I talked about this a couple episodes ago, but certainly being able to say, Okay, I've got this three hours, and what can I get done in it or whatever? Like, how do you make that three hours, the most productive three hours as possible. So I'm kind of interested to hear about this.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, and this is one of those things where we've really, really like run into this situation as being a solution. Because it has been a difficult road for us. You know, we've constantly been sort of butting our heads up against each other schedule since trying to work together from home and and have to manage the kids on top of this, it's been a very difficult situation for us. And so after really struggling through a whole bunch of different attempts and non attempts of different things, I had been aware of time block planning, I read all of Cal newports books I listened to his podcast is one of my favorite productivity people. And because of that I just had never really fully dove into this time block planning specifically, in the past, what I've always done is just a to do list, right? Here's the to do list, here's your most important things. Let's get them done. But what happens is that you you see that certain items, when you come time to do it, you maybe put it off for the next week, and then the next week and the next week or whatever. Or maybe you don't give yourself enough time, or maybe you're not noticing you're actually accomplishing things. So time block planning largely is all about blocking off that time for specific goals and specific tasks rather than like global tasks. And it really starts with really removing the time on your calendar that is not open. So the very first thing that we did is we had added to our calendar, I use Google Calendar. So just Courtney, we both have our own schedules, but we can both can see each other's schedules. And we both start just adding our stuff. For instance, I added all of the time, typically with the exception of Mondays, I am on dad duty until noon. So every morning until noon. I'm on dad duty and every day Afternoon, I'm on work duty. So by just sort of blocking off all of that time to say, Alright, this is the time of Monday of duty, it's, you know, 812. I don't even think about that time, I don't schedule that time. I know it's the same every week. And you think, Well, why even put it in your calendar, because it's so visual. And who knows down the line, maybe you'll schedule something here or there. But either way, you're blocking off this time individual for very specific things. Okay. So first and foremost, you want to block out all those regular appointments, you want to block out all of the stuff that you got to do every day. So me personally, I throw dinner around there, here's the time from like, 430, to, you know, 630, it's like, Alright, we're either I'm either going to be making dinner, or I'm going to be watching the kids while Courtney makes dinner. And then after that, it's, you know, hang out with the kids and then bathtime. So I make sure I have all that time blocked off. So I can see exactly what my open blocks of time are. Mm hmm. And then you can start scheduling things. So I like to do this on a Sunday evening, where I kind of sit down with my to do list, and I used to do list, but it's basically just a big old to do list, I sit down to my to do list and I just start adding stuff, anything that pops into my head that I have to do for the week. Alright, got to release a course, got to push it update, got a send this person in email, got to connect with this person, whatever I I put it all into my just inbox of to do list. And then I can sort of see everything in a glance, I can see how much time I have available over the course of the week. And I put each individual task into a real time slot. So instead of just saying, alright, I'm going to work from noon to four, right? Yeah, I'm going to work it so up in the air, or even still up in there. I'm going to code from 12 to four. What am I going to code? What's the end result going to be? How far Am I going to get? What am I going to try to do? Those things are not answered by just throwing just some generic thing. And and if you say hey, Oh, I like to do lists. Yeah, I'll just I'll just approach my to do list. But sometimes, it really ends up happening where you have this to do list, you have these things that you want to do you have coding time, but then something else nudges you away. Within that coding time, your your calendar says it's coding time, and I was supposed to be working on, I'm supposed to be working on this aspect of the checkout flow. But instead, I've decided to refactor this little thing, because well, it's still coding time, it fits under the description. And what you find is, is that if you block out specific amounts of time for specific tasks, ie, I am going to work explicitly on the checkout flow for this thing, right now, then it makes it so much easier for your brain to just say, this is what I'm doing period. This is I'm not doing this else, I'm not doing this other thing, this is what I'm doing. I'm doing this checkout flow. And it really helped me one of the things that in the past I would do is that I would go to record for my tutorial series. And for the most part, you know, I'm prepared or whatever I have my material there, I've got my notes ready to go and I start recording but then I kind of Lottie dot because you know, I have all this time blocked off, I have eight hours blocked out for recording and I got to get like yeah, videos done or something like that, then you just kind of make it fill in at the time. But now what I'm doing is it's like, Alright, I'm gonna spend this hour specifically to read over my materials before I record that I'm going to spend these two hours explicitly to record and only these two hours to record, I'm going to take a break, I'm going to do something else. It allows you to schedule in breaks allows you to schedule and very specific everything, and it prevents things falling from the wayside. Also, if you do it weekly, you definitely get a good handle on,
Wes Bos: like, what
Scott Tolinski: are the key things that I need to accomplish this week? It's not just about today. It's not just about tomorrow. It's this whole whole week. And when you get that stuff out of your brain, like I know I do, I'm not sure if you do I have so many floaties in my brain of
Wes Bos: Yeah, yeah.
Scott Tolinski: What What did you What did you say pick a couple of shows that go the water noodles. I have so many water noodles floating around the side of my brain? Just ideas. And I just want. Like, it's so easy to feel like you have a handle on all that stuff. Like, Oh, I got a handle on this. I got a handle on that. Yeah, yeah. And then all of a sudden, you work on something else, you work on something else. You're like, oh, shoot, I forgot about this thing. Here it is in my deadlines, whatever. So by time blocking planning, as long as you throw everything into your to do list and then you give it a specific time and a specific duration, and everything like that it really has made both of our corneas working life so much smoother.
Wes Bos: Yeah. I think the key thing you said there is that like the task will just expand to the amount of time that you give it Yes. And that is so true. Sometimes like I hate time blocking and stuff like that. And I just like to like sit down with literally nothing on my calendar and just work but I know that I probably would be more productive if I were to give myself an amount of time like this morning. I had two hours before I had to my wife had to run an errand so I think the kids I had six videos or something like that that I wanted to edit and I got them all done, but it was because I knew I had a hard out at 1110. And I had it had to like be done that and I didn't want to like I hate when I'm like halfway through editing a video and I have to pick it up the next day, because I'm not in the like headspace or whatever like that. So being able to block it off with those time blocks seems like a really good idea because it definitely does work. I definitely do that for stuff that is not related to stuff that I enjoy. So whether that's phone calls, or taxes, or big stack of mail that I have to go through or like all of that, like annoying stuff, email, stuff like that I'll definitely block off time for but when it comes to my like creative work, when I'm coding, creating courses recording, I often will just sort of give myself, I think, just unlimited time. And I think the the problem with that is like I don't I'm not good at estimating how long something will take. So like, how do you deal with that? If you're like, Oh, well, I have two hours to do this. And you're like, Oh, I didn't get anywhere near what I wanted.
Scott Tolinski: For me what I've done. It depends on what the deadline of said thing is, if the deadline is not today, and whatever, I found myself getting ahead of things a little bit more with this time block planning, for instance, like I've been, I've been scheduling in time to work on next month's series in the current month that I'm working on one series, I never had done that before. And you might think, well, that's crazy to start working on the next month series when the current month series isn't even done. And maybe you see the timeline, you know, getting closer and closer to being finished. And because maybe the time that you've prepared for the time that you've spent for this month series isn't being totally utilized, or isn't being finished on time. I don't know project estimation overall has been very difficult. Yeah, I think as long as you give yourself enough outs, maybe potentially, like some flex time to say, All right, here's Monday, I'm gonna work on this, you know, from nine to nine to 11, right, I'm gonna work on this one thing till nine to 11. And then maybe didn't get done. So then you could have a flex time later in the week, or maybe even later in the day to say, Alright, whatever's going in here is going to be something that I couldn't finish before. But still scheduling that, that flex time. And I think for me, the biggest thing has been scheduling, scheduling, scheduling, utilizing the calendar, like my calendar, and my productivity has been at its highest, my stress level has been at its lowest with my calendar is absolutely full. It's absolutely full of non meetings, found things and whatever. One of the biggest, small aspects of this, one of the biggest small aspects is really that Courtney can look at my schedule, and not have to ask me anything like sometimes, like just coordinating our schedules was the most, most difficult aspect of this whole thing is to say, like look at our calendars and say, Oh, can I schedule this for this or whatever, whatever. And now we know if it's like the next week coming up, and my calendar is filled out that she can schedule things in the time that she has available that I whatever that just works without having to have that additional layer of meaningless communication, right? Like because I would rather spend the time talking to Courtney about things that aren't like calendar and schedule and whatever. Yeah. Fun stuff.
Wes Bos: My wife will often be like, oh, like, Can? Can you do this during this time? And I'm like, just check my calendar. Like it's not a conversation I need to have over and over again, I don't want to have to think about it. I don't want to have to like, like it's unnecessary overhead, when you've got so much else floating around in your brain.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah. And it's it causes decision fatigue, it's asking, it's pulling you out of context to make a decision on something that you hadn't thought about. And that was such a huge, that was a huge problem for us, too. Because either Courtney would be in the middle of some work. And I would interrupt her to ask her a question, or I'd be in the middle of some work. And she'd interrupt me to ask me a question that was like, couldn't be answered by looking at the calendar. But we weren't using the calendar effectively. So now that everything that we're both doing is going to be in in the calendar, like, it's been like crystal clear Pepsi, for us just like really having a good time with it. So I think it's been a huge upgrade. For me, the biggest difficult component to it is, as you alluded to, not giving yourself enough time to do the right tasks or specific tasks or get the task done in time. But being able to work around that and to be personally I think that's coming with a little bit of experience feeling a little bit better about Alright, this is how much I need for this. But we all know as software developers, bugs don't happen like that. I mean, you could work on a bug that you might think is, you know, a five minute bug and the next thing you know, four hours later, you've stumbled into the gates of hell, and you don't know what's going on, and you don't know what you're doing. And those things can be rough. But the way I really solved that problem is by giving myself some flex time, you know, later on in the week, and actually putting a pin in it and saying, you know what, this is this difficult problem. The deadline isn't today. Let me go ahead and just say like, I'm gonna sit on this problem until tomorrow. Mm hmm. And that's a hard thing. We all know that right? When you get into like, the actual mess of something is like the moment when you want to keep going and sometimes it's worth it and other times you just end up wasting a whole bunch of time. So I didn't know it's still something that I'm learning quite a bit about the Cal Newport books are good. His podcast, I think it's called like, deep work with Cal Newport or something is, is very good. He talks a lot about time block planning. So if you want a greater greater depth of time block planning, his book, deep work is really good. And then his podcast is deep questions, Cal Newport. Both of those resources are fantastic for learning a little bit more about this, but I found both Courtney and I stress levels have been definitely made quite a bit less intense from doing this, especially during quarantine here.
Wes Bos: Beautiful. Wow, thank you for sharing that. definitely gonna have to give that a shot. I've read deep work a lot, but I don't think that I took away the time block planning of that type of thing. So I'm gonna have to give that a shot. Yeah, definitely
Scott Tolinski: do. It's very worth it. And me personally, I've just been getting very into it, putting everything, everything, everything on the calendar. So my calendar is becoming the source of truth. And it reflects that it looks very good. Beautiful.
Wes Bos: All right. Well, thank you so much for tuning in. And we'll catch you on Wednesday. Peace, peace.
Scott Tolinski: Head on over to syntax.fm for a full archive of all of our shows. And don't forget to subscribe in your podcast player or drop a review if you like this show.