Unknown: Monday, Monday,
Monday, open wide
dev fans yet ready to stuff your face with JavaScript CSS node module, BBQ Tip Get workflow breakdancing, soft skill web development hasty, as crazy as tasty as web development treats coming in hot here is Sarah CUDA, Bob, and Scott Taylor.
Totally ski.
Wes Bos: Oh, welcome to syntax. And this Monday histy treat, we're going to be talking about something a little bit different. I have been a longtime Android user, and I bought an iPhone. So I'm going to be talking about my experience moving between the two platforms, and sort of what I like about each platform and what I don't like about each platform, but we're going to keep it largely positive. So all good stuff there. My name is Scott Tolinksi.
Unknown: I'm a full stack developer from Denver, Colorado with me, as always is West boss. Hey, everybody. Hey, Wes. This episode is sponsored by century. So with more about this century AD read is Wes.
Wes Bos: Yes, century is we've talked about them a million times on this podcast, Aaron accepted attraction. But I have something new for you today we'll talk about century just launched support for monitoring errors in native application. So what does that mean? Well, they've extended their toolset, you know, you can use it in in any language out there. Like you can use an a PHP JavaScript on the server or JavaScript on the client. Now they've just rolled it out for native apps. That means if you're you're building a game, or you have an iOS app, or an Android app, or Mac App, or Objective C or cocoa, there's like you should see the list of Go to sentry.io. forward slash for forward slash native. And that will give you a list of all of the different things that they now work with just for native alone. So check it out, use the coupon code tasty treat. To get two months for free with Sentry, go to sentry.io. For that, thanks so much to Sentry for sponsoring. So cool. Let's get into it. I think I wanted to start off first with some of my device history. I want to keep this largely about the platform's themselves, though. So I'll be brief on this. I've always used Android phones, for as long as I've had a phone. My very first phone was the original droid. And then it went to Nexus and then I got pixel phones. So basically, I stayed sort of almost mainline Google phones this entire time. And that said, I do have experience with iOS, I had, you know, an iPod Touch. When it first came out, I had pretty much every iPod ever before that. And largely when it came to the phones, I think the initial iPhone was not very excited about it, the fact that you couldn't do copy and paste, it seemed like they withheld a lot of features that they just should have had from day one. So because the original droid had that stuff directly out of the box, there was just so many features that I was like, Okay, this phone clearly is like loaded up with features compared to the original iPhone. And I think that really just kept me into the Android ecosystem this whole time. Now, at some point here, I started thinking like, hmm, all of the apps I use on my Android phone are available for the iPhone. And it should be pretty decently easy to swap between the two. So maybe I should give it a try. I think there are some rather large misconceptions about Android Oh, when I mentioned that I was going to buy an iOS phone, people were largely like, oh, you're finally getting them a modern device or something. I don't even know what the the sentiment is there or that I heard a lot of that Android phones were sort of analogous to Windows computers, like, oh, maybe you can, you know, drop windows can be I'm not using a Windows computer. And largely, I think the comparison is pretty bad because Android Yeah, way more design focused. And we're like when you use Windows like Windows 10 or something, use Windows 10. There is remnants of Windows XP throughout windows 10. Right, just like icons that don't match and some really ugly design stuff and having to click through some weird error messages. And largely Google's done an amazing job of in particular with their their mainline pixel phones, of really matching like a very nice experience. So the design across Android phones is lightyears ahead of what I would consider design on Windows stuff windows. People don't ask me, I just don't like it. But for the most part, I never really found that comparison to be that super great. And as far as like cheaper and not as nice if you're buying a flagship Android phone, and that's really not a concern. The Samsung's and the pixel phones are really they're really excellent phones. And I think that's another thing too is that people see there being like two OSS here, right. There's there's iOS and then there's Android. Yeah, but really, the Samsung version of Android is very different from the Google version of Android, which is very different than the LG version of Android. And sure enough, Google has had some issues with that aspect of things. But what you have to know is that everybody tweaks in manipulates the platform. So they're not all the same. Okay, so why switch? Again, I mentioned that to be easy to switch. You know, I have a lot of users of my platform that use iOS and I wasn't experiencing my platform as one of those users. So I needed to get a modern iOS device anyways, just to do testing. And I figured if I can, why not just get the king of the hill here? For
Unknown: Which one did you end up getting the iPhone pro Max? So the big boy pro so like the most decked out one you can possibly buy?
Wes Bos: Yeah, pretty, pretty much that looks sick. But not with the most hard disk space. It's only 256 out here. Only 256 to come up. We're gonna use that with all the cloud storage.
Unknown: Oh, I did no Hold on. app you do have storage is the worst I run out of there. I stopped using it because they give you like one gig. And like, that's like three photos on on an Apple phone? Oh, yeah. Well, I'm
Wes Bos: still I shouldn't say I'm still using Google Photos for photos, obviously. Because Yeah, that is way better. I use Google Drive, because I'm paying for it. And I've paid for it. I got like two terabytes for like $8 or something. So
Unknown: it's like, it's pretty cheap. I don't use any Apple services. They're all way too expensive, and not nearly as good. Yeah,
Wes Bos: yeah, they're really not as good. And so that's like, part of the the bummer about switching here is is a lot of these little things that I've kind of hit like that. But so I switched. I've been using the iPhone for a week. And I've been using it every day as my main phone, I have largely put my Android devices in the drawer, just to allow myself to not, you know, fall back to it. And I figured I would give a little bit of pros and cons to the iPhone here. And I will basically approaches as to who does what better, right? So who does things better? Who does the apps better? While iPhone is way better for apps, that's the one thing I've quickly learned is that every single app that I'm used to using on my Android device, even like the exact same app one to one runs better, feels faster, feels more connected to the operating system looks better, every little aspect of these apps is better on the iPhone and and that to me was sort of shocking, because I never really felt like they were bad. On Android, most of the apps I've used felt really good. It's only after using them on the iPhones like oh, yeah, these are really smooth. And that's coming from I had a one plus 70 Pro for a little bit. And that has a 90 hertz screen. So for those of you who don't know, the screen is basically refreshing at 90 frames per second, like a you know, it's like a super fluid video, rather than like a choppier less frames per second video. And I was thinking that after using the 90 frames per second, or the 90 hertz screen, that I wouldn't be able to go back to a normal screen. And I think the iPhone smoothness overall really sort of put those concerns to rest because although the screen isn't technically as smooth, it just feels very smooth. And all the apps feel good to us. So that to me was like really, I was blown away by that aspect of iOS. And I really, really enjoyed how the app experience has been. That said, one of the things I like way more on the Android phones is the homescreen. The homescreen on Android phones is basically compared to the iOS, iOS is just a grid, right. And it's a grid that keeps you in this very specific grid. You if you move an app, they all shuffle around where an iPhone or an Android, you can, if you put an app at the bottom of the screen, it stays at the bottom of the screen. Likewise, you can throw widgets on the Android homescreen. And they iOS added widgets to their little sidebar, but to be honest, everything they suck. They suck every week that I've had on here has been worse than the counterpart on Android. I wish that you could like add them to the homescreen. And like have useful ones where you could like glance at it. But there instead they were like hidden in this like weird swipe Yeah, spot with all of your notifications. I've never liked that at all, either. Some things are weird about it like like a podcast, player one. The one on Android has the keynote, the widget has the ability to jump forward 30 seconds or something. And that's something I would use somewhat frequently. And now this the pocket cast widget on iOS is just like a playlist of the upcoming next tutorials are now coming next podcast. But iOS like unifies what's playing? And the apps have the ability to add skip buttons to the homescreen which is what I use. Does you not see
Unknown: that yet? What do you mean, you skip buttons to where on the home screen like in the pull down? No, if you're playing if you're playing a podcast and you like wake your phone by pressing a button, you see what's currently playing Oh, yeah. And there's their skip buttons as part of that media player. Right.
Wes Bos: Yeah. And that's a whole nother thing is Android does all that stuff better. So for me that's like not really like that. Oh, like a negative. That was a big deal for me when I got gift buttons on the homescreen. So I kind of feel like iOS users just don't have the breadth of experience with like a Pixel phone to know what's better or worse about them. Because there's so many things that Google does really well as phones. But there's a lot of things that obviously iOS does really super well too. So so far we're blissfully ignorant is what you're trying to say about us. Yeah. Think that's totally true. Because, yeah, the homescreen is definitely worse. You know, a lot of people because I got the big phone, and I've mentioned like not being able to tap the Apps in the top left corner, and people would say, well, you have to turn on reachability, you'd have to do this weird, weird little double tap trick, or you have to do this or that or what I was like, or, you know, they could just let you put the apps at the bottom where your fingers are, so that you could touch them better. Because to me, that seems like a no brainer. I mean, like, Apple wants to talk about your thumb position, but it is shocking how many things in iOS, the tap target is in the upper left hand corner. Yeah, even situations where you have, you know, the gesture, pullback gesture, there's so many instances where that gesture doesn't come into play, and you have to physically go up and reach in the top left. And I've just like, there's solutions that have been available for this specific problem in in Android for you know, you know, whatever, 10 years, and like, they have that much time to look at these and say, Oh, yeah, let's adopt some of this stuff. But in, you know, typical Apple fashion they're just holding. So what's the what are the solutions to that? Because right now, what I have to use is the reach ability, where you swipe down quickly on the very bottom. Yeah, and that works like, like one in 10 times that actually works for me, it's awful. He used to be great with that used to triple tap the home button. Yeah, and it would dry with john good, scoot the whole thing down. And it was great. But now I've I've moved to mostly just using swipe motions to go back and things like that. It's it's kind of annoying. Yeah, I mean, the solution to that is to not pin all of the apps to the top left of the screen and pin them to the bottom right. You know, if you had to, if you wanted to have them pin somewhere, pin them to the bottom right where their hand is, or the bottom left or, or heaven forbid, let the user choose where they're pinned or not have them pin it all. You know, like I could see it functioning like a you know, an iOS or Mac OS desktop where you could like clean them up or something that said, I just I wish that I could like because what this encourages encourages you to have a billion apps on your homescreen. No, no was one a billion apps in my homescreen. I'm a little bit more minimalist than that. But if I were to put everything into folders, then all the folders would be in the top and then I wouldn't be able to go and touch them. So it's almost like I have a layer of two of apps that I don't really use just to push down the apps that I want to use. And so people will say get a pop socket, or these were all bad solutions to worse. Yeah, easy answer. And the easy answer is let you move the apps to the bottom of the screen. That's a that's just a you know, a thing that they could have done by now. So another thing that iOS does really super well as the new cameras are awesome. But the wide angle lens, the ultra wide, I keep playing with the ultra wide like crazy. The new camera system is super good in every single facet. And it really beats the camera system on any Pixel phone I've ever owned. With the exception of night photography. Apple's like really advertising their night photography. They very oversold it. It is like if you were coming from an iPhone to this phone, you'd be like, Oh, this is awesome. But if my pixel two has better night photography, then this brand new Apple does. So it wasn't really impressive to me. And it was a little disappointing. The night photos were kind of muddy in comparison. Sure, they're they're better than an older iPhone. And honestly, the the phones interface for doing a night photo was way more intuitive than it is on Android. So props for that, largely like most of the apps and camera app stuff is way more intuitive on the iPhone. But for the most part, I found the camera system to be incredible. With the exception of the night photography was just kind of weak. Another thing is the device quality, this thing is darn heavy, then I kind of I'm trying to figure out where the weight comes from. Because I have pixel phones. It's the gigabytes. Yes, it's the gigabytes. I like really wonder like if there's like weights in here, because the Pixel phone is all glass. It has all the same features and whatever, but it's way lighter, maybe even like I don't, I'm just holding them here. It doesn't feel like half is light, but it definitely feels like I don't know, third as light or something as the Pixel phone. So I don't know where all this weight comes from. But it's a heavy darn phone and it feels nice. Feels nice in your hand. Yeah. So overall, I feel like the build quality is is nicer on this. That said,
Unknown: I think there is assumptions about a pixel or Android device build quality and for my experience, they've always been totally Excellent. So did you get a case for it yet? Or do use a case? No, I don't know if I will. It's like $5,000 if you drop it, I know the back is like $350 if you break the glass which happened to me on my other one but thankfully I had another issue and I was still within a year and they just swapped it out and without worrying about the broken class. Yeah, maybe
I should just order one
do it honestly man. Yeah day and it's it sucks cuz like thanks for making the phone out of glass and I take this beautiful thing at the throw in this ugly rubber case. They have to make it heavy man that's the whole thing is so for people like me will be like, Oh, it's heavy. Yeah, glass is expensive. Yeah, it costs $350 per square of glass. Yeah. Well, this machined out of one piece of glass. Yeah. I don't
Wes Bos: I can't really. Yeah, no to that. So overall device quality is awesome. The phone does like fun things really well. So what I mean by that is like they make like using the camera very fun. The amount of apps that exist that are more fun than what exists on Android. You know, games come out sooner, those kind of things on iOS, I found for the large part this, this phone to be a lot more fun. Like I wanted to be. I wanted to be playing with things on it more often. Which isn't to say, I didn't do that on my other phone. But like, I just I had a lot more fun on this device, if that makes sense.
Unknown: Interesting. Ya know, something that I did a couple of weeks ago is I took one of my old iPhones is actually the iPhone eight, nine, what's before the 10? The before the 10 was eight.
Wes Bos: Well, nine comes before 10 not an apple world. No, I think it's an eight. And I jailbroke it remember like, I don't know, like years ago when I first got like the first ever iPhone. I jailbroke it and then you could like run like apps on it. Because there were there was no App Store for the first one. Yeah, and I recently needed the ability to run a jailbroken app on my phone, which was interesting. The tethering they locked down tethering on some phone plan. And I was like that honestly. So I i jailbroken. And I was like, man like this is you can get like custom homescreen layouts and yeah, other stuff. But like, let's
Unknown: talk about that. Bit. The problem is with jailbreak Look, I've been looking into jailbreaking extensively because it solves a lot of my issues. Like Yeah, to move the apps to the bottom. But then you open yourself off to some random Chinese hackers. And
Wes Bos: there's only so much that I know because I rooted Android phones for a little while. So I'm like sort of in in that that like know what to look for sort of vibe about stuff. But again, you you're you are opening yourself up because once you know the the walled garden is open, who knows what can get in? Yeah, but I'm really I yeah, I might jailbreak if it comes to the point where it's easy for this particular phone to do. But so far this phone and this OS is not available. So if it was I might have already jailbroken it to be honest. So we'll see, I found that the iOS keyboard is not good. And I complain about it a lot. So I'm sorry, if I'm being annoying on social media, the Android keyboard out of the box, the G board is way better. What's better about it? I was curious. So yeah, it's funny because people were like, I never I got a lot of people on Instagram saying, well, I never had a problem with the iOS keyboard. Okay, but you maybe you've never used a good keyboard before because the iOS keyboard is dog sh it, it's not good. So, for instance, the iOS keyboard feels like it's always trying to know what to do for you at all given points at the time. But like sometimes they'll hide the number row when you don't want it to and then you have to do an extra click, or the keyboard always has your numbers behind any of the letters. So you can just push and hold, just push and hold on the P and it gives you a zero anytime anywhere, you never have to ever touch that. That's just always there available to you. And oddly enough, I found most things in iOS took one or two more clicks to do than than Android, which was shocking to me, I was figuring it to be the other way around. But like for instance, the the Android keyboard has things like gift search and an extended clipboard built into it. But in a way that's way easier for you than to like have to rely on the app that does it. Like a lot of the stuff that I message has in it, the G board has an out of the box. And the G board on Android is way better than it is on iOS, I found it to be not so good. I actually have found my keyboard sort of bliss on this thing with swiftkey, which is a keyboard I used to use way back in the day and Android and never really loved it. But the iOS version is basically just a slightly augmented version of the iOS keyboard itself to the point where it makes it just a little bit more usable. So for those of you who feel like the iPhone keyboard is great. I just, I feel like you probably haven't spent enough time with a nicer more modern keyboard. It just hasn't changed. It feels like the iOS keyboard feels like the exact same keyboard that was on my iPod touch that I got when I was in, in college. Yeah, they I ran I ran the G board, which is Google's keyboard for iOS for over a year. And it's amazing. I like it. I especially like the ability to search emojis. It's like yeah, how much time I waste flip, flipping through looking for the like dead eyes or something like that, oh, gee, you can't do that on iOS. It like tries to suggest them for you. But it's never. I always like type like dead eyes or something like that. And I can't figure out what it is. And I switch back.
Unknown: I feel like the Google frequently used emojis is better. Yeah, g board. Interesting. But I switched back just to try the new swiping. And I feel like the swiping on iOS is better than g board. Yeah, I the swipe thing has existed in Android for since like version like one. Oh, like I got it like three weeks ago. I know. It's funny. I used to use it all the time. And now I don't use it as much. I
Wes Bos: pretty much just use voice dictation. But that was another thing. It's like A lot of these things that are coming to iOS that people make a big deal about are like not a huge deal to me only because they weren't ever problems for me in the first place. They were problems that have been solved. So that the keyboard, okay, yeah, I just don't I don't love it. But the swift key is better than nothing are better than the iOS one.
Unknown: There was a one thing I thought was really interesting. I use a password manager. I don't know if you do I use one password. Yeah, I use LastPass. Okay, I use LastPass. But their support staff was rude to me. So I cancelled the service.
Wes Bos: I was like, how did you do a team account and a family account? They're like, well, you have to create two separate accounts, and you can't merge them. Like oh, my Okay, see you later. Yeah. So yeah, so I use a one password. And one password takes like three or four more clicks to get my passwords to autofill than it does on Android. On Android, if you like pop open a form that it just like you can do the fingerprint or the whatever authorization, the moment that you load the form, you just do the fingerprint, and it does like a little paint over like a modal. And then it just auto fills. We're on iOS, I have to click on the input, then click the passwords and then select from which key chain manager whether it's the iOS built in one or one password, and then I have to then select to autofill. The thing it's like three or four clicks when an Android it's really just me resting my finger on the fingerprint reader. So there's like little things like that where I'm like, okay, I feel like they probably should have should have figured this out by now. But is that enough to negate the positive things about this phone? No, obviously not. I think the iPhone overall isn't like an awesome package. And I've been super happy with it. The haptics on the iPhone are way better, which is not surprising, or which is surprising to me, because Android has been doing haptics for a long, lot longer. And so I was expecting the haptic feedback engine, which is the little vibration, I was adapting that to be okay. Especially because on Android out of the box, each key press on the keyboard triggers a haptic vibrate, which is something I really love and something they don't do an iPhone because they feel like it will artificially make the battery or it'll make it seem like the battery's worse than it is. So they just say, Hey, we can't You can't do this at all. So instead of like giving you the option, they're just like making that decision for you, which is fine. I've gotten used to not having it but I wasn't expecting the haptics to be so good, but they feel very nice. I like it a lot. I like the vibration motor, how it feels in your hand, for Okay, so let's get into the last couple of things I don't like about the iPhone before this episode goes way over. Android does a couple things way better. So search and usability are generally better. So because the Google search bar is at the bottom of the phone with a little microphone in the bottom, right, the very easiest thing for your finger to hit on the Android phone, or at least the latest pixel is a microphone to do a Google search or Google Assistant, whatever you want it to do, right. So for me, it's really easy for me to press that button and just ask my phone something or search something. Siri is nowhere near as useful or as good. So for me to even get a Google search out of that, what I had to do is create a shortcut that opens up the Google app and then selects the input. And then I have to click the microphone button. So it's like three clicks to get a Google search Where is like the easiest click in the world on an Android. And that's it, I could just ask Siri. But I haven't a great experience with Siri. Also, it like triggers all the time when I'm not even saying the word. So I don't love it. Last one is notifications are way better on Android notifications, like they don't dismiss easily on iOS. Like you have to swipe them twice, like a message one, you have to swipe and then swipe again, to clear it. You can't just do like a hard swipe to get it to go away. The Android has these quick replies. So that if I had a notification is the text message. And like Courtney would say like, Alright, I'm coming home, or something I could just with basically one click from the notification, send a response that says See you soon or something because that's like a built in reply. So that aspect, I know the built in replies exist on iOS, but they're not integrated as well until the notifications. It's just, you know, notifications. In general, I
Unknown: think anybody who's used the two operating systems would probably say that the Android implementation is a little bit better. But overall, I am I gonna keep this phone? What am I gonna do? I'm gonna keep using it as my daily phone. Oh,
Wes Bos: yes, I'm gonna keep it. I'm gonna keep it, I'm gonna keep using it. Like I said, I just have a lot of fun on this device. And not to mention, I feel like I need more experience with iOS more, you know, just more exposure to the apps in the ecosystem so that I can have a totally different breadth of understanding of interaction and that sort of thing that you get from using a completely different operating system. But I do I do recommend people check out the pixel phones and try them out. Beyond just talking trash on the internet. They're not windows. It's not It's not like that at all. They're very good phones and they just A lot of things in my opinion better. So you know, give them a check out if that any of this sounds interesting to you. So this is my experience switching from iOS to Android. I've been using Android forever and ever. And I probably won't stop using Android. But for right now, my main device is going to be the iPhone. And I look forward to getting a dead Apple watch because it looks pretty dope.
Unknown: Sweet. All right. Well, that's good to know. If you think Scott is wrong about any of this stuff, we would love to hear you tweet us at syntax FM, and we will catch you on Wednesday. Alright, catch you then. Please head on over to syntax.fm for a full archive of all of our shows. And don't forget to subscribe in your podcast player or drop a review if you like this show.