Unknown: Monday Monday Monday open wide dev fans yet ready to stuff your face with JavaScript CSS node module BBQ Tip Get workflow breakdancing soft skill web development hasty as crazy as tasty as web development treats coming in hot here is Sarah CUDA, Bob and Scott Taylor.
Totally ski.
Wes Bos: Oh, welcome to syntax in this Monday hasty treat. We are transforming ourselves into the Joe Rogan experience podcast or or whatever, because we're talking about the float tank experience. Wes and I have both done a float tank in the past couple of weeks here. And we just wanted to talk about it because it was a really interesting experience. My name is Scott Tolinksi. I'm a full stack developer from Denver, Colorado and with me as always is Wes Bos. How you doing Wes? Hey, good. I was gonna do like a hilarious intro like Joe Rogan podcast by night all day. Let's go. I stole your joke. It was written in the in the show notes, so I decided to just yank it for my own. What else is in his? His intro? The one UFC fighter said something hilarious trained by day Joe Rogan podcast by night. Oh, yeah. Anyways, this is gonna be Yeah, like a kind of a different episode. But I people are so interested in this whole flow of flow. Just Just to give you a quick rundown real quick before we hit our sponsor, like a float tank is where you float in salt water in complete darkness, which sounds terrifying. There's supposed to be all these benefits to it. So Scott and I, the good journalists we are we tried it. Yeah, that's exactly why Yes. So this episode is sponsored by one of our sponsors here that has just been so incredibly useful for both myself and Wes, and this is Log Rocket. Now Log Rocket is the exception tracking tool that allows you to see the errors and bugs as they're happening in real time on your site. The cool thing about Log Rocket is they give you this session replay allowing you to see the video of what the user did. So you're not going to be in a sensory deprivation tank, while you're trying to solve these bugs, you're actually going to be able to see things and understand what's going on instead of pitch black. So you'll want to head to Log rocket.com forward slash syntax to get 14 days for free. So check it out. Again, get out of that sensory deprivation tank when it comes to solving your bugs and figure out what's going on. So let's get into it here. You said you mentioned What is it off the bat but I think our experiences might have been even a little bit different in terms of like what it was so do you want to give a rundown of what it was in your experience maybe like the actual physical what was going on there? Yeah, so there are these float centers or float tanks probably you have one within a 20 minute drive from you wherever you are the if popped up all over the place. Anytime I'm driving I see one and there's been one like literally five minute walk down the road from me for a while now and I've always wanted to try it. So I booked up one the other night and went on over and what it is is it's kind of like a spa they do massages and stuff there as well. And you go in and then there's like three different rooms each have a tank in them and then they have like a shower where you have to shower before and after. And then there's some other kind of cool stuff there's like a oxygen bar with kombucha which is pretty cool. So you can hook yourself up to the otu and get going and there's just like it's kind of like a gym as well where you can like do your hair after and things like that so I don't know like what what was yours like how is that different? The place I wouldn't was only floating like that's all they did. They had maybe like 10 rooms or so. And the rooms are like very lodgy with very woodsy very lodgy Oh, shower super nice. And did you have to do the whole like, plug up your ears with the there was like some like wax that you did like yeah, plug up yours with because you can't get the salt water. They gave you some wax earplugs. They got a stick in there. Yeah, it was pretty intense. Yeah, they they say you cannot do them and you're supposed to put some stuff over cuts as well. Yeah, like Vaseline stuff over cuts. Yeah, and that's just because if salt water gets in your ears and dries up and that could be bad. So I have like a lot of like little scrapes and cuts all over me all the time. Yeah, just from breakdancing but because I just bump into things all the time and I'm very pretty clumsy dude. So I had a lot of nicks and cuts and I used the entire thing of Vaseline just basically covering myself and handed to him as a lead. I didn't do any of it and it did not help that much if it still hurt it still hurt. Oh yeah, I was like screw this. I just went in the guys like you don't have to use it if you don't. It's good for you. There's like magnesium and salt and those are good for any little cuts that you have. Well,
I got my fair share and it was a not the best feeling. So I saw A photo of your tank and your tank looked pretty small my tank was like the size of my kitchen. Like my, I really I could, you know, put my arms out in a T pose and like, you know, spread my legs, I would not be able to touch any of the walls. So my my tank was almost large enough. It was I would say my tank was like eight feet vertically by five feet wide. Like I couldn't I couldn't lay horizontally in it. But I had a lot of room and there was points where I felt like I was spinning in a circle. And you just expect to hit the wall at some point. And I didn't I never hit the wall. Yeah, you didn't. Okay, cuz I my take was like, I'm just kind of like ballparking it? Yeah, it was definitely at least eight feet by like six feet wide. But I definitely did bump into the sides every now and then. When I was in it. So you take was how tall was your tank? Because it looked like it might have been shorter. It was five oh, like three and a half feet tall? Oh, yeah, that's
Unknown: kind of creeps me out, man. Yeah, here's a little bit like a coffin. And mine was like, at least like eight feet tall, like vertically.
Wes Bos: Okay, I'm just looking at the website. And they have three tanks here. I think I have I was in the oldest tank. And I think they buy higher tanks. Because of that. Like it. I think the hardest part of getting people to try this stuff is getting over the anxiety of being trapped in a black hole. Because the other thing is this is alternatively called a sensory deprivation tank, where you can't hear anything. You can't see anything. And you're floating in water, which is people's nightmare and a lot of cases. Yeah, yeah, it is. So okay, they talk about the benefits in the benefits are largely in my mind, you know, they could be a lot of things they're going to claim it does a lot, obviously. But in my mind, it seems like the the biggest benefits would be just simply that ability to meditate and totally zone out in that kind of space. And really just shut off your mind a little bit. But not only that, but it's like how many times in your life Have you ever been in a position where your muscles aren't doing things to hold you in a specific spot whether you're laying down even if you're laying on a bed, your muscles are still activated in some way with this float tank, there's so much salt in in the water that I found for like the very first time I've been having all these back problems that like I was able to identify when I'm at rest, which of my muscles are firing and which ways and I found the ability to shut off each muscle individually to the point where I was just sitting there like a dish of mold or something like I was just in total able to shut off every single one of my muscles. So for me that was the biggest benefit of everything was the ability to just like deactivate any sort of tense muscle activation I was having. Yeah, I could feel it. So as soon as I laid down, or maybe about 1015 minutes in you could I could feel like my neck was the biggest one where you could just like feel that it was tense. And I have to like actively focus on relaxing it. Um, it was my lower back for me. Oh, yeah, lower back for me was the one yeah, just never been in a situation where your head can like maybe my pillow is wrong or something like that. I've just never been a situation where you can just like let limp like that. And it was kind of interesting. Totally. There's supposed to be all kinds of like benefits. The reason why I got interested in right now is that I got a watch that tracks your sleep. And it says I have very low deep sleep. So I'm going down all these different roads of like, what are different things you can try to get better sleep. And this was sort of on the list. And I've always wanted to try it at some point. I didn't we talked about it on the podcast like a year ago. So that's kind of why I tried it. And I thought it was pretty neat. So like, you want to go into now like how did you feel like how long did you float for about an hour? hour and a half? Oh, wow. Yeah, right in Yeah, I did it. I did an hour but I think the guy gave me an extra 10 minutes on either side. So I was an hour and 20 minutes for me. Yeah, mine was an hour and a half I got in the tank. And I don't think I had like panic immediately because so the blue lights on the light shut off and all of a sudden it's pitch black. And I didn't necessarily have a problem floating the water in the air and everything is like perfectly 90 degrees. So you're just like best band ever feel comfortable? And yes, yes, you're right. Sure.
I initially, I don't know if I it took me a little bit to shut my brain off in any sort of meaningful way. But I was worried that I was going to have some sort of like panic issue or anything like that I didn't. But I did have a bit of anxiety at the beginning that Oh, you're in here for an hour and a half, like doing nothing. And for those of you who know me at all I like to do things I'm a doer I'm I'm bopping around and moving around. And I haven't found you know, I wasn't able to float and relax the whole time. So what I did is I got it. And I it took me, you know, like really, you know, 1520 minutes to just sort of decompress. And then I found myself okay saying now I'm going to really heavily relax and I would heavily relax for about five minutes and feel very relaxed and then get the urge to like, okay, now I need to like stretch. And since mine was big enough, I was like doing sort of side by sides stretching out my side stretching on my back, like I said, I largely when, because I was having back issues. So I was in there really finding them that muscle and moving around, and I would do that for maybe about 1015 minutes. When I say, you know, you're in here to relax, let's float again. So I'd float, not move and just chill out. And then I just started, like, I'm just like this, I was starting to like trying to figure out what kind of positions I could get into and still float, which is ridiculous. like trying to get into like, in the hour, I was like doing my legs like totally cross like a yoga, Lotus yoga. And then I put my hands up in this different ways. And I'd like to start to roll over. And I was like, seeing what kind of, like balance points I could find. And it was like it was so to me, that was like ultimate relaxation. Because I wasn't thinking about anything, it was like you're floating here and you're you're not exerting energy, but you're trying to find these positions in which you can maintain your balance, which is kind of ridiculous. But I went into it thinking, Okay, I'm going to have some quiet time to just think in plan out my month, week, whatever we're like, really run through course ideas, run through code ideas, run through that kind of thing in my head. And let me tell you, it was impossible to think about any of that stuff. I couldn't think about my computer, I couldn't think about code I tried like eight or nine times to be like, Alright, so let's just the series that you're recording right now, like, what are we going to do about it, and then just couldn't get anywhere. So I found the best use of my time was to again, stretch and to just zone out. And when I was expecting, like the time to be over, and I was maybe like 45 minutes in. So I just realized, okay, just need to chill out and chilled out and floated for the last half an hour and just relaxed. And it was it was very refreshing. And like I said, I think the biggest factor is just how much stress I've been having on my back lately. So I think that was the biggest benefit for me. That's really interesting. So I ended up bringing my phone in so I could take no joke and bring my phone and I was about to like it. I didn't want to judge too hard until I heard the rest of that sentence. But I was I was putting on my judgemental hat right now. Oh, no. So when I went in you so you go in and you close the door on yourself. And then you lay back and the first five minutes had like a couple mini like, oh, maybe I should open the door and just like get my bearings like little panic attacks. And then you just have to learn how to like sorta just give it up and just lay there and that's very hard thing for me to do because I'm very much always on and whatnot. And a lot of people told me like, I'd be too scared because like, I don't want to have these like, like weird thoughts like my thoughts come and eat me, you know, that I didn't didn't have any of that. So first, after the first five minutes, the panic went away. After the first 15 minutes I finally started to just like, just relax and sort of let my head float and then just kind of totally go for it. And then for about I don't know, at about like 40 minutes I didn't do any moving around. I the only thing I changed is my arms floating above my head and then the beside my head. And every time I did that my head hands were like so heavy. They feel like they're 5000 pounds. Did you ever flow with your arms like this? I for those of you who can't see me have my arms back and like you if you're doing the YMCA football. Yeah. Oh, touchdown. Yeah. That's how I spent most of it like that. And then like, I was also getting like sore. Like, like, I felt like I needed to stretch. And I asked the guy about that after. And I was like, does that happen? He's like, no, sounds like you need to do yoga.
Unknown: Yeah, if you're like this and you're feeling sore, it means you're you're activating some sort of muscle because maybe this isn't like comfortable. Like this is a venue to watch more football. Maybe. Celebrate more, man.
Wes Bos: So I out about 40 minutes, I started to like, see like these blue lights. Like I felt like I was dang I felt like I was laying in a tent camping. And I could start to see like blue light and stars, which is really cool. So I was like, Alright, I'm I'm digging this all like I don't have anything like that. Oh, totally into it. So I just kind of like at a certain point. I was like, oh, maybe I shouldn't like this, but I was like No, I'll just like go totally into the blue stars and whatnot. So it's kind of like a really neat experience for about like 10 minutes of just feeling like you're floating and like obviously are floating. But you feel like you're floating in sky. At a certain point, I didn't know if my if my body was underwater or above water. I didn't know if my eyes were open or not like I remembered like, opening and closing them. And I was like, I can't tell the difference. And that was really, really neat. And then that stopped about 1015 minutes. And then yeah, at the end I had like, I don't know how long I had, but I kind of just started to anticipate it being over in the day turn music on when it's over. And they play Enya. Or something like that.
Unknown: Yeah, I had, like, I was like hearing Phantom music.
Oh, yeah, me too. Like, oh, is
there music playing right now? Is there music playing? Wait, is there music? The adult like?
Wes Bos: Yeah, the other thing I have is I have a very slight amount of tinnitus from probably going to hardcore shows when I was a kid. So I have a slight ringing in my ear. I noticed that a couple times and started driving me nuts. Because you have earplugs in and everything is pitch quiet. But then as soon as you start to I started to focus on something else and just on my breathing, and that totally went away. Which I was glad I didn't have to spend an hour there hearing ringing in my ears. So yeah, that was and then after about 15 minutes, I came out I felt amazing, like so relaxed. almost felt like you had like a really nice massage, which was cool. And then you go ahead and you shower off all the salt. There's just so much salt on you. It tastes disgusting. I think it's Epsom salts is what they use. It tastes this you got it in your mouth. Yeah, like I had a scratch and I scratched it was tasted awful. It's not like like oh, salty ocean are like an oyster so that it's like, it tastes like like super bitter. Like you had laundry detergent in your mouth or something they told me like, or no, I sorry, I read that in some blog. And they were saying do not scratch your your eye or anything when you're in there because that would just totally ruin the experience. I was like hyper cognizant of not touching my face in different ways. Yeah, he said to make sure you dry your hair very well, before you go in because if there's one drip of water that drips down your forehead, you're you're toast, huh? Yeah, that would suck. So that was experience. It was really, really neat. I thought it was pretty cool. I felt super relaxed after it had an unreal sleep that night. Like I did it from 9pm to 10pm. So I just walked home and that sounds great. fell asleep and had an awesome sleep. There was the stats were not any different. on my watch, which they have been actually getting better. I'm still trudged trying stuff, but that was pretty neat. So now the question is, would you do it again? Yeah, yeah, I would absolutely do it again. I might augment the experience to hair. But no, I would definitely do it again. I thought it was fantastic. In terms of how much I was able to shut my brain off. I was impressed with myself. I left being like, Oh, I had no idea. I could be that calm for that long. And just like with no assistance whatsoever, just chill out. So yeah, I would absolutely do again. I had a great time. I actually I wouldn't double duty on this. And so I went on that Tuesday, and I had just gotten a massage on Monday with like cupping. So they had like done little cupping on my back and they just like hammered on my back and then I got to do the floating for an hour and a half. And I think between those like those two days, was like really instrumental in bringing my back out of some sort of hellhole that it was in currently. I think I'll do it again. I think I need to give it like two or three more goes to sort of get the full experience. My only apprehension is it's super expensive led like mine was 60 bucks, or 6069 bucks Canadian which is like what let's 65 Canadian and US is 50 bucks us for a float. Well, how much was yours? For a one and a half hour? Probably like 60 bucks us. Okay, we did a Groupon and we had like Groupon bucks because we were returning one so we were just like trying to get rid of the Groupon bucks before they expired. And yeah, that's so we didn't pay real money for it. We paid Oh yeah, that we had paid already at some point and another like a year ago for it so it was allocated money. I the 60 bucks is a lot. Some of them you can get your your if you get it with a massage, you can get your like, what's called your benefits to cover it, but my benefits don't cover that kind of stuff. I pay for my own benefits, right? We don't have that good of a plan. But like you can get a full body massage for 480 Yeah, so that's I don't know I think I'm gonna give it a couple more to see if there's anything revelate revolutionary about it but it's probably something I'll do every now and then yeah, especially if I see like a deal where it's like I think they have like one day a week where it's like 39 bucks for a float maybe I'll try that. Yeah, I I think the massage to me is more beneficial simply just for how goofed up a lot of my spine, neck back and all that stuff fire. But the flow was just I thought it was great and I would definitely do it again. And I wouldn't dissipate that it will happen. We've both had a lot of people telling us that the benefits really come in in the second and third more so than the average one. Also, one thing I just couldn't stop thinking about when I was in there was how much just one of these costs. Like, I want to figure out, like, Can I put one of these in my house? I have no room for maybe put it in my office showing like that
Unknown: you best believe that? Like major athletes have these in their houses? I can imagine that's like a thing.
Wes Bos: Yeah, I bet it's like, I don't know, like 15 grand or something like that. It's it's essentially you're getting a hot tub installed in your house. And then I think there's some extra equipment to filter it with salt in it. Yeah. Cool. Well, that's it. That was a kind of a cool experience. I know. We tweeted it out. And tons of people are say, oh, man, I've been meaning to try that for a long time. And I would highly recommend to go try it out and see what you think about it yourself. We'd love to hear what you what your experiences were on it. Yeah, I was, uh, I was just excited to get to do it. Now. Look forward to training again. So I hope you enjoyed this episode of The joyride funny I don't even listen to the Joe Rogan is that the Joe Rogan podcast or the Joe Rogan experience? Yeah, I I like MMA, and I like Joe Rogan as a commentator, but man, I can't get over on shows like that when they just like spout off some like pseudo psychological bs without like actually understanding it as somebody who's married to a doctor of psychology when people just start like talking out of their butt about stuff they don't know too much about. Yeah, irks me a little bit and hidden that that sort of like the prime place for that sort of thing on that show. But yeah, he he often does have actual doctors on Yeah, but it's definitely has a reputation of like, bro science where he just has this random person on that heats mushrooms or does this crazy things? like yeah, definitely we get we get the joke like every single person who's like, Oh, you do Joe Rogan? Yeah, I know. Yeah, I know. I know. I still let me try it. Yeah, I know for sure. So that was the bro science half hour on syntax FM. Let us know what other things you'd like us to report on as non doctors and we will do it. Yes, absolutely. Actually, I've mentioned this twice. We should get Courtney on here. Talk a little bit a psychology stuff. We should also get Kate on here. We should? I don't know. We still may be on the same show. They could just tell great stories about the two of us. That would be a lot of fun. Yeah, I asked my wife. She thinks that that would be pretty fun to do. Yeah, I think Courtney is dying to tell some ridiculous stories about me. So like, definitely, we should have like an episode with your wife because she probably has a lot to say, just on like psychology in general, and how that can relate to devs. And she's an actual doctor. Yeah. And then we should have like another one that like people submit questions for our wives and tell stories about us. That would be good.
Unknown: That'd be very good.
Wes Bos: Cool. All right. Well, that's I think we're this this hasty is getting a little tasty. So she'll end it here. Thanks so much for tuning in. We'll catch you on Wednesday. Please
Unknown: head on over to syntax.fm for a full archive of all of our shows. And don't forget to subscribe in your podcast player or drop a review if you like this show.