Announcer: Monday Monday Monday open wide dev fans yet ready to stuff your face with JavaScript CSS node module BBQ Tip Get workflow breakdancing soft skill web development hasty as crazy as tasty as web development treats coming in hot here is Sarah CUDA, Bob and Scott El Toro ski.
Scott Tolinski: Who Welcome to syntax. In this Monday hasty trick, we're going to be playing the top level domain game where we It's been a while since we've done this. So if you haven't heard a top level domain game episode, what we do basically is we pick a top level domain from a list and the other person needs to guess it will give you a better rundown on the rules right before we start, but let's get into it. My name is Scott Tolinksi. I'm a developer from Denver, Colorado, and with me, as always, is West boss. Hey, everybody. Hey, Wes. It's been a hectic morning for both of us. So this one is guaranteed to be a mess. And I'm excited about that. But you know, it won't be a mess as your website because you have a one of our sponsors, which is Log Rocket, and Log Rocket is going to be the service that allows you to visually see that mess so you can fix it. Now what is Log Rocket? Well, it is a visual tool that gives you a scrollable timeline of anytime an error, or an exception happened on your website, allowing you to have a pixel perfect replay trying to investigate some of these problems. Sometimes you become an investigator, but you can't see the problem. How do you how do you fix this? Well, this actually allows you to see the problem and see it happening in real time with the network request activity with the console log an error is no more emailing your clients saying, Hey, can you tell me what you did? When you click on this thing and what browser you're using, you'll get all of that with Log Rocket. So I don't over to Log rocket.com forward slash syntax, sign up, and you will get 14 days for free. All right, thank you Log Rocket. Now, if only Log Rocket could have saved me from last time, we played the TLD game, I really got worked. I think I had a bit of a comeback. But I think I ultimately lost out to the West was the the I'm trying to come up with a cool nickname for you. But I guess it just was better domain name master. Yeah, let's talk about how the points are. So we're gonna pick a TLD. A TLD is top level domain that means.com or whatever. And Scott has four, I have four. And the other person has to guess. Is it for a country? Or is it like a business or marketing domain name? So we'll pick one that we did before.af? Is that for a country? Or is that for a business that that can register that? The second one is what type of country business is it for? So you have to guess the country? Or you have to guess what sort of like what it's targeted at. The third thing is how much per year does it cost to register? And you may also say unregistered because there are some domain names out there that have been claimed by companies that cannot be registered by you. Like we just talked about this earlier. There's a dot Home Depot and a.tj Maxx and you can't just go register those those leaders are saved by the companies. And then finally, the last one is is Scott dot whatever and Scott, Aaron West dot whatever available so we're going to give you points for each of those. Whoever wins wins. Cool. So do you want to rock paper scissors for the first one? Whoever wins goes first.
Unknown: Okay.
Scott Tolinski: Do you do rock paper scissors throw? Rock Paper Scissors shoot although throw is way more Canadian Of course we do a shoot in America here of course. Yeah. Rock Paper Scissors throw. Okay. He I when I go deeper? Yeah. All right, my first domain that you have to guess is dot s d? Is that a country or a business? That SD? It is a country? Correct? What country or business is s? d?
Unknown: Ah
Scott Tolinski: El Salvador? No, it is Sudan. S. D is for Sudan. And I know, ss is for South Sudan. I just learned I made zero points. Now. Next one. How much does it cost to register a domain name? So I just typed in Scott, s d. So you have to tell me how much does it cost per year? Do we have to hand first got that SD to determine that or? Yeah, that's what I'm basing it off. Okay. Do we just always use Scott? Yeah, Keystone here. I'm gonna say it's 49
Unknown: incorrect is 100 Didn't $75 So come on. So you are this 175 minus 49. You are negative 126 points, man this point
Scott Tolinski: thing really gets me. All right is got DOD SD available? I'm gonna say, no, it is available, but all right, man. Yeah, man, I'm getting worked already. All right. I will say Wes that SD is also available. Oh good. It is available. Yay I finally did not lose points. So I I come out at the end of that round. Fantastic round for me I come out at negative 126. So that's great. Love it. All right, hit me with what you got. Okay. So my first one for you. This one's good. dot o n g
Unknown: o n g.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah. I must say Business is business plus five. So what type of business is it for? I am going to say it is a unregistered bubble. Um, so I'm going to head here but I'm gonna say the type of business is some some sort of like something something group. And this is going to be some sort of business that is unregistered. So I'm gonna say what type is business before? It's for a large corporation? It's for a large corporation. No, you're wrong. If it says private registration, does that mean it's unregistered trouble? I think so. Yes. Hmm. Because it doesn't have a price. I shouldn't have said this before. Oh,
Unknown: it does have a price. Okay, hold on. Yeah, maybe not. Well, like to try to go ahead and get it. So hold on. Let's let's go back to okay.
Scott Tolinski: It's available. Yes. Okay. Okay. What type of corporation is a for it is for a non government organization? Whoa,
Unknown: really? o n g? What does that mean? operation non government? organization? Non government? Maybe?
Yeah,
Scott Tolinski: that seems like oh, RG but yeah, interesting. Never heard of that one. How much does it cost to register for a year? I'm gonna say $19 $19. Rooney's? It is $49. Oh, no, that don't don't don't act like that's a big hit. That's not the last 30 points. So you're at negative 30 points here. And is Scott and Wes available? I'm gonna go ahead and say yes to both. And both are available. So you get 20 points, which means you come out negative 10. So the total at the end of round one is looking very similar to last time. I didn't watch 26 to negative 10. I'm really bad at these prices. That's definitely going to be my Achilles heel here.
Unknown: I've got an excellent for you. It is dot k OEL n. And
Scott Tolinski: that is going to be from a business. Yes. Oh, Cray. So what type of business is Colin? I saw this one. And I was like, What could that possibly be? It's actually not pronounce colon. It's going to be for coconut trees. Close, but not at all cologne. So it is a TLP friends made for businesses of the Cologne community as well as residents of the city itself. So cologne is a city in Germany. And I guess that's how they spell it in German. That was a good one. It was rough. That was a Hi, are you FF I got even rougher one coming. No. Okay, so pricing here pricing on this one. Um, I'm gonna go with $49. Again. That was pretty close. 29 Okay, okay. Okay, so I can do some math here. 4929, obviously, minus 20 points. So I'm at currently at negative 46 points. Well, I'm gonna say Western Scott are available. Both of them. They are deeming. I have survived this round, with no change in points. So I'm still at negative 126. That's fantastic. I'm very happy about that. Okay, well, I have a fun one for you. How about this one? Good. luck.co.ke Koch. Okay. I'm going to say this is a country. This is a country. You're trying to throw me that it's coke. It's not. It's I'm gonna say it's Kenya. Whoo. Whoo. Whoo. Yes, it's Kenya. Yes. Ah, dang, gotcha. How do you know this was Kenya. Because Kenya is like one of the only countries that starts with ke and I know there's a lot of countries that don't have a dot whatever. They have a.co dot there. The name like tokota jP.
Unknown: He's Japan. Hmm. Oh, he is salty folks. salty. How much is a cost to register a CEO? I'm gonna go with
Scott Tolinski: 39 bucks. 54 Oh, that's pretty close. That's not bad. Yeah, that's a win in my books. That's the closest we've been that's that's only negative 15 points for you. Is Scott in West available? I'm gonna say Scott is not and Wes is a you're gonna even out there big old whopping zero on those because oh, they're both available. So I'll have lost five points this round, which means not a lot of Kenyans name sky. Yes, apparently. Yeah. So the current point total is negative 126 to negative 15. West, you're basically hanging tight treading water. And I am plundering here although last round was was decently okay for me. Okay, so let's get into the next one. All right. What do you got for me.tr? Tr is going to be a country. Yep. So that's five five points from me. Now I got to keep these five points. That's tr. Man. My memory this morning is just not going really great. I'm scanning the globe in my brain and my visual brain space. I'm seeing the countries and projecting the map and onto a sphere instead of onto a plane. Is it for Trinidad? No. Turkey.
Unknown: Wow.
Scott Tolinski: That Trinidad was an okay guess. What is their TLD? TT I think Trinidad and Tobago? Yeah, it's not TT I had I had a concern that Tobago part of this. uh how much does it cost to read? Sure. They go with my, my girlfriend $49. Now that is it. Really? Yeah. Cool. Hey, zero album. That's the first one.
Unknown: Yeah, yeah. Now they should be bonus points. If you get it like exactly Next time, we'll do that.
Scott Tolinski: We should just wipe out my negative 126. That's what we got that tr available. Scott, that and when? I would say Scott is not available. Wes is available. Even though they're both not available? Both not available? Michael? Yeah. Okay, so I have ended this round with a big old zeros on the board. Negative six. That was a good round for me to not lose any more points. Okay. Wes. I have for you.is TIST eu. International Space travel. Maybe? I'm gonna say it's a business. Not a country.
Unknown: Bo,
Scott Tolinski: it's a country. Assemble. It is this damn bowl?
Unknown: Oh, she's
Scott Tolinski: actually city. Right? Yes, Kimball? Yeah. So that was interesting, because that's a new one. Like, that's not been around for a while, but it is a geographical one. That cologne could be either there because it was made for business purposes, but it also is geographical. Oh,
Unknown: but I you you you got points for that. I'll give it to you. All right. How much does it cost? So Richard is t? I'm going to go with Tony. nine bucks.
19. Oh,
Scott Tolinski: so negative 10. There?
Unknown: Is Scott just available? I'm gonna say Scott is not. And Wes is because it's kind of cool. iist? Yeah, that is kind of a cool. Yeah. Scott asked.
Scott Tolinski: They are both available. Wow, Scott is getting right. Okay, so that you have rounded out that round with a negative 10. So you were if we play this game for like 20 plus rounds, I might actually come out on top, the current score is negative 126 to negative 25. So doing pretty good West. I have got a good one for you. Oh no,
Unknown: this might be a little bit out of bounds, but I'm going for it. There's no rules against that. Out of bounds dot x n dash dash for five q one one c? x n dash dash
Scott Tolinski: for five q one, one c? It is a business. Correct? Okay. Is it like a debugging type of a top level domain like an actual technical use for this top level domain? No, it's not nothing technical about it. Nothing technical about it? No. exists. company's domain. Okay. I can pronounce it for you if you want. Yeah. dot Bagua seems like it's Chinese thing. Yeah. Okay. I'll give you that. Okay. Well, you mean like to get points for it? Give me give them five points for known it's Chinese donate name. Okay. Cuz I like I think we both know right now it's a that's the ASCII representation of a Chinese character domain name, though. Okay, so that's really interesting. ASCII characters. Okay, so Bhagwat What's it? What's it for though? So Bhagwat converts to gossip in Chinese Oh, man, there's no way I would ever know back. I watched a lot of Chinese films and they don't ever talk about gossip that much. So. Okay, so next question is how much does it cost? Is it? It's for gossip, and also money, then? I'm gonna say it's 29 bucks. It's like 100,324 90 324. is Scott Bagwell available? Yes. And what about Wes? Yes, they're both available. So if you got 700 bucks, congratulations to me. I got I got I got 20 points minus 20 plus points minus 100 295 points. So a negative scoring of this makes no sense. Because if you screw up one price, you're shot. You're totally shot. We talked about fixing this at the end of last time. And of course, the benefactor of this all did not want to listen to that. So let's see how many points I actually have right now. It is 20 minus 295. Minus 126. I'll come on I did so well. Negative 401. points. So congratulations to me. All right. Well try nail me a lot on I'm gonna be backwards here. Okay. It's not gonna happen. It is. dot r. e. i, t. o real estate investment trust. That's a business that's dedicated to real estate. And it's going to cost you Okay, well, you didn't even wait for me to say yeah,
Unknown: okay. I know. Okay, go ahead. Tell me if I'm right.
Scott Tolinski: You are. You are right, sir. Okay, how much does it cost to get a receipt? I'm gonna say 39 bucks. For Scott that rate. Is that true? I got it. No. Oh, Scott. That read cost 1499. No way, you know, negative 1460 here. Getting down to Bagwell level here.
Unknown: Wow.
I was so cocky because I knew it. Mm. box and West reice is available. Yes. Give me my 10 points there.
Scott Tolinski: So it's got that read. So yes, they're both available.
Unknown: Oh,
Scott Tolinski: you rounded up that round? Because you finish that round at negative 1440 plus negative 126 is Oh no, you don't have negative 126 That's me. 25 So you've finished that round with negative 1465. Oh, bro, big retro. I lost the game.
Unknown: Oh, it
Scott Tolinski: looks like that. That the scoreboard? Yes. Unfortunately. What's you've lost the game on the very last round of the game.
Unknown: Ah,
man, that was that was like, like overtime shootout where everyone thought it was fine. I had a huge lead. Even halfway through. I knew what it was and the price Are you sure $1,000 type it in?
Scott Tolinski: Do a verification check. 1500 bucks. Wow. So sorry. So sorry about that one. I was I was feeling charitable. I had a one all nice one lined up for you. And then you went back while on me. So I had to go bust out my, my bad. I thought for sure Bagwell would would come and kill it. Yep. All right. Well, most part did. That was good. So if you like that, let us know. Shoot us a tweet at syntax FM. Hopefully you learned a few new tlds today. Anything else to add? No, that was a lot of fun. And definitely I think we both had a rough morning. This was a nice little nice little kickoff to the day. So thanks. Thanks, Wes. I have a lot of fun. Beautiful. All right. I'll catch you later. Later. Peace. Head on over to syntax.fm for a full archive of all of our shows. And don't forget to subscribe in your podcast player or drop a review if you like this show.