Announcer: You're listening to syntax,
Unknown: the podcast with the tastiest web
development treats out there, strap yourself in and get ready to live ski
and West boss.
Wes Bos: Welcome to syntax. Today we're gonna be talking all about how to find freelance clients. This has been one of our most requested episodes in the last couple of months. People want very tangible examples of where do I find clients? And what are the tactics that I can use to convince them to hire me. So that's what we're gonna be doing today, we're gonna hopefully send you home with some tasty take home treats a doggie bag, if you today's episode is sponsored by Log Rocket, it's going to do all of your error and exception tracking as well as Stackbit, which is going to give you themes for your jam stack based website. We'll talk about them partway through the episode with me today, Scott klinsky. How you doing Mr. szalinski?
Scott Tolinski: Hey, I'm doing good. Doing super good, ready to go. Ready to get this week going. I'm starting to record my next series, which for all of you view fans is going to be right up your alley. So keep your eyes open for that. I'll probably do a little bit of announcements on that in the next week or so. But yeah, no, I'm just ready to go. I'm ready to kick things off a little bit, do some coding, do some recording and all that good stuff. And I'm ready to talk about freelance clients. So let's get into it.
Wes Bos: All right. So this question was from an Andreas trattner. And he says, I'm a back end developer with four years experience on working in Europe, and consider moving towards freelancing and contracting. However, I find it difficult to discover quality opportunities, any tips you can share on how to strategically get projects. So I thought this was an interesting one as well. You know, there's a lot of people out there who sort of look at the freelancer, the contractor, and we should say right now, a contractor and a freelancer are we refer to them as the same thing. Sometimes a contractor is someone who just does only one client for like six months, or as a freelancer tends to have many, but that could that could go either way. So we started to say them, I refer to myself as a contractor just because it sounds better. And I think you can get higher paying jobs as a contractor. But a freelancer does kind of the same thing. So there's a few categories that you can use to find freelance clients, we should say like, I was a contractor for, I don't know, 10 years or so. And Scott does has done quite a few different contract works as well over the years. So there's a few different categories, and we're gonna break them down into tangible things. I think the main thing that we have today is that there's no like secret trove of work. You think people when they ask for these things, they just want us to be like, Oh, well, let me tell you about this wicked website that nobody knows about. But there's thousands of amazing high paying clients, and you're going to get it. And that actually does exist. But you have to cultivate that little pond yourself.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, there's no hidden IRC room here where you have to enter a password and you get in and there all of a sudden, like here, here's your 10 best clients you've ever had. I think also the one of the misconceptions about some of this stuff, too, is that there's one way or one good way of doing it, there's not one good way or the best way to find freelance clients. There's several, and I'm by several, I mean tons of different ways that you can market yourself to get freelance clients. And these again, are, like I said, they're going to be varied in different sort of ways. So you can pick and choose, you can do all of them and cast a very wide net, or you can just do one of them and see if that works for you. But again, I think people often think of finding freelance clients, there's one way to do it. There's one way to get clients. No, there is so many different ways. And I know you and I have both experienced probably a lot of these different ways over the course of our careers already.
Wes Bos: Yeah, these are everything that we have here. We're going to go through relationships, display of expertise, visibility, maintaining relationships, and other tactics. So we've got all kinds of different things under each of these, but these are all things that I personally have done myself. I would say I was a extremely successful Freelancer when I was at it. I was charging. I think by the end of it, I was like 150 us an hour. I was booked solid. I had lots of people asking if I could do work for them. So I would say that was a successful career in being a contractor and these are the tips and tricks that I've used to actually find well paying clients
Scott Tolinski: Nice. Yeah, some good horn tune.
Unknown: haunting horn
Scott Tolinski: tooting your according to your own horn.
Wes Bos: I'll toot my own horn there. I did. Alright, so first of all relationships. I think this is probably the biggest one. Yeah, because the best paying gigs always come from relationships, the best paying stuff, the best, the most the funnest gigs that you get They're never posted to a job board or something like that, because they are all done through relationships. So I think that this is probably where you should spend most of your time. So relationships with people, but who, so let's break it down first person is other developers for when they need help. So this is where I initially got my start is that when I lived in Toronto, I got to know a lot of the other developers that were in the same scene as me. And I met them through meetups and conferences, and Twitter and IRC at the time now would probably be the different slack rooms, just making friends with people who have similar interests you. And by knowing other developers, often the developers are the first people who need to ask for help, because they say they're the ones that give time estimates for something. And if something can't get done in amount of time, or a developer's tied up and a client project needs to be done before they're available, they will often ask their developers, hey, do you know anybody who would have a similar skill set that would be able to do this project for us?
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, building these kind of relationships is going to be difficult. Actually, I should state that maybe most of these things might be difficult for you introverts out there, because a lot of these things will involve putting yourself out there in a way that's a little bit more socially forward than maybe you're comfortable with. And as a somewhat of an introvert myself, I'm not entirely in that camp. But I am pretty shy around people, sometimes, I have had a hard time just reaching out and just just talking to people like that, but you need to practice and you need to start a little bit here and there. And maybe it's easier for you to do so online via slack rooms, or something like that, but finding these other developers and other people in your community, or maybe Hey, it's the person you're sitting next to at some sort of event, and just trying to strike up a conversation without the intent of even building a relationship there. But just with the intent of practicing talking to people, because to build these kind of relationships, you do need to work at it a little bit, especially via, you know, your your personal skills there. And those skills are something that sure enough, you might think I'm an introvert, I can't do it. No, you need to just practice some of that stuff a little bit. And again, I don't think anybody is going to follow you. If you're shy, talking about work. It's not about that. It's more about your skill, and what they know you can do and know you can get the work done. One of these nice little tips I have here is if you have a friend who's friends with somebody who you know gets a lot of work, right? Maybe you don't get any any work. Maybe your friend themselves has a full time job, but they have a buddy who's crushing it in the freelance game, they have a ton of clients. But you could ask your friend, hey, is it you know, I know your friend has a lot of friends, or a lot of clients, is there any way you could put me in touch with them? And I could just put myself in front of them to say, Hey, I'm looking for work? And potentially, could you toss me some of your Yeah, the stuff you don't want to do?
Wes Bos: That was huge for me when I got up and running. And when I was too busy, it was hard for me to find reputable people who I could recommend clients to because I would get all these emails and I could only do a certain amount or sometimes there wasn't a good overlap between the type of work that needed to be done. And I would say no, sorry. And then the immediate question after that would be okay, who can I talk to? And then it's like, oh, that like, this is one of my most hated things. Yeah, people always make me play like like a matchmaker hiring manager. Yeah, I have to play matchmaker with these people and introduce, and it takes up a lot of time, and you're putting yourself out there. And I've had people come back and say, Hey, this person you recommended, totally dropped the ball, and then no good or like, what happened to your buddy? And if you can be super reliable and good at what you do, people are happy to have like a list of like two or three people to say, Hey, I can't do it, but contact these people. Yeah. One other tip I have here is I mentioned conferences. And as a freelancer conferences are sometimes just off the table, because they're expensive as hundreds and hundreds of dollars to buy a ticket, you have to get a often get a flight and things like that. And you could be out and a couple grand before you're done, you're done the conference, and that maybe just isn't in the cards for a lot of freelancers. But I know what a lot of people do is they volunteer to get in at conferences. So often conferences will pay for your conference ticket or pay for your hotel and your conference ticket or depending on what kind of conference it is. And that's great, because all you have to do is sometimes it's introducing people on stage, sometimes it's just holding up the 30 minute, 30 minutes, 20 minutes left, to each of the speakers. Sometimes it's doing the registration desk and by having those jobs, you get to know the like the really important people, the speakers at the conferences much better than than just the attendees is often people just hanging out in the speaker room with me who are volunteers and you get to know them. So I think like I know smashing cough does that I know fitc here in Toronto will often do that. And I think that's a great way to get in because you get to meet hundreds of people in the industry for free, and you also get to attend the conference to for free. So I think that's a good option.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, great option. And we'll get into that a little bit later in the episode. But Ted, typically people who are that visible, are usually getting somewhat amount of requests for work even without asking for them. So being around or experiencing or just being able to connect with those types of people is going to be hugely beneficial to you. Now, the next one we want to get into is going to be more of these people who are working inside of other companies. So we have two examples here, which will be project managers and office managers, typically working for both companies that have contract work available, as well as maybe agencies that have a per project freelance basis stuff available as well, I've experienced both of these, both working for agencies as well as companies who are hiring on people for short term time or project based stuff. And typically, when you have a project and you need extra help on it, because so many times we run into deadlines that they need an extra hand here or there, you know, these people who are managing a project, or even better the people who are in charge of the overall project, they're going to flip through their their Rolodex, for those of you young uns who don't know a Rolodex is they're gonna flip through their their virtual Rolodex, so to say, and they're gonna, you're gonna pick the people that are visible in their brains so that people they remember reaching out to them are the people that you know, that are going to be able to do the work. And they're going to hire on these people for contract or freelance work
Wes Bos: of the office manager, one I found particularly helpful, because the average manager, if you don't know is just the person that manages the office, they sort of do everything around the office. And they often know absolutely, everybody. Yeah, because that's their job. They're usually the first point of contact at a specific office, they know what's going on with all the different projects and whatnot. And they often move into other roles, once they've been there for a certain amount of time. And by getting to know those people, those people are always at meetups, they're usually the people welcoming, or they're usually the person Well, I like doing like, Hey, everybody, thanks for coming out to this meetup. And this is our office, by the way, we're hiring that's often a an office manager, who is sort of facilitating these meetups, and if you can get to know them and say, hey, look, I'm a freelancer, if anything ever comes up, let me know, I'll shoot you an email or whatever. They are very well connected people to know at a specific company.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, absolutely. And even, you know, to add on to the list of this developers at this company, I mean, we talked about developers, the other developers in the section above, but developers who are working in an agency or a place like this, we often had situations where we needed extra hands on deck. And even if the office managers or project managers didn't know, somebody, they usually came to us and said, Who do you think would be perfect for this? And oftentimes, we would say, Oh, hey, I met this, this person at a meet up one time, who said they had the ability to do this. And this is exactly what we need. Let's bring them up, see if they can do it. So definitely reaching out to people who work in these things. Now, you might be wondering, Well, how do I get in contact with some of these people, I found, personally, the best way that we always hired out for freelancers or anything like that was contacts through people that used to work with us. So if we used to work at some place, and we knew that somebody had access or knowledge of this code base already, we would reach out to them and say, Hey, do you have any freelance bandwidth you can take this on. So make sure to keep in contact with some of your older employers, if you're on good terms with them. And you could potentially get tossed some freelance work that way, or even just let your previous employer know that you're looking for freelance work, because they might keep you in mind next time they're looking. Next up we
Wes Bos: have I'm going to group these together is entrepreneurs and venture capitalists. This is where I got a lot of my early work was just going to demo camps. This is where different entrepreneurs will often like pitch their their startup ideas, Facebook marketing groups, I'm part of a couple for email marketing. And there's always people asking, Who can I hire to help me wire this thing up? Or who can I help? Who can I hire to build a custom integration with getting data from this thing to this and because these marketers are often just stringing things together with Zapier, and sooner or later, they're gonna realize like, oh, that this doesn't work as well as I had hoped. I need to hire somebody to build a custom UI or a custom integration, something like that. So like getting outside of just the developer, designer, marketer world and getting out into the entrepreneur world. Also, the entrepreneurs are fairly well connected, because that's part of their job is just having coffee with people and whatnot. I can tell you that I've had a couple situations in my life where I was offered like a part of a company. What's the one thing about entrepreneurs they'll want to pay you and they'll just want to give you part of a company and those companies sold for millions of dollars and I kicked myself for not actually taking it but hindsight is 2020 I guess
Scott Tolinski: yeah, but I'm no flipside of that Eric, who who's a dev for level up, he worked for a company for like half a year to a year. And that was just like, they kept dangling that equity in front of him like, like, we're giving you more equity. And then sure enough, the company was never worth anything in the first place. So yeah, you know, like, totally, you know, lost a ton of money on that one. And, you know, just just pay me, you could just pay me How about that.
Wes Bos: The other one is venture capitalists. So these are the people who actually invest the money into these early stage startups. And I've worked with, I think, three different VC companies. And these are usually just a couple people who have some, some money to invest. And they have dozens of companies under their belt that they've given 10,000 to $100,000 of their money to start up a company. And the the smaller VC firms are usually very involved in the initial product development. And because of that, they will often be talking to the founders and say, okay, you you need to build this specific feature. I know, Wes, I think he would be able to help us out in that specific use case. So yeah, how do you get introduced to these people, they're hard people to get in touch with, obviously, lots of people want to talk to them. I found that like, demo camps introductions was my big one where I was working with one of the companies, I was in their office, and then I actually met their, their, their VC people. And then from there, they introduced me to other VC people. And that's the thing with these relationships is like once you're in, and once you have shown yourself to be good at what you do, then the recommendations just start flowing from from there on out.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, and I think you do need a bit of reputation as being reliable at that point. Because Yeah, these people aren't going to recommend somebody who they it's like a total unknown for them. So whether or not you can prove it via friends of a friend or relationships or straight up just based on your previous work examples or things like that, this one's gonna be tough if you don't already have any prior work, because they're gonna want to see some stuff.
Wes Bos: This is funny, I'm trying to turn to move into a sponsor here. And we're talking about Stackbit, which is a new company that provides themes. And we actually met ohad, who was an investor in Stackbit, at a conference and and because, like the good investors that will actually go to the trade, like, they'll go to a tech conference just to meet the right people. Because as much as we want to meet these, like VC people to do work for them or to get funding, they want to meet the smart developers that can help bring their product to fruition. So we just met randomly at jamstack cough. And he said, Oh, I would love to sponsor the podcast. So that's just another perfect example of, of how to meet these specific people. So what is Stackbit? Stackbit is going to give you themes for your jam stack based website, a jam stack is JavaScript API's and markup these are these static sites that we've been talking about a lot lately. And it's kind of cool, because instead of just providing a a theme, for one specific one, they're attempting to make these themes that will work with all of the different static site generators, like yeah, Gatsby and Hugo and Jekyll. And all the different headless CMS is that are out there. And it's pretty cool. They are adding new CMS and new static site generators on every single sprint. And they want syntax listeners to beta test it. So if you want to get in early, go to stackbit.com, forward slash syntax FM, and you're going to get in early with Stackbit and be able to try it out. This is pretty interesting. The theme world and I think even as a developer, the theme world sort of just blew up when with with WordPress, and I'm very curious to see if that happens again, in the jamstack area as well. So check it out. stackbit.com forward slash syntax FM Thanks so much to Stackbit for sponsoring. Nice.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, thank you. I think that's such a cool space. I'm really excited to Yeah, how Stackbit evolved here. Cool. So let's get into the next one. Which is certainly how I think we've both experienced a lot of growth and our freelance sort of contacts coming in, which is the display of expertise, right? This is showing the world that you know, things I know stuff. So I'm gonna I'm gonna make sure that people know I know stuff. So therefore, people are going to come to me, so that I can do
Wes Bos: like, you know, stuff, right? Yes.
Scott Tolinski: Okay, make it you got to wear the T shirt that says, you know, my other car is a div or something. I just made that up on the spot. How about that display of expertise, okay, so this is one of those ones where again, you want to make yourself look like you know, stuff. Because if people think you know, stuff, like we just said, you're gonna get gigs and that's just as simple as it is. People are gonna come to you, they're gonna, they're gonna email you, they're going to find you any way possible. They're going to make sure that they reach out to the person that they say When they think of JavaScript, when I think of JavaScript, I think about Wes. So if Wes, well, he probably, you know, can do some work for me. And if he can't, maybe he knows somebody who can do some work for me. So they're going to reach out that way. And I'm sure you've experienced that as well.
Wes Bos: Yeah, absolutely. The way I did this, mostly was speaking at local meetups. So I would work on something fun, like I would make a webcam demo. And then I would reach out to local meetups, or they would come to me and say, Hey, do you want to speak about it meetups are always looking for people always speak Yeah. And you get yourself in front of 1525, sometimes even more local developers, and you say, Hey, I made this thing. Also, I'm a freelance consultant, if anyone would like to work with me, I'd love to hear from you just drop in a little line like that, that puts something in their in their mind and says, oh, something like that is going to happen. Or I know of West to do that thing. Another thing I did was, I would volunteer on weekends, once every I don't know, three or four months. And I would teach a workshop for ladies learning code, which is now Canada learning code. And there's tons of these all around the world. And it was amazing. It was just a huge treasure trove of project managers, marketers, people who worked in the industry. But were not coders themselves. And were interested in either becoming a coder or they just want to know a little bit more about the technical side of their business. And I got tons and tons of work from that, just because if you stand up there and teach a workshop for eight hours, you probably know what you're talking about. And I was specifically teaching a WordPress workshop. So people would come that wanted to learn WordPress that likely had WordPress in their company, and needed to maybe hire somebody for WordPress, and it was like, perfectly aligned. And it's amazing, because you're helping this amazing cause at one time. And also, it's just extremely beneficial for your business to run these these workshops. So yeah, reach out to your local, not for profit that does these coding things, because I think you can, you can get a lot from there.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, and these are again, just like some of the other things that we were talking about with putting yourself out there, it takes a lot to put yourself out there to go ahead and speak in front of people in general. So speaking in front of a meetup, in my opinion, is a great practice way for getting in front of larger and larger audiences. Because typically, some of these meetups, I think the largest meetups I've ever been to, it's like maximum of like 150 200 people. And that's a huge meetup. Most meetups are pretty small, like upwards of, you know, 20 to 50, some people. So that's a pretty low stakes, if you put yourself out there and talk about something that you know, about for 15 2030 minutes. That's not that that's not that hard. And one of those things is if you sign up for it, you sign up for it, get just do it, you put yourself out there, it's gonna pay off, it's absolutely going to pay off. So it's a good way to practice this thing. And speaking at like you said, workshops, workshops, is a bigger step, conferences is a bigger step. But in the end up is a nice little small step, and it's gonna put you out there a little bit. Next one is going to be for those of you who might not feel super comfortable putting yourselves out there and that way, but you are confident in your code skills, which is going to be working on open source. Now there is a ton of open source projects that are always looking for help, you can put yourself out there and work on these things, you'll often get listed as a contributor, your little face will be on the repo, if they're, if they're wanting to advertise who's working on the project, which a lot of projects do. So you'll want to make yourself aware that you're working on this stuff, again, you This doesn't require any social standing up in front of people doing those sort of things, recording your voice or anything like that. It's simply working on code. So open source projects is a great way to put your name on something and put yourself out there as an expert.
Wes Bos: Yeah. And I think even like this doesn't mean you're going to come out with a library that's going to be wildly successful. Now it might be like the Lewis who works on my course platform, doing react and node and all that. I met him in the next jazz slack chat room because he was helping me try to figure out my own problems. And I was just like, Hey, you seem to be smart work for me. And not like like he didn't create next jass. He didn't write some amazing blog posts for didn't have a YouTube he was just like extremely helpful and knowledgeable and was able to display the expertise where I thought like, wow, this is the type of person that I need to help me out. So don't think that you need to make your own open source frameworks. It might just be helping posting guides, updating documentation, that sort of thing will get noticed base. People like me and Scott, who sometimes want to just hire someone who is knowledgeable. We're not necessarily looking for someone who is a rock star and super well known because they're probably super booked up or they're probably extremely expensive. We want to find these little hidden nuggets of people who are extremely smart and and are able to help you.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, absolutely. Another good way that you can put yourself out there is the way that I did initially, which is starting a YouTube channel. And this one does require a little bit of overhead in terms of having equipment to make it worthwhile. But I started recording content simply just to help people out. And let me tell you level up tutorials, the YouTube channel, the fact that it had such a large visibility, not only got me more freelance gigs, but it also got me some really excellent contract gigs. And full time gigs. Anytime I was in a job interview, seriously, I just pull up my YouTube channel and watch the interview ORS jaw drop, as you know, 100,000 followers on YouTube. Oh, wow. So this is a big one. And you know, there's also the ability maybe if you want to start a podcast, I know everyone's starting a podcast, there's like 10 million podcasts. But putting yourself out there. And that sort of the way away, you're actually giving people value is going to make yourself so much more visible. And it's going to again, up that flow of new clients.
Wes Bos: Another kind of interesting way, this is more if you want to get the the high end clients, I think of somebody like Harry Roberts, who's CSS wizardry, CSS wizardry, on on Twitter, and he offers these like CSS performance reviews, where he was tweeting the other day, how he like helped the performance of his website was crashing and how he fixed it. And that sort of informal performance review just on Twitter or, and I think he also just makes these actual performance reviews for companies, sometimes they allow them put them online, that's probably a little bit later on in your career. But that's the kind of thing that you can offer, whether it's performance reviews, or accessibility reviews, or I would often do like a WordPress PageSpeed reviews where people would say like, WordPress takes 45 seconds to load the homepage, like, what can you do? And I would say, okay, like, Look, I can, I can come up with just like a, like a bullet list of things you could do, or I can go in and fix it myself. Or often people will email me and say like, hey, Wes, can we just like, pay you for two hours of your time you we can tell you how we're going to approach building our application. And just let us know what you think and things like that. That's just a great way to position yourself where these these huge companies are no problem paying a couple hundred dollars an hour for this type of thing when you are such an expert in this one specific very small area.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah. And then another way to if you're, if you're not wanting to put yourself out there visually, audio, whatever you can blog, blogging is just as good as a lot of these things. And you get the added benefit of your blog showing up in Google somebody's searching for, oh, I really can't do this thing on WordPress. I've been struggling with it for hours. Let me Google it. Okay, I found a blog post telling me how to do it. But I still don't understand it. So you know what I'm gonna do? I'm gonna go ahead and email that contact that's in the contact form of that blog and say, Hey, you, I'm trying to do this thing. Can you just do it for me? How much would that cost?
Wes Bos: Yeah, I can't tell you how many times I've met emails, people being like, Look, I'm at the end of my rope right now. I'm ready to do it. Can I just hire you for an hour, and you can come in and fix this sort of thing? Yeah, I kind of wish that I did that more. When I ran upon issues, where it was a quick little code fix. I just throw that up on my blog. I think maybe maybe that should be my my goal for this year, something like that is just start posting smaller little things on my blog like that blog post doesn't need to be this huge thing. It could just be six lines of code. I ran into this today, it was a really easy fix. I have here this,
Scott Tolinski: I had I hired somebody off the meteor forum, because I could only get SSR. Working with art, I get to two of the three things working SSR data fetching and code splitting. with Meteor and Apollo in react, I could only get two of them working. And I was like, why can't I get all three of these working. And this guy came in and did it for me. He spent an hour doing it. I paid him 200 bucks. It was the best 200 bucks I ever spent. Because seriously, I had spent so many hours plugging into that. And I wouldn't have figured out the answer. He actually ended up having to write his own patched version of react loadable to get it to work, but it was like, thank you, thank you so much, that that is exactly what I needed. And that's exactly the type of person who is going to find you in those type of situations.
Wes Bos: Next one, I think this is along with relationships, I think the visibility, and this kind of goes into the last one of displaying your expertise as well if visibility is the most important, because if people don't know that they can hire you. Or if people think that maybe you're out of their league for a specific thing, that's that's not a good spot to be in. So one thing that I always aggressively sort of battled against was being the guy who was always too busy, because no one wants to hire the guy who's too busy, who barely has time for you. Someone wants to hire someone who's going who's willing to put in the time. So letting everybody know what it is that you do and that you have availability is extremely important in that way. might just be as simple as saying, Hey, I have availability. Yeah. And I'm looking to, like, it's such a simple thing. But most people forget to do it, where they're like, I'm writing all these blog posts, and I'm putting off all these like mixed signals and things like that, where you maybe just should straight up tell people. This is this is what I'm looking for. So how do you do that? I always told my students a big one is just like posting on Instagram, posting on Facebook, what it is that you're doing, whether that's a silly cup of coffee at a coffee shop, hashtag be your own boss, hashtag work for yourself. Hashtag remote life, as stupid as those are. What that does is it lets your extended network know, oh, there's code on the screen. That's what they do. They write code. They work for themselves, because at some point, your mom's uncle's friends, cousins, birds, dogs nephew is going to be running a company and say, I need to hire someone. Does anyone know someone? And I guarantee you I did this once I was teaching. I was teaching freelance at hacker you and I just searched in my search to my Facebook for like, hey, Wes, long time no talk, or, hey, Wes, are you available for hire, and I showed them like 15 different people who I hadn't talked to in like eight years. But then they said they always they see everything I'm posting. And they knew that they could reach out to me and say, Hey, are you available for hire, and I got some really, really good jobs of like, third or fourth connections through referrals like that.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, it's huge in posts on every social network posted on LinkedIn posted on Facebook posted on Twitter, one of the cool things that I see a lot is when you know, visible developers with a lot of followers will retweet somebody saying that they need work. And then I'm sure they get a lot of work from those things. Because sometimes these things get passed around and really get put in front of a lot of eyes, you have to be the one to share to tweet it, initially, people aren't going to do it for you, you need to say, Hey, I'm available, I want to cast this big, wide net, and I want to catch some fish darnit. So we talked about this, a lot of these things with visibility, also go sort of hand in hand with the display of expertise. Because if you are displaying your knowledge, typically you're putting yourself out there, right? You're putting yourself out there somewhere that you're visible, whether that is blogging, right, whether that is YouTube videos, or anything like that, you're actually making yourself available. Now the difference between just displaying your expertise, and making yourself visible in terms of picking a freelance client is the simple fact that you need to state very clearly, hey, I'm looking for freelance clients. If you want to work with me, please hit me up some of my favorite podcasts, I listen to our personal finance podcast, and a lot of them they'll be like, well, we are money managers. And if you need a money manager, well give us a call. And so they've already displayed their expertise. By having a podcast by teaching you something, they've already put themselves out there and made it visible by being you know, a popular podcast. And then they're saying, Hey, I'm available for work. So come hire me. And I'm sure these people get swamped with stuff based on the levels of potential popularity, but just the met the fact that they're saying that they're available,
Wes Bos: one of my favorite podcasts as well. It's called Canadian couch potato, where the entire podcast is about showing you how you can invest yourself. His entire mantra is how showing you how to do it yourself. And then they also say, oh, by the way, we can do this for you, too, if you want to their entire business model. Yeah. And it's amazing. Like, give it away for free show people that you're an expert, and you clearly know what you're doing. And then there's a small percentage of people who don't want to do it themselves and are gonna go off and want to hire you. So that visibility one is super important. I know it doesn't come easy to a lot of people. For me, I just can't stop myself from posting stuff online. So it's just like second nature. But for some people, they really have to say like, oh, like, Okay, get the coffee cup, put it beside the laptop. You know, like, gotta go order some stickers from red bubble to make it look like I'm an elite hacker. So I like that,
Scott Tolinski: you know, elite hacker sticker and just put it right on there today. Elite hacker sweatshirt.
Wes Bos: But you just got to get that new developer starter pack of the stickers with a cup of coffee. What else? The developer coffee shop starter pack. cobalt to VS code theme.
Scott Tolinski: Yes. Yes. All of it. The syntax podcast subscription that there we go.
Wes Bos: That's true. If you're listening to us right now, take a picture of you listen to the syntax podcast and post it on Instagram. Hashtag dev starter kit dev started. Hashtag dev starter kit and tag me. I'm at Wes Bos and tag Scott. He's stilinski sto l i n s k I
Scott Tolinski: nailed it that's on the like I said sto Well, I am this guy. I just bought that domain that the other day. I'm pretty psyched about it as Husky dev because my current domain Scott to Lynskey that has three T's in the middle, and that always throws people off. So I'm excited to try to get rid of that it's super annoying. Another one of these ways you can make yourself more visible is inside of slack channels. I have a Slack channel, Wes has a Slack channel for people who've purchased his stuff. And I always let me say I always prioritize people in my Slack channel over other people, and I get a lot of requests for freelance work. So if you're in my Slack channel, you're giving people advice you're showing up there, I post some work in there. And if I know you can do it, I'm always reaching out to those people first, because I know those people are going to do a good job, or I have some sort of more personal connection to them. They're not just some randoms or something like that. These are people I feel like I know, because I've been talking to for a while now. So like candles are a great way to make yourself visible. And there's a lot of slack channels. I know there's a even in Denver here, there's one called Denver devs. And there's people posting jobs and stuff there all the time or need for work or stuff like that. So find these slack channels and show up there and just make yourself visible.
Wes Bos: Yeah, that's I get job postings in my Am I react or my node node all the time, just because it's kind of cool, because people have taken my courses are in there. And they'll be able to hire people who they know have taken like the same course that they've taken. So they're sort of on the same page with their their skill level and how they approach things. It's pretty neat to see that super neat. You know, what else is neat, Scott?
Scott Tolinski: Ah, my desk, my desk is super neat right? Now, you cleaned it off this morning. No, I know, it's super neat is my error log. Why? Because I use Log Rocket. Log Rocket is an excellent service that allows you to better find out how your bugs happen. And I use Log Rocket all the time when my standard ways of sort of trying to solve bugs just won't work. Because Log Rocket gives me a session replay. It's a video of a pixel perfect replay of what the user saw when the error happened. And let me tell you, this thing is so so useful, because Sure, error logs are great. And all those things where you can see what's happening with a bug, that's all great. But when you have an actual video showing you how to do it, and what happened, it totally takes all of the guesswork out of it, then you can go try it, reproduce it yourself, you can see the error log, you can see the network activity, maybe they hit some sort of weird network bug, you can see all of the stuff. Not only that, but you can even see the Redux store. And it integrates with all of the things you know and love, such as react Angular, just normal JavaScript, Ember view, j s, and it integrates with all of the bug tracking tools which you use already. Things like century bugsnag, robar, New Relic, JIRA, Zendesk, intercom, drift, Salesforce, Trello, GitHub, the list goes on and on. So Log Rocket is such a cool product. And we're so happy for them to sponsor because it's so incredibly useful. So check out Log Rocket at Log rocket.com, forward slash syntax, sign up and get 14 days for free, you're going to want to do that proof is in the pudding, check it out at Log rocket.com. Cool. So let's get into the next section here, which is going to be other tactics. And this is going to be other tactics to gain both visibility, notoriety, as well as put yourself in front of people who are going to be able to get you those gigs.
Wes Bos: Yeah, so the first one here is SEO search engine optimization. When my wife was a print designer, or graphic designer, we live in Toronto, I built her website, and I built it in very clean HTML. And I'm not sure exactly what I did. But she came up number one, when you googled Toronto, graphic designer, nice, and she got tons of people emailing her saying, Hey, I'm looking to hire someone. Because that in a lot of cases, that's the first thing someone will do, let's just type in Toronto graphic designer. So she got some pretty good leads out of there. But I will say, I don't even know if it was all that worth it. Because she got a lot of riffraff contacting her people that had no idea about the industry. People had no idea how much things cost, she spent a lot of time on phone calls, where it ended up to be just like people like oh, no, I you who we have to pay you. And it was really interesting, because we got a lot of emails from people being like, how did you get her number one for Toronto graphic designer, and then we got a lot of emails from just random people that probably shouldn't have been contacting her in general. So that's one way. Also specific technologies. I've gotten a lot of work. I just used to keyword stuff my my page, I would just list off every tech I ever worked with. And the reason why is because I remember having jQuery UI on my website, and I got a really good well paying job because he said they had me and say, Hey, I see you work with jQuery UI. Our thing is built on jQuery UI. And we need some help working on it and just to the person who's hiring you, especially if they're not technical. Seeing the exact technology that they work on in your list of skills or in what they've googled for is really important because it puts them at ease. They have no idea that it's just JavaScript at the end of the And you could probably pick it up, they much rather hire someone who has that exact skill.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, I think some of these, these other tactics here are going to land us into territory, where the work might not always be amazing that's coming in or the potential work. So some of these things, you do need to be decently good as screening, which is the problem, because a lot of these tactics are going to be coming in handy when you are just starting out, and you don't maybe have the network, right, because once you have the network, you get it all through referrals. But when you don't have that network, you try things like SEO, and Craigslist, which believe it or not, I have gotten some decent work off of Craigslist. But to be honest, I've also gotten so many headaches off of Craigslist, maybe most of the time, I've had a headache with a client, it's been off Craigslist when I was just starting out. So it's almost like a paradox, because Craigslist is is a decent place to find good work when you're just starting out. Because you don't have that network, you can reach out to people directly and try to win projects that way. But you need a huge training in LA want to say bullshit detection, and just like detection of who's a bad client. And unfortunately, you might not get that until you have the experience. So you know, for the most part, you'd stay away from Craigslist, and I would almost always recommend to stay away from it that said, Yeah, I have gotten some decent gains from it, I one time I got a gig that I designed a logo, and the logo ended up on the side of a building, and that logo is still there and a 3d logo. And I did their website, and it was a great client for many years of mine that I got from Craigslist. And to be honest, though, for every one of those you get, you know, maybe 20 off of clients, but you have to be able to look through that and and know who doesn't have the money, who doesn't have the the idea of what to do. And with those clients, I might almost always veer on the side of over not overcharging them, but charging them a lot. Because if somebody is willing to put up the cash, then you know, they're probably a better client than if they're not willing. Yeah,
Wes Bos: yeah, totally. It's funny the The more you charge, the better the clients get, which it seems like it Yeah, the more you charge, the harder it should be is, the more you charge, the easier it should be. But you can't just charge more. And all those problems are gone, you have to sort of go through the whole, all the steps that we've talked about going through here. Other things, putting a phone number up on your website works. So well. I can't tell you how many, how many things I got where sometimes you get these a type personality people who own these businesses, and they just want to pick the phone up and just say, Hey, can you do a website? And if you can say, hey, yeah, for sure. And we can talk about it, let's grab a coffee. And I realize, again, that's probably a very extroverted thing to do. But if you can get past that initial where they probably emailed 15 people, you're the only one that picked up the phone, you go to the top of the list, you schedule call you schedule coffee right away with that person, there's a good chance that you're actually going to be able to get that. So almost no one ever calls me, I have my phone number up on all of my course websites. And maybe once every three or four weeks, I get a call. Yeah, that's six or seven minutes long, right? Every now and then you get somebody who calls me in the middle of night with a problem with their code. And that's to be expected if you put your phone number up online, but it's not the scary thing that I think most people think it is. And I think it can benefit you more than it's gonna detriment you.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, absolutely. Another place you can look for work is things like Upwork, or other job boards. Now, these are going to be tough, because you're going to be bidding against people. And chances are, the work is not going to be super well. It's not going to be super worth it. But if you're just looking for experience and portfolio stuff, you can bid against people on up work, it's gonna be tough, and you're probably not going to get a ton of work, but it exists. And there is good people fighting for good work and up up work every single day. So definitely check out those kind of places. I think most of the people who post on Upwork are serious. I haven't experienced Upwork as a freelancer myself only as somebody looking for work. But it definitely is the place is the place. Yeah, last time
Wes Bos: we talked about Upwork I got I got a bunch of tweets from people saying like, I make my entire living off of Upwork. So I definitely think that you can you can do that. But always feels weird to me relying you're trying to like build your own business and work for yourself. But then you have this crutch of like this outside company that you rely on for all your work like in my world. And this goes for everything, whether it's blogging on medium, or like building your entire business on another platform. It's not if the rug will get pulled, it's when the rug will get pulled. And then all sudden you have this big YouTube gate or people getting mad at medium or being like, it's not fair, my views are going down or they're taking a bigger cut and I have to feed my family and yes, if you build your business upon somebody else's business, at some point, you're going to get cut. So I always think it's much better to just circumvent these things. It might be easier at first but circumvent them, build your own Empire and then no one can really take that away from you.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, absolutely. And again, if you're going to do some work on Upwork, maybe you can sort of move it out of Upwork. or maintain that network in a way, that's like moving it off of there. Don't always try to keep it on there. Because again, you're then you're you're tied to that platform and yourself to a platform isn't, as you mentioned, a great idea. Now, another one is local business listings. These are sort of maybe like an older school way of doing things. But I found even there's like a lot of local business listings online. Or you can just list yourself as like, here's a provider that's in Denver, who's a freelancer. So look for that stuff. Because again, it's going to come up on SEO, and you're gonna have people who find that and just think that, hey, this is the way to go about it and going contact you there. So I don't think these are like maybe amazing ways. I've been on several local business listings that I've never gotten hits from them at all. But you never know, again, cast a wide, wide net. And there's always the old fashioned mode of printing up some business cards and going in nailing them to some walls at some local places, coffee shops or breakfast places there, wherever you visit. Just make yourself visible, put yourself out there.
Wes Bos: There's this whole industry of businesses that are totally offline and they're all built on. Like I just think of like I've got friends that parents run mulch companies, and they they're just a mulch guy in the town and you need them or like there's like a Bait and Tackle spot near my brother in law's called rotten Ronnie's and rotten Ronnie's got, like you need. If you need any bait, you go to end like there's all these businesses that have been running like that forever. And at a certain point, they're going to realize, okay, we need some sort of online presence, we need an online ordering. because someone's going to come around and make a better a better experience for doing it online. Right. And these people who are there, they're running very successful businesses. I know, I've plenty of friends who have these have parents that have these like old businesses that have don't even have a website or just have a crappy little website. And they're millionaires. And at certain point, they're going to need some sort of online presence because it it's all moving that way. And I think going to I don't even know what they are. But just like Local Business Bureau, what are they called? Like? You have like these luncheons and these breakfasts, and
Scott Tolinski: oh, yeah, we're tying groups there.
Wes Bos: Yeah, networking groups and things like that. Like, that's, it's a very old way of business. But I don't write off old as bad. Yeah, that's where a lot of the money is.
Scott Tolinski: Definitely, definitely. Lastly, let's get into a little bit of maintaining relationships. Because oftentimes, we do work for a client, right, we've done the work, the work went, well, we've maybe gotten a referral from that client, or maybe we've never heard from them, and we don't reach out to them again. And that's missing an opportunity. Because again, we want to cast a really wide net here. And if that person knows somebody who needs something they might think of you. But they also might not think of you if you haven't talked to them in a year or two years or something like that. I have a perfect example of this, our realtor, who he's an amazing guy, he did such amazing work for us. And he's just relentless. He is incredible at maintaining relationships. Every few months, I'm thinking like every four months or so we get a handwritten letter from him in the mail. That's like a card and you open it up, and there's a Starbucks gift card in there. And it says, What is it saying like referrals are the best way that you can help me out or something like that, he makes it very clear that he's looking for referrals hard
Wes Bos: ask,
Scott Tolinski: it's a hard ask. And he does it really nicely, you feel like, oh, he gave me a Starbucks gift card, he's just checking in, he says something about like, I can't wait to see you and your family. Again, if you know of anybody who's looking, just reach out. And let me tell you if we ever need or if anyone we know ever needs a realtor. He's the first person we think of every single time, we don't ever even consider telling them to do anything else. Because we have such a great experience. And now I wouldn't necessarily say that for the realtor that we had in Michigan, because she never reached out. And you know, she was just okay, she was fine. But more importantly, she didn't nurture that relationship in a way after the fact that we constantly think of her. And in addition to that, if we give him a referral, he gives us $100 gift card to like the fanciest steak restaurant in Denver. And so every day, he's just so good at maintaining that relationship and making us think of him. It's just so thoughtful. So having this in your back pocket as a way to maintain relationships, what I would do is maybe even like put on a timer, like every few months or so to reach out to certain contacts. And there's apps that will do this for you. I'm not I can't think of them off the top of my head. I know. There's apps that will basically you'll say I contacted this person and then it will keep in like a record for you. Okay, you haven't talked to this person in this many months. You haven't talked to this person in this many months. Maybe you should think about just reaching out and again, reaching out putting a hard ask and just saying hey, ah, let me know if you ever need anybody referrals you liked our work together. If not, you know, whatever and you could even also be very personal with it too and just be, Hey, how are you guys doing? I hope you know everybody's doing well, maintaining that relationship in a way of more of like a friendship level as well.
Wes Bos: I think you did a really well there because I've certainly like I bought life insurance once and this guy hits me up every year and says, Who can you refer to me? Like he's just read the like, one on one sales book. And it just feels so grimy to me. And then I take the other way, yeah, and authentic. And then the guy who sells me health insurance, every now and then he sends me movie tickets as a thank you for referring someone. And every time I call him with a quick question, he remembers my kids names. And yeah, I think developers think that sales is the sort of like manipulation thing, when the sales really is is just maintaining good relationships with the people that it can be done very poorly or great, right. So like this past Christmas, I spent like quite a bit of time trying to find the best hoodie out there. And I got the best hoodie. And I got like a little one of my stickers that this is idle hands build nothing. I got it printed on these hoodies. And then I shipped them to I think about 50 or 60 people who had helped me out in some sort of significant way this year. And I felt like that was people say like, Oh, I love this hoodie. Thank you so much. And I feel like that was like a good way to just show people like I care about you. I care about our relationships. And thank you so much for for whatever it is that you had done for me this year.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah. And let me tell you, I love that hoodie. I wear that hoodie, 24. Seven, I wear it's like the warmers to do and I wear it all the time. And every single time I put it on, I think Wow, that was so nice of West to just send me that hoodie. Wow, I was such a great gesture I every time I put it on. And you know what i bet every single person you gave that to is going to have that same thought. So those kind of really thoughtful gifts, things like that. It's gonna go a long way for you
Wes Bos: totally. And I think if you are in the freelance business, you can afford to spend like those hoodies. By the time they're shipped. They cost me I don't know, 70 to $100 per person, which is not nothing. But I thought to myself, anyone who probably has who's helped me more than $500 Yeah, I do this for right. And if you get a referral for like a $12,000 website, a $2,000 website, you can afford to throw 80 bucks at something like that, or, or even just like a $20 Starbucks gift card is just shows that that relationship, I think gifts, especially like we talk about love languages, especially if that person's love language is gifts, that really goes a long way.
Scott Tolinski: It goes a long way. And it's Think of it as like a marketing expense. I mean, it's a marketing expense. It's your you're putting out there you're buying the so that when they think of somebody they think of you and that's it, it's a business expense. It's a cost of doing business. It's not necessarily Oh, I have to spend all this money to buy things. No, you're paying it forward so that those people are going to come back to you when they need anything. Do you have anything else here? Because I think we really nailed it on a lot of this stuff.
Wes Bos: No, no, that's that's really all I know about getting clients and it just comes down to being good letting people know what you do and having good relationships.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, that's really it relationships, relationships, relationships, because once you have that work done, once you have those referrals done, you're just gonna every if you have this big network everyone's gonna think of you you're gonna get that work. Cool. So now is the part of the show where we do sick picks and a sick pick is just a pick where we pick something we talked about it that we're really liking feeling in life. So Wes, do you have any sick picks today?
Wes Bos: Yes, I'm going to sick pick my mattress which was pretty fun. So when my wife got pregnant, and whenever that happened six months ago, we thought like okay, let's get a king. Let's get a king mattress because we had a queen and we'd love each other but we'd like our space so I asked on Twitter like like what's the deal with these like mattress in a box companies out there and there's a Casper and Lisa and and all these ones and a couple of them reached out to me and said like hey we can give you one for review in exchange for like an honest review. So I said okay to the Canadian one. So unfortunately for most of you this you won't be able to buy this. But the Canadian one that I got was called an ND mattress and people had said like oh I don't know about these like they're probably too soft or they hold the heat and people think it's like like memory foam where it just like you kind of sink into it. So we've had it for what maybe four or five months now and we absolutely love it. It's like the perfect firmness for us. Which is weird because I think they only sell one firmness and people like have opinions all over the space. But for us it was the perfect firmness where you can still sit on the edge of it and not like fall off like it's not this big hunk of foam that you're going to sink into. And other people said that they get really hot where like you sleep on it and thing just a collects all of your body heat. And we haven't found that to be an issue either. We've been absolutely loving it. We actually bought another one just with our own money for a cottage that we just bought, so we're big fans of it. So if you are in the market for new mattress and you're Canadian, I would definitely give my thumbs up to this nd mattress.
Scott Tolinski: Nice. That's sick. Yeah, yeah. Do
Wes Bos: you have you tried on one of these mattress boxes things before?
Scott Tolinski: We have a Casper in our guest. Yeah, but we no sleep on it because it's in our guest room. But we've heard good. Yes. Yeah, we have like a really nice mattress already. So it's like, oh, yeah, it was like we weren't gonna swap out the CASPER for a really nice mattress. But we've heard good things. So it was a really cool process where it came in the box and you open it up and yeah, that was pretty sweet.
Wes Bos: Pretty cool. We we had a Simmons beauty rest. We also got the the nd pillows, which is just like chopped up hunks of the mattress. Maybe that's what they do with the ones that get returned. I don't think that's actually what they do. But and then they give you a bag where you can just take out hunks if it's too firm. But I didn't like I didn't like the pillow. I felt like it was like, oh too squishy. We have like these like really? we pretty much have like the mattress but in pillow form. Yeah. I like that forget whom who makes like, it's like they're the
Unknown: firm's memory foam pillow.
Wes Bos: Yeah, yeah. They love and loving those pillows. So we don't didn't like the thing. But the mattresses were sorry, the mattress was great.
Unknown: Yeah,
Scott Tolinski: super great. Cool. My sick pick is actually going to be functionality from an app that maybe some of you already have. So this is a this is a weird sick pic. Because it's just a piece of functionality that you might not know about. Because I didn't know about this until I found out about this. within Google Drive. In the app, the plus button the action button on your phone, there is a bay an action to scan a document. Now we've been having to scan a bunch of documents come tax time without all of our tax information. And people send us like a 46 page thing that we have to fax to them or scan to them and
Wes Bos: so much stuff lately.
Scott Tolinski: It's like, you can't put an editable input on this PDF. Come on, like, Look, wait years this. So either way, I was like, how do your clients do this, he's like most of them just scan it. I don't have a scanner that I I'm living in 2019. Here, I don't have a scanner. So I found that Google Drive has a scan documents functionality where you just take a picture of it, and it scans it so nicely, it's incredible. And you can make multi page PDFs just by clicking the plus button. So you scan plus scan plus. And if you don't have a scanner in the first place, it was fast, it was way faster than getting in my car and driving to Kinko's or something like that and trying to get all these pages scanned. I've been using this a ton. So if you need to scan documents, and you don't want to buy a scanner, Google Drive has a scan functionality that is going to do wonderful things for you. And the tyquan even converts text to text where it can so it's pretty sweet. Awesome.
Wes Bos: I need to check that I've been scanning stuff like crazy lately, like we were down in the down in the States. And we had to go to the hospital. I told that story A while ago and are still trying to get our our insurance to cover it. Like we took a an ambulance at one block and it was $700. And I'm just like not used to getting bills. I've never had a bill for anything in my life. And we're just getting all these bills and people calling and we had travel insurance, but the travel insurance needs all these documents and they need to be scanned and like what an archaic system, this whole thing that is and it's all built upon scans and faxes, and it just drives me crazy. I can't believe that.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, for real cool. So do you have any shameless plugs?
Wes Bos: I'm gonna shamelessly plug all of my courses. Wes Bos comm forward slash courses, there's free, there's paid check it out. there's anything that interests you
Scott Tolinski: sick, I'm going to shamelessly plug my hooks course, which has just released react hooks for everyone is 20. Some videos that will teach you hooks and no time, not only are you going to learn about how to use hooks, but you're gonna learn how to write custom hooks, you're going to learn about third party hooks, you're going to be writing some really amazing reusable functionality. It is super duper, duper, duper cool. So check it out at level up tutorials.com for slash Pro. And I hinted at the course that's going to be released in this month and the end of the month here on the 31st or the I think they'll probably be out on the 29th. To be honest, I like to release it on a weekday is going to be on view j s it's going to be about building static sites with view j s using grid some. So that course is already well on the way to being completed here. I'm so excited because it's basically you could think of it as the Gatsby for view j s. So if you're interested in learning that or anything else level up tutorials.com forward slash Pro.
Wes Bos: Awesome. Thanks for tuning in. If you have any tips you'd like to tweet us we're at syntax FM. I'm at Wes Bos and Scott is at s toe linskey Beautiful. Alright, thanks for tuning in. Next week, pace
Scott Tolinski: head on over to syntax.fm for a full archive of all of our shows. And don't forget to subscribe in your podcast player or drop a review if you like this show