Unknown: You're listening to syntax the podcast with the tastiest web
development treats out there. strap yourself in and get ready to live ski
and West boss.
Wes Bos: Hello everybody and welcome to syntax today we've got a tasty potluck episode for you today, which is a potluck episode is one where we take in your listener questions and we answer them. It's kind of nice because we'll spend a couple minutes on a whole bunch of different topics will bounce around with me as always, today is Scott to Lynskey. How you doing today sky,
Unknown: I'm doing super good. I got stung in the head three times by wasps yesterday while I was mowing the lawn.
Oh my gosh, that's it. That's I feel good though. Other
Wes Bos: than bad that I was mowing the lawn right, just typical standard mowing the lawn. And then all of a sudden, yeah, I just felt like something whacked me in the back of the head. I actually I'm sorry. It was weed whipping at the time. And I thought like part of the plastic thing broke off and flew up and hit me in the head. Like that's how hard it was just hit really hard. It's like out and then like two more really quickly, like, wow, dang. And then I look around. I'm like, swarmed by bees and I found a huge nest in my fence. And I was like totally oblivious. I was standing next to it. And I look I turn around there's like, you know, 30 plus bees. Are there not bees there. Was there like the yellow jacket? Yeah. And it sucked. It sucked. But I'm doing good today. Today. My head is feeling alright man. How about you? I'm doing great. I'm just doing some a little housekeeping because I've got I'm heading off tomorrow to Chicago. Actually, by the time this goes out. I'll be back from Chicago. So thanks so much to everyone who came to Lera con Chicago It was a blast. There we go. That's my forward feature. Looking back nice. And and then after that we're heading off on some vacation going down to Pennsylvania, which should be which should be pretty fun. It's pretty sick, man. I have no more vacations left this year. So I'm gonna have Oh man. Likely, like two or two or three more weeks left. I do a lot of vacation in the summer. So nice. Yeah, some some nice downtime. I'm looking forward to it, Brad. So today's sponsor is our view School, which is an excellent place to learn view j s, which is a topic we really need to cover on this show. And we've been saying it for like half a year now. We need to have a view episode and get over with I think we all know who the blocker on this one is but we also Scott know cuz this episode is also sponsored by our longtime sponsor freshbooks, which is a brilliant, amazing cloud accounting software, which is something you absolutely need in this work environment. Cool. So do you want to get into one? First question is from Moz Saeed Abdi I think I nailed that our editor fonts worth the investment. Are they such a big deal? Why are they such a big deal in the first place? If yes, why? So let's do a quick rundown. I use operator motto in my text editor is 200 bucks. It's that one where you have the fancy italics and about 13% of the population absolutely hates it. And then the rest of the people are fairly into it. Nobody's in between. and I'm a big fan of it. What are you using right now? sky use dank mano right now, which is about 40 pounds. I don't know what that hurts to to be honest. I never I think it's like 50 bucks. We looked at it. We mentioned it and thing someone came out with like, kind of like it's like operator motto but it's it's a quarter of the price. It's a quarter of the price. It's also in my opinion, I like it a little bit more, but it has ligatures, right. It has ligatures, which is a big thing for me, because for a long time I used Fira code. ligatures are another those things that like, you know, half the population absolutely hates, like do you absolutely hate and they do. But I love I love being able to look at the code and see the ligatures like that. So I was wondering, what is it like a chair you want to I think there's probably some people that don't know what a ligature. So look at your, oh, I'm gonna type graffiti people. Don't be mad at me if I butcher this, but my understanding is that it's when two characters combine and then visually, they form one character. It's like often use and things like maybe other languages, where they have different accents on letters and things like that, but ligatures in these coding fonts are useful for essentially creating visual shapes out of your code, for instance, an arrow function, which is just an equal sign, and a greater than sign becomes an actual combined arrow. Instead of looking like two separate characters, the characters combined to form sort of one thing, or like three equal signs in a row, instead of being three equal signs in a row, they stack up vertically, so there's three horizontal lines on top of each other, and they're wider and flatter. So these ligatures allow you to see things in your code, recognize patterns a little bit more easily, right. So again, I've been a huge fan of them. For me, I'm a visual person I'm the spatial person looking at my code is a lot more readable with these ligatures in them.
So is it worth it for someone who shows their code day in and day out? Absolutely. I think using operator model early as one of the first people to actually buy it, I think. And it was a huge kind of like draw into my coding screenshots. People were really very, very, very curious about how it worked. And it sort of drew them into some of the other stuff that I do. Is it worth it for you? I don't necessarily know. It depends on a 200 bucks is very hard to swallow, especially when there's so many good ones out there for much less or even free I use in consolata for a long time, and a Fira code is a really good one as well. So I don't know, it's hard to say, it's kind of up to you, if you want to spend it. Like if I wasn't someone who visually showed my code day in and day out, I probably wouldn't buy it. Yeah, I mean, and I again, I used and bought dank moto. And I might classify that as a frivolous purchase, because it you know, I was fine with Fira code. So if you want to take advantage of some of that stuff, like ligatures, and maybe some more fancy stuff that's in a web font, and you like open source stuff and fear code all the way it's free, there's no reason not to, if you like it, but yeah, then this is pretty much how I look at it to like it. Yeah. Next question. So this next question is from Steve O'Neil, how can I come up with ideas for projects? What can I put in a portfolio when I work for an agency? So we've covered this kind of topic a lot in different sort of ways, where we just say, hey, find aspects in your life, find things that are interesting, find things that are stimulating to you, and just make something out of it, right? A lot of times in your portfolio, you know, if I'm looking for something in someone's portfolio, it's like, you know, maybe more interesting things or more technical challenges. So if you find something that has like a technical challenge, you want to cover as well, like, it doesn't have to be a personal challenge, right? It can come up with like a technical issue itself, right? You might be thinking, well, I don't have any, any hobbies to do this with. But maybe this face detection API looks really cool. So maybe I'll hack together something with that and just make something interesting. But the end of the day, I think people just want to see that you actually work on stuff, and that you like to work on code. Totally. I think that another another way to approach this, if you're working for an agency, a lot of times you can't put the stuff that you've done in your own portfolio, just because like you can't like people don't necessarily like you doing that, especially agency worlds where someone gets a big contract, and they sub that out to another agency. And that agency then hires a couple freelancers, usually three or four things away from the actual company that you did the work for. And the agencies don't want the client knowing that right. So what I did was I have just a huge grid of the different companies that I've worked with, like sauza, tequila Scotia Bank, Jamison, vitamins, TELUS Porter, Bell Media, Red Hat, and like a lot of those I'm not allowed to show the stuff that I worked on. But what I did is I maintained a private portfolio that I would just send to people when they ask for it, because like, I don't know, like, Is that allowed? I'm not sure. But I did it for a long time. And it was I was able to show people stuff internal stuff that wasn't necessarily allowed to, to show on the open web. And, and that is great. So you can just put a little thing on your website, say, please contact me for a private portfolio. Yeah, definitely. And also, I mean, we haven't talked a ton about portfolios or anything like that on the site. I think, again, when you're developing a portfolio that people like to see good things rather than lots of things. So like, you don't need everything you've ever done in your portfolio, like have like five or six good items, like no one's gonna have time to look through all that stuff anyways, so pick your best work. And again, if it needs to be private, make it private. But yeah, pick your best work and show it off that way.
Yeah, go back to the freelancing episodes that we did. Because we talked a lot about the portfolio being such a small part. For most of my career, I did not have a portfolio. And when I did, it was often out of date, and the links were dead. Oh, yeah. But I still had tons of tons and tons of tons of work. Because of the other things that we talked about on this freelancing episodes. I don't think that the portfolio is as important as most people think it is. Next up, we have a question from JavaScript, Joe, which is, let's say have two hours per week to work on coding projects? Do I spend a building a side project? Or do I spend it contributing to open source? What's your experience with contributing to open source so I think that if you're trying to learn your your, your two hours that you have per week is best spent on actually building something that you're excited about something that you are putting your own time into, I think the open source aspect of that, at least in my experience, the open source stuff sort of finds its way into your work. I've never once set off and sat down and said, Oh, today I'm going to open source some stuff or I'm going to work on some open source. What happens is that you work on a project and you use something and you say, Oh, this is broken. Let me fix it for the the library maintainer or you, you build a project for yourself, you say this is really handy. I bet other people can make use of it. So you go ahead and release it. At least set yourself under your own GitHub. Right. So I think open source will sort of find its way into your workflow. And I don't necessarily think it's something they should set off to explicitly do. Yeah, I totally, I totally agree with this. And, and it's not going to be I mean, contributing open source projects is amazing. But I don't know if it's going to be the best way for you to learn new things, maybe it's gonna be the best way for you to learn how to work in teams and maybe dive into stuff. But I would personally be a little apprehensive to do something I've never done before in an open source project, but maybe that's just me being you know, that kind of vibe about it. But yeah, I agree. I think you're gonna have better learning opportunities. But that says, you know, if you have the opportunity to come commit to open source, then please, by all means, go ahead. Cool. So we have one. Here's another one from Diane, who gave us pronounciation instructions. Thank you so much, Diane. That's, that's hilarious. I was cracking up when I read it. She asks, Why is it so hard to grasp and team projects? What are the best resources to master it? Now, this is a good one, because Git is hard. And I guess a lot of people just sort of breezed by the fact that Git is hard, right? Everyone sort of just says, Yeah, it gets, you need get. So here it is, right. But get when it breaks, it breaks. And it's very difficult to fix, you end up you know, really spending a lot of time with some obscure get error that you've never seen before. And you're trying to make it go away, and you Google around, and then you eventually fix it and you move on, right? But learning get, especially in teams, when there's a lot of people touching a lot of different things. And there's a lot of commits and branches, and all this stuff coming in, there is a lot of potential for stuff to break. So my recommendations for this kind of thing is don't like go nuts. People want to go nuts with all of the features with git, like all the time there would they want to do this and this and this. And they're trying to overcomplicate it, rather than just keeping it basic, right branch, git commit, merge, whatever, right? That very most basic stuff, pull requests. And that's it. And then once you have that down as a team, and you have a nice workflow down as a team that way, then maybe you can try to, you know, improve your workflow by complicating with some of the more obscure features a little bit. But I might Yeah, my recommendation is to keep it simple until you can afford to not keep it simple anymore and know what you're doing. My recommendation for a place to learn is to check out try github.io. This is a site I think run by GitHub that has links to a bunch of resources such as, like the GitHub Learning Lab, you can hire professional training and stuff up here. But there's a lot of great stuff from you know, the good Handbook, cheat sheets, visualizing it, that sort of stuff. So check out try.github.io if you have not already, my experience with this is the team stuff gets funky when not everyone's on the same page. Like Scott said, you all have to be on the same Git workflow in order for it to work smoothly. Because if if one of you is rebasing frequently, and one of you isn't or one of you is squashing commits, and one of you isn't, and you're just going to get into a place where somebody accidentally force pushes something in, you're gonna have a bad, bad day. So I recommend looking maybe we should do an entire episode on a couple of the different Git workflows that are out there and quisha. But doing something yet, do some research on different workflows that different teams use, because Git is a tool that can be used in many different ways with a team, and everyone has their own opinions on it. And the most important way is just to do it the exact same way as everybody else on your team. So do some research into some of those workflows. Yeah. def.
Next question is from grant chambers. What are some tips for going to your first meetup, so I went to a ton of meetups when I was first got started. I don't go to meetups very often, anymore, just because of having kids. It's it's not really great for going out and drink a beer all night. But I still do try to make out to at least a couple per year because I find them really, really good. So if you are someone that is brand new to a meet up, I think that it's really important to to push your comfort level. So that is talking to people asking lots of questions. There's often extremely smart people at these meetups that love to talk about the stuff that they know. So being able to just be a sponge and listen to all all the information, listen to the talks, talking to people. It's great for learning things. It's great for meeting people. I think everything that we said in the conference episode how to get the most out of a conference is applies to meetups as Swanee. I know that this seems like something that is very extroverted too, but I think it's also something that you could even if it's just one person, if you're very introverted, maybe if you just like kind of latch on to one person or you do research for who's speaking and maybe you'll prepare a couple questions that you specifically have for for that person. That's probably a good idea. Yeah. Someone who's talked to the meetup before right like there's nothing that the the speaker likes more than when people come up to them. afterwards and tell them that there was a good talk or that they enjoyed it, or something about it that particularly was interesting, or just something that showed that you were you're paying attention or something like that. So, you know, going up and talking to the speaker is never a bad idea Unless, of course, they look like they are in a grumpy mood or something. But for the most part, I think that's like a good Good idea. Again, I, I, as somebody who is not as socially outgoing, as Wess, right, it's harder for me. And so I totally understand if you aren't the type of person who wants to go up and like, talk to everybody. I think the easiest way, if you are a little bit more introverted, is to talk to the person you're sitting next to about anything, what are you working on? Hey, Where do you work? Because chances are, if it's a react meetup or whatever, you have that in common, unless the person's like, Oh, I'm a recruiter, I'm just here to watch. Then you can say, oh, okay, you know, what are you recruiting whatever. But the idea is, is that you all have this common thread, and then that that aspect of it should be an easy conversation starter. But if you just ask the person, where do they work? And what are they working on, that should be enough to start up any sort of conversation with somebody, and you're gonna get some good practice actually being a little bit extroverted, which is always great to do. Again, I am not good at it. And I need lots of practice. So I've been going out of my way to practice that a lot of conferences and meetups and stuff like that. So again, you're gonna want to do that. I just meet somebody find something interesting out and just become a sponge, taken everything, maybe you're not interested in what the talk is about, specifically, but take it all in and figure out what you like, and come out of there learning something, because that's really you know, why you went there? So yeah, that those are, those are my advice, find something that interests you. Yeah, go to go to meetups, I think one other. One other tip I have as well, if you are extroverted, or if you are one of those people that people come up to you, sometimes you get trapped, this happens to me, not not a whole lot. But every now and then somebody sort of dominates your time and is not respectful of your time, and will just kind of keep talking to you about stuff that you could do not care about. And it's so boring. And being able to practice your breakaway is, is really good. And there's a comedians in cars getting coffee, or Jerry Seinfeld, who's one of my role models in life, he's he says, the best way to do that is say, well, it's been great meeting you. Because the only thing you can say to that it's such a nice way to break it off. And like what do you say to that? Yes. Thank you. Yeah. Nice to meet you. Yeah. Yeah, that's, I mean, that's really, really like a thing. If you are one of those people don't monopolize someone else's time, you know, look for body language signals or whatever. But just, you know, take a couple of minutes, you know, introduce yourself, if you're having a really in depth conversation, like, Don't feel like you need to end that conversation if both people are really, you know, having a good time. But if, if, like you're dominating the conversation, and the person's like, checking their watch, yeah, and and that thing, and that thing. Yeah, that's actually the body language is a is a really good thing to learn. So it's something that sometimes I guess, we take for granted, but like, what are some of the other cues that you can take there where someone's feet are, so if someone's feet are open and pointed towards you, then it's likely that they're enjoying it. And if their feet are closed or pointed away, sometimes people will cross their arms and fiddling with their phone, there's a couple like little telltale signs that someone is not interested in talking to you. It's probably worth
looking up a list of those don't don't take that personally, either. Right. Sometimes people just got stuff to do places to be people to see that kind of thing. And, yeah, totally. Yeah. Cool. So again, you know, the main thing is, you're going to a meet up to learn things. Another great place to learn things is through view School, which is a new series and tutorial course designed to teach you view j s. So you want to learn view, I suggest you check out view school.io forward slash syntax, you're gonna get 25% off for the first 50 people that register, it was sold out, which means 50 of you already did, it looks like since they renewed their sponsorship here for another episode. Looks like they put another 50 up there, which is great. So even since the first time we've done this, it looks like they have a whole bunch more videos that have have been put out. So that's really good. So if you want to learn a view, j s by building a real world application, which is a form you want to learn a couple things that come along with view, which is the view see Li the view read or other things like that are x jazz, best practices, code splitting Webpack, modern JavaScript, everything that you want to know in order to write modern view j s, I would check it out. Kind of one of the I guess the best parts of this course is that it's built by this guy called ah Alex and I'm not even gonna attempt the last name was you know how I like to butcher last names, but he is on the Vue JS core team. So there's any sort of like, if you're not sure if he's good at view, he is he actually builds view, so If you want to learn view, check out view school.io forward slash syntax grab. You're one of the 50 25% off coupons, and thanks so much to view school for sponsoring. Thank you. Yeah, look really nice. That website is a straight fire. I mean, that's several fire emojis. So check out view schools. Oh, yeah, several in a row. Cool. Awesome. Yeah. So let's get into the next one here. It says from Michael Hoffman, have you ever thought about using Linux or Windows as your main operating system? I've thought about that every day. I think about that all the time, whenever my computer has any issues, or I hear about, you know, MacBook Pro throttling and stuff like that. I yeah, I've been wanting to get off, I think is my last MacBook Pro that I had. I was like, I'm never buying another MacBook Pro. And then sure enough, I bought another one, you know, three or four years later. So I think about it a lot. You know, the options are interesting with the Linux subsystem and stuff in Windows, now you get you get access to a lot of the the Linux stuff that we like before, I still can't bring myself to love windows. There's so many weird little legacy design things, icons, and like several different styles of things all over the operating system that just kind of makes me really mad. Just there's like a lot of like, little windows, things that like, I mean, I used windows for a long time when I was growing up. And so many of the problems that I had with Windows when I was a high school they're like still exist. And just wondering like, why isn't this a smoother situation? Or why haven't they like really nailed their design language yet, when they have such a strong design language, right? They just don't propagate it through the entire thing. So that said, you know, Windows is a beast, I can't ever see myself running Windows full time. I think I could have a Windows machine and be happy as a dev machine for various reasons. But I don't think I could run it full time. Linux. On the other hand, I would be very happy to have a Linux machine. I've always said very frequently. I mean, I'm an Android phone user, if I could have some sort of computer system that was like Android, but like actually a full on operating system. I would probably buy that. And it looks like the the new Chromebooks you can run Android apps, and you can have access to the Linux, all your commands and everything. Yeah, you can run VS code on Chromebooks now. Right? So because you have access to all of that, if I had to put money on what my next computer would be, it would ever be whatever Google or whoever's releasing at the time, the pixel book looks great. I would have bought that if you could have done web dev on it when it came out. But now that you know, you can install Node and everything on those, like very easily, I think it would be if whatever they're making is good at the time, I might get a pixel book and be super happy with that. Yeah, it's a interesting one to me, just because it's funny, because I love OSX or OS, what do they call it?
I love Mac OS on the computer. It's really smooth. I've been increasingly frustrated with the MacBook Pro hardware in the last years. A couple years. It looks like they fixed a couple of the issues with things like the touch bar and whatnot. It's it's just frustrating. Would I ever switch to Windows? I don't know. It's It's so hard. So I have a What is it like a Surface Book sitting on my desk here, Microsoft gave me like a evaluation unit, just to try it out. And I've been primarily using it just to research the W SL windows subsystem Linux stuff, because a lot of my tutorials use all these snazzy command line stuff. And I want it to work just as well on Windows and and I have been able to get absolutely everything working on Windows, which is so surprising to me. It works really, really well. But that said the rest of Windows First of all, I don't want to like have to relearn everything. Yeah, like I'm not as in love with computers as I was when I was a kid. And I would like spend time evaluating applications and tweaking and customizing. And I just want it to work. I've got work to get done at the end of the day. And the fact that I have all of these different applications and then I have to find like the equivalent, like, Oh, I love Alfred. And then someone's like, Oh, yeah, there's something kind of like it. But it's not as good and doesn't work well. And there's not all the workflows and it doesn't really work out. Right. And that tends to happen with with a lot of my stuff on on Windows, I don't really want to put the time into into relearning it all in the hardware itself. This I don't even know what it is Surface Book Surface Book Pro, something like that. It has like a, you take the screen out and a screen has a battery in it and it becomes a tablet, which is really cool. I like it for teaching because it comes with a little thing you can draw on the screen. Like I tried it for I think a couple of weeks full time but it just just couldn't couldn't move over to it. I think if you're getting started fresh, maybe maybe give it a give it a shot. I don't I don't think that some of the reasons why everybody used a Mac are as relevant anymore because I think that Windows is working really hard to solve a lot of those pain points, especially the windows subsystem Linux stuff, but the switching costs from me is just much too high at this point. Yeah, and I don't care all that much. Yeah. And I think the cult of Mac thing is I kind of in an odd spot because you still have people defending, like, every bad decision Apple makes left and right. And I would have thought that people would be like, at some point being like, yeah, these are some bad decisions, but you still get people like really, really hot. You know, just I will only buy Apple stuff for this, like the the home, the home pod thing, whatever that is like there. Oh, yeah. It's like, that's a joke when people buy that you're like, okay, right. Yeah, because it's way worse than Alexa or Google Assistant. And at the same time, it's way more expensive. And so like, yeah, I again, I just, that's it's too much for me. As for like other Linux operating systems, I've used mint actually have mint installed on my, my old MacBook Air because you can do that. It just I have like, that's the only OS I have on my MacBook Air is meant just because I wanted to see if I could live with it, right. And it's pretty good. But like, I just don't know if it's as polished as something that I could I could live with like that. And for me, a lot of the applications that were tying me down were like sketch, I use Final Cut Pro to edit and a bunch of Mac stuff, right? I use logic to record this podcast. And slowly those reasons are going away, though I use figma. Now, which is available on Linux and Windows, right, I use a Why have a video editor now instead of doing my editing, and then logic? Sure, there's probably audio recording applications that are decent on everything, maybe not as much on Linux. But you know, as long as you you can replace that core functionality, I would move to a Linux system, I just would want it to be as polished of an experience. Yeah, yeah, I don't, I don't think I would ever move to Linux, just because I don't want to babysit, like I used to run a hackintosh like full time, like I'm done. I built like a tower. And I would install this hacked version of OSX on it. And it was amazing. But like when that thing went down, you're in for like a day or two of like, like trying to like SSH drivers into your into your machine from an external laptop. And it's it when my laptop goes down. I what I do is I just go into the Apple store and I buy a new one. I restore it from my hard drive that I have here on my end that I just keep going or they fix the other one. Right. I don't have time to I don't have time to to fuss around with fixing silence. Yeah, absolutely. That is it is a big thing, right? Because it's a huge time investment also, right our audiences. I know there's a ton of people who use Linux and Windows in our audience. But I would say the majority of our viewers probably have a Mac and like that, you know, that familiarity of what they're sitting on their screen is what they're seeing on your screen is kind of a big deal.
Yeah, that's a good point. Next question we have here, there was no name associated with it. But would you recommend Upwork for starting out freelancing or something similar. So Upwork is this website where you can go on and find a whole bunch of jobs that are for sale. Like if I wanted someone to build me a WordPress theme, I would go on Upwork. And I would post the job along with some information about what's going on. And and then people would bid on that, and then I would find someone and pay them through it. And I know that there are lots of good people working on Upwork. But it just seems to me that Upwork has and all of these freelancing websites, it doesn't really seem to me that you're you're actually running a business, it seems like you're sure to just like going to this place where you can get some work and you're sort of dependent on this third party. Whereas if you're trying to freelance ideally, you'd be you'd be running your own business, you'd be doing your own marketing, and you'd be you'd be like really putting yourself out there because as far as I've seen, there's not extremely good paying work on Upwork it tends to be the sort of bid to the bottom stuff. I may be wrong with that. And there's probably some like edge case, areas where people are like, really into legal writing or something like that. But what I like to think I don't know, Scott, do you do you start to see this in now that you've had your first kid? Do you start to see all of your friends from high school starting to sell stuff? Like, there's like, like, there's a very essential oils, a very specific like type of person that I could like, maybe write out like, if you were to give me a list of the people I graduated with that I knew I could maybe give you a list of all of the people who will fall for a multi level marketing scheme at some Yeah, like, it's like a very specific type of person. But yes, absolutely. Yeah. There's so many of them. And the funny thing is, is that like some of them don't get it after one or two even they did like the it works and now they're doing the Rodin and fields and now they're doing like press on nails or something like that. It's like these people just bounce from one to one to one and they don't get that it's a scam. It's like their damn Yeah. So these if you're not familiar, I'm not sure if they have these in Europe and stuff like that. But in in North America, when you have your first kid, you realize that you don't want to go back to work and you want to work for yourself. And what happens is that people get sucked into these like Tupperware party do Tara sweetlegs There's all these like things where basically, you buy a whole bunch of stuff from the company, and then you shake down your entire Facebook list for people trying to sell them stuff, then you invite all your friends over and exploit their friendship to sell these overpriced goods. Right? And it's funny, it always frustrates me to see this on Facebook, because these people are hashtag and be your own boss. Yeah. Hashtag entrepreneur and I was like, you're, you're, like, posting quotes from shark tank and stuff like that, and that you're not running a business. You're just exploiting your friends group for this kind of stuff. And I think like, I always think like, some like, I actually have a friend who's doing really well selling oils. And I often wonder, like, how much better would you be doing if you actually were running your own business? Alright, yeah, clearly, you have the skill to do it. Most people don't. But I think that like Upwork is is kind of the like Tupperware of the web development industry where they offer they say that come to us, be your own boss, run your own business. But at the end of the day, you're you shouldn't be relying on somebody else. If you're running your own your own business like that. Yeah. And it might, you know, might be in decent place to get a foot in the door with a client or maybe get some referrals up. But I don't think I would hang out there for too long, right? Yeah. Totally. I see that too.
Yeah, that's pretty much all I got on that one. Let's see, we have one from Mike see. In he actually spared us his last name, because apparently it's too difficult to pronounce. I love how like how many pronunciation jokes we're getting in our inbox. Now, that's hilarious that everyone's caught on take a drink. They can't pronounce names. What do you think about sites like code wars and code fights? being new to web development? I find problems hard to solve, or find the problems hard to solve? Is it important to know how to solve all of these problems? if so how do I get better at developing the mindset to problem? This is an interesting question, except we use these sites and I like a lot of these sites. I like what they're doing, like for the most, for the most part, like they're presenting you with a challenge. If you haven't seen any of these, it's like, here's a question, here's an array, filter out all of the odd number items, or whatever. And then you have to maybe come up with a solution that qualifies and passes all of their tests, and you submit it and then you get points for it. And then you can look at all of the solutions. And they're they're ranged in difficult to super easy to anywhere in between, right. And sometimes they'll even pit you against someone else who can solve this problem faster. Now, the thing that I like about these sites is they do get you solving problems that you might not encounter in your day to day code that you could encounter in the future. Or that could come in handy when you're trying to think of a technique for some of these things. There's definitely a lot of value in the type of questions that they ask you. And the type of answers that you're going to come up with. Now where they don't have a ton of value is maybe some of the time crunch stuff. It could be fun as a game, right? If you want to challenge yourself, but like in a real world situation, you're never going to have like 30 seconds to answer this question. Or else, you know, you lose. So a lot of the times, you know, I think they're very helpful for getting yourself into a mind state. And do not be hard on yourself for not knowing the answers. Part of the the coolest thing about them is that when you complete it or you give up, you can look at the solutions. And in my mind, if you spend 20 minutes on it, and you can't come up with the right answer, you should probably look at the solution. And then understand the solution don't just glance at it is like oh, that's the answer. Take the time to look at it and really truly understand that solution. Because even if you wouldn't have come up with that, maybe it was just like a method you didn't even know existed that does the whole thing for you, right? But you can't always know the answers to all of these things. So spend some time on it. Don't spend too much time on it. Really the value comes in evaluating different solutions in seeing how other people are doing it and getting to look at code that is good. I think that's the big value. Yeah, I think that they're they're pretty cool too, especially because a lot of the times the the the way that they test if your solution is right as they just like run unit tests against the functions that you're running, which is really cool, because it teaches you to write modular functions that are very easily testable with a unit testing framework. Where it might not click for a lot of people is that when you're getting into web development, I think a lot of people just want to like build stuff. Like they want to be able to see what they have, they want to be able to click a button and to play a video. And a lot of times the stuff on this is very much like extend the prototype filter for X, Y and Z. And like that's a whole nother section of programming, which might not be exciting to you at the time. Because you don't know why would you ever want to extend a prototyper? Like why would I even want to filter this array, right? But when you stumble upon it, where you're like, Oh, I have a an array of photos, and I only want to I want to filter them for ones that include the word dog, and then it starts to set in. I think that's the reason why a lot of people like my JavaScript 30 cores is because it's very much not about the Foo bar Baz and functions and stuff load. That's a really important part of programming. I think you should do it but there's another part of Especially if you're looking for those small wins where you actually built something, I think maybe you can also spend part of your time on just building little little apps, little things that you click little buttons, little toys that we do in JavaScript 34. Yeah, I love that about your course to actually I've been, I've been thinking a lot about your course, because I do want to have some sort of basic beginner JavaScript content on level up tutorials. And I do it's like, really bad, though. It's just not it's like, very, I don't know, here's how to do this, here's how to do this, but not a lot of why. And I've been really thinking about how your course really excels at having an interesting context for everything that you're doing, and how I can make something that is as interesting. So I definitely have a lot of ideas there. It's going to be aimed at beginners. I don't have a timeline or anything like that. But it is going to be sort of beginner JavaScript training. Like I have no experience in JavaScript, but at the same time, still practical, like gets you into web stuff. really early kind of stuff.
Yeah, I've been I've been thinking about that a lot too, as well, just because and I've asked on Twitter like people give me your in if you haven't chimed in on this, feel free to tweet me at Wes Bos and Scott as well. Because like, like, what, what did you trip up on when you're first learning JavaScript? What was frustrating to you when you're first learning JavaScript? Because it's easy for like us experienced devs to come in and start chancing learn the basics and, and stuff like that. But I think back to when I learned it wasn't like that at all. I've been thinking a lot about like, how do I teach people because I don't have a beginner course, either. My JavaScript 30 course, is very much popular in the beginner crowd or people who are looking for a refresher, but it's not it. It assumes you know, functions and variables and passing arguments. And the DOM assumes, you know, a whole bunch, right? So I'm missing this like, like, and people ask me all the time, like, Where do I learn JavaScript? I'm like, I don't know. I like. So I've been thinking a lot about how do I make something that's not your standard, boring, the Foo, bar Baz have a function that adds a and b and returns the total? and things like that, but it's sort of like plays off the the nerves that I hit with the JavaScript 30 cores? Yeah, absolutely. We should we should have a powwow about that at some point. Totally word. Yeah. And then eventually, if you get good at JavaScript, from all this stuff, you're going to be rolling in cash. And what are you going to do with all that cash you're rolling in, I don't know you better have some good bookkeeping. And that's where Freshbooks comes into play. Wow. Haha. Freshbooks is the best cloud accounting that you can get. So if you are a freelancer, a small business, you need to keep track of any number of things. So you need to keep track of invoices that you have people, if you need to send people quotes, I often need to send people a quote, then they go off and get it approved, then get a purchase order, then come back, we turn that quote into an invoice, managing all of your expenses tracking your time. So sometimes you have multiple clients with multiple types of work, and all of that different types of work of different dollar values that are associated with your per hour. If you want to track how long it's going on. I love the time tracking thing because you can get a desktop app and turn it on and off, you can do a quick summary, what I would do is every day when I'm done, I would do a quick summary today work seven hours, here's what I did. And then when it came time to invoice time, it was very clear that I could just like generate an invoice and it would give all the details as to what I worked on. And it was very easy for the manager to approve that freelancing stuff. So if you are a small business, a freelancer anybody who needs to send an invoice, don't create some janky thing on Microsoft Excel. Go to freshbooks comm forward slash syntax and sign up for sign up for a 30 day unrestricted free trial and use syntax in the How did you hear about a section doe?
Next up we got a question from unnamed question was when I work in a website, I need to record usernames, passwords, URLs, keys, login, C panels, WordPress, FTP, SQL, you name it. And that's for each and every website, local and remote. Currently, I use a text file. And I save that all in a website that I NF and I use this format or you just list out there's a URL, here's the username, here's the password. So this is definitely like a worldwide problem where people don't know their passwords. What it often results in is people just keep a txt file on their desktop with all of their passwords, which is let me tell you don't ever do this. You should never ever have a password in a plain text file where anyone could pick it up any desktop application that you're running on your computer could scoop that file up, send it off, and you'd be poached. So especially when you're like you're doing this for clients, right? And if your client website goes down, you might be held liable for whatever's going on in that. So what is the solution to being overwhelmed with all of these passwords and whatnot. So I think first of all, for all of your servers for accessing MySQL, FTP, or SSH, any of these things where you need to push things to, ideally, you'd be using an SSH key, which an SSH key is, is a key that lives on your computer. And it's sort of like a fingerprint of your computer. And then when you want to access a server, it will bring, bring that SSH key along for the ride, and then it will authenticate you, which is great, because then you don't have to worry about username passwords. And as someone who manages the server, if you ever were to quit, or ever were to have your SSH key changed, they can just revoke that key. And then it would, you'd no longer be able to go in it, right, there's no, there's no thing about passwords or sharing or stuff like that. So that's good if you can use SSH if you can't, because a lot of people still do username and passwords, and I had this a lot with clients, they would give me their username and password, what I would always do is first go and make your own username and password. That way all of the actions are tied to your username. And then also when your client goes to login into yours, because they have to renew their hosting, and they forget their password, they're not going to reset it on you. And then that's frustrating to to actually get the password from them. So make your own. And then what I do with those is I store them in I specifically use LastPass, I use one password years and years ago, I switched to LastPass. And I'm thinking about switching back now because I'm not super happy with with LastPass. But anyways, what I'll do is I'll create a note for each website and in that secure note will contain all of the username passwords and all of the secure information that is required for that specific one. And then you don't have to ever worry about it. So just keep it in somewhere that's password protected. Don't ever put it in a plain text file that could be accessed by anyone who has remote or local access to your computer. Yeah. And the benefit of SSH keys is that like it makes SSH ng and fun because you never even have to enter a password or think about it. You just SSH in and it doesn't even prompt you for anything you just in. Yeah, I love that. Again, if you're actually using one password or LastPass, I want to hear your opinions on which one you like more. So shout out at us which one you're using. If you're using a password manager, if it's one password or LastPass? Or if it's something we don't even mention here. I want to know what kind of Password Manager people are using. That's it's a topic that's really interesting to me. Here's a question from Chandler Bing. Thank you for the friends, the friends joke here. What happened to Scott's YouTube channel? No upload for weeks. Yeah, about that. So I have recorded over 130 some videos this year, all of which have gone into the pro channel. Well, at least I have like five videos every series that make it to the YouTube channel, but 130 videos this year. So I have been recording a lot. The only thing is, is that it's sort of a transition period. So this summer, I did a lot of I do a lot of traveling, I did talking and I just had a vacation and I have a child. So all of those things combined have really prevented me from releasing a ton of content on YouTube. That said, part of the reasons why I just remodeled my office. And by remodel, I just got a new desk, a new setup and sort of stuff like that. So that it's going to be way easier for me to crank out content for YouTube, I'm also looking in just having like an editor take care of YouTube content for me. So the plan is, is that YouTube content will be back in some sort of full force very soon here. But I'm still in this period of adjusting and getting things worked out. And then I think later this year, even next month, I think you're going to see the floodgates open and a lot of free content on YouTube. And, you know, eventually I would love to do one, one free series and one Pro Series every single month. But that is a lot of content. So we're gonna see how that works.
Totally having a kid I totally feel that pain, where at the end of the day, like I don't really see a whole lot of YouTube stuff either just because I'm more focused on building my premium content. That's what pays the bills at the end of the day. And spending more time on this podcast which takes away from from YouTube time, but that's fine because that pays the bills. Yeah, it's interesting to find a balance between doing that free stuff which people really enjoy and also help sell stuff but then also like doing the stuff that pays the bills at the end of the day as well. Yeah, people think that YouTube makes you into a millionaire or something like that. And I'll tell you what, 250,000 subscribers you do not like I don't even have enough for rent off of YouTube at all like YouTube does not pay the bills. I'm just gonna say that it doesn't pay very much at all i the way those people are making a lot of money is by millions of views on every video plus sponsorship deals and stuff like that, you know, most YouTubers are probably not making very much money. I'm literally I 100 air from YouTube. So if anyone wants to go out I'll buy tickets because I'm rolling and rolling in hundreds of dollars from YouTube over the years.
Unknown: I got a plaque that count as money. I think that counts as money. Yeah. Can I take that to target and buy something with it?
Wes Bos: No, I'll buy that off for us. I haven't hit that hundred Thousand yet. Last question we got here is kind of a fun one Whose idea was it to do a podcast? who approached whom? First? I don't. I don't remember. I don't remember either, you know, because we had been chatting for a while. And I think the idea of a podcast came up at some point. The the idea of even like we had a lot of the details for syntax worked out a long time before we recorded it. Like a year before we recorded the first episode because I think we were in a mastermind, which is like a group where you get together and laugh maniacally. And no, it's a group that we got together with a couple other people in the industry and just kind of chit chatted about ideas about what's going on sharing what's worked and what hasn't worked. I highly recommend you started mastermind with some of your biggest competitors. We also had Joel, who runs egghead IO. And Josh Owens, who runs a lot of the meteor stuff it was asked for we met every week and just shared some stuff in it. We're no longer running it just because I don't know I think a lot of stuff. Same with like podcasts and stuff, you kind of do their course and you get what you get What it from, what you had hoped. And then and then it's sort of sunsets. Yeah, it goes away. But we had talked about doing the podcast all along that and we had a whole Google Doc full of ideas full of like, possible names, possible ways to approach it. I was looking at some of the failed syntax logos the other day, it was like a picture of Scott and I with the word syntax underneath. It was brutal. I actually didn't think that was brutal. Oh, maybe we should use it seems like, Well, for me, because everything you were coming out, I'm not I'm not that much of a designer. See, see, Wes. I'm like you I know my designs. First my design? No, no, I when I saw that, that design, I don't know. All the stuff you were coming up with was way better than the stuff that I could have come up with. So yeah, I was I was impressed with all of it. So I would say about the original. Yeah, I wish we had the absolute original dock that we had with I think we do. So we just pulled up the dock from April 1 2016. These are good. Oh, that means we've we've had we've been thinking about this podcast for over two years. Now. The podcast itself is only a year old. Yeah, we started it in like June 2017. So while we had the idea for sitting for over a year, just sort of sitting there. things I love about the podcast, juicy details on how hosts build things and earn money, show notes, section descriptions. Here's
Unknown: a good title here. Things I Hate About podcasts too long and rambly. inside jokes. The original
Wes Bos: inside jokes is all this podcast. This podcast is almost entirely jokes I made. I made an inside joke right before introducing this segment. Yeah. Oh, yeah. Here's the some of the original names, which are all pretty good. Oh, I guess we had syntax is sort of right in the middle. And then we had like syntax, caste, code life async code time with West and Scott. website. sauce tips.
Unknown: Code code. Yeah, the fun dev show like code code code.
Wes Bos: You know, you have to say three times. Block scope. I really liked that name. Still, if someone wants to start a podcast, feel free to take it block scope would be a good name for a podcast. Yeah, these are all great. Except for the fun dev show. That's the worst name ever. The codec? Oh, that's funny. Yeah. One of the things I found on this on the even the shoot, where was that it was on the latest version of the dogs barking. And one of the latest versions. I saw. Where is this thing? Dang, I just saw this. Oh, we had our original podcast layout, like when we were describing the layout. And so we say in formal intros. Hey, I'm Wes. Hey, I'm Scott, what are you working on? What's going on in your life? In terms of topic, I talked about topic, sick pics with like eight eyes. And then we have a whole section. Like we have such little on the actual structure. But then we have like a whole 10 lines on different audio samples we wanted to use this is before we even made up any of them. It's like we've spent more time thinking about audio samples. Like for the intro? Yeah, we did. The actual structure. That's great. Yeah. Now Now we, the way that we kind of approach this podcast now is just, we open up a we have a Trello of hundreds of ideas. And then we open up a Dropbox paper and sort of riff on on the layout. And then we just give her so usually like an hour long podcast probably takes us like an hour, hour and a half hour 45 and then and that's it. Yeah, yeah, not too bad. Yeah, you can probably tell
Unknown: we still gotta use some of these audio things that we wanted like the drama Mama, and pound it and Oh, wait, where's
this?
Wes Bos: The system the most recent iteration if you just do a command find for audio API's? We have one that says easy breezy. And then we have hot take time machine which I don't even know how we would use this but hot takes from years ago which I guess would be something about jQuery so these are things that we I guess we wanted to say pound it smash that like button drama mama sick tips tasty treats easy breezy hot take time machine heartache from past years What does that even mean? I wrote that at some point and that is hilarious no I have no idea what I think I came up the word hot take time machine as like a plan Hot Tub Time Machine and then I like just wanted to come I wanted to shoehorn something in there really badly just cuz I was you know laughing about it so much these are good we got the pit we got peace in here as well. Yeah, these are all good cool that's that's kind of fun to look back two years ago we thought the podcast would be and now look at us look at us now you know you know what else was in this doc doc is the Twitter username and password which I just finished saying don't ever do
Unknown: the best part is I didn't even I don't even know that I didn't even know that was in there because I didn't have the Twitter username and password.
Wes Bos: Yeah, well, you can log in now and start start talking shit on the on the syntax. Oh, yeah, look out everyone it's about to get spicy All right, uh, let's move into some sick pics, sick pics. I got a sick pic. that's appropriate. Because I just rebuilt my desk I'm going to be doing a lot of photos of this desk setup. So if you want to check it out, check it out on Instagram I'm gonna be doing on the level of tut's at level up tutorials Instagram account and be showing off this new desk setup that I just built here. And one of the cornerstones of this desk setup is the new like standing desk legs I got which I got the Jarvis standing desk legs, I got them after talking to a ton of web developers about what they're using and why they like it and almost hands down the Jarvis seemed to be the winner. There was a couple other ones the uplift, but the Jarvis really seemed to be the winner and it seemed to be well worth the price I purchased just the legs, I got an Ikea countertop, which you'll see which is pretty sick, and I screwed the legs into the countertop. And it has presets so I can go from standing to sitting I just hit the one or two or whatever and it takes it to the right spot. And let me tell you, these things are awesome. It moves like very quietly it moves very solidly, this desk is huge and it feels very, very comfortable. So I actually have an ergonomic setup now Ed standing or sitting rather than having one that was sort of halfway in between both and having both bad posture and either set up like in my standing one it was a little too low. So I kind of hunched forward and then my sitting one, my elbows were up at my shoulders and I was ridiculous. So these standing desk legs I highly recommend these Jarvis legs. They are awesome if you're looking at standing desk, I've heard the desktops are great as well I can't speak to that but the legs themselves are awesome. So if you know standing desk space, Jarvis legs, check them out. Cool and you got an Ikea countertop on top of that. Yeah, I just bought a slab a countertop is 140 bucks and beautiful looking. And it's a great desk it was really easy to set up I just had to the only you know scary part was drilling into the countertop, but at the end of the day, you know measure a few times first and then you know drill once and it all worked out. So so many people that I know like I've had this countertop desk for probably seven years now. It's just a huge IKEA countertop and it's like it's the best desk that you can get. I think like desktop you have to figure out the legs otherwise, like I just use like IKEA box and some legs underneath and it's just so sturdy. And it's like the right depth. A lot of desks are too deep. And I don't know it's just unreal. I just I think IKEA countertop is the best desk you can for your money. Yeah, they should really like move the countertop section to the desk section because it was it's really yeah, cuz the death section has like a, they have like a butcher block top. But there it's like really thin and flimsy and limit and then it's light and it rattles and it's no good. Yeah, yeah, no good. Awesome. My sick pick today is going to be vices or Thrashers, King of the row, which is a throwback. Oh, it's it's back. I think you sick pick this last year. This might have been like the third ethic pick this. So if, if you're not sure what it is i a lot of people I know that Listen, this podcast grew up as skaters. And what it is king of the road is takes three skate teams out on the road and they have like all these contests and some of the contests are crazy tricks. Some of them are really stupid things like drinking other people's pee, which is disgusting, but it kind of reminds me of remember jack cK cK I had all of those growing up. Yeah, kinda like that. But also like really good skating in it as well and it's just hilarious as all get out. So it's in this third season now called king of the road and You can watch it on viceland.com. Last year, I watched it on viceland calm because I had like a, I could sign in with my phone provider and get access to it. And now it tells me that it's not available in Canada. So I think it's available in the States. You can procure it by other means if it's not available in your country because it's hilarious, and very much recommended to watch. Yeah, I love this show. I love it for the music. I love it. Because you get to know these skateboarders really well, you know, you follow them around in a van across the country, I end up like following most of the skateboarders on Instagram afterwards. And I mean, these, these are the best in the world. So it's not it's not like you're watching just some jackass, people mess around on the skateboard. It's like you're watching professionals. And then the goofy stuff is just like extra fun. You know? It's hilarious. It's awesome. Oh, what about shameless plugs today?
Yeah, I'm gonna shamelessly plug my new course, which is going to be on Apollo client. This is all about using Apollo client with react. So it's also about graph qL servers and setting up a graph, qL API and more about all of the cool features that come with Apollo. So it's called level one Apollo client. And it's really diving into how to use the query component, that mutation component, we really get into things like optimistic UI, we get into things like, you know, pagination, or loading more kind of style, and how you can just really understand and set up Apollo on the client side of your react site. If you haven't done any graph QL. This is a nice introduction, because we set up a really easy basic API. And then we work through all of the cool stuff about how like why graph qL is amazing to work with on the client side. So I'm really excited for this course. I'm a huge fan of Apollo, a huge fan of graph qL in general. So if you're interested in these things, check this course out. It's going to teach you how to use Apollo on the client side in react and you can get access to this course I level up tutorials, comm for slash pro sign up become a pro save 25% by sending up for the entire year at once. And you're going to get 12 series every single year. Lots of good content coming out nonstop. And there's going to be even more lots of awesome announcements to make there is shamelessly plug all of my social media today. So Twitter at Wes Bos that's probably the one where a lot of you already follow me. But I'm also on Instagram quite a bit lately. instagram.com Ford slash West boss I'm on Facebook facebook.com forward slash West boss dot developer, which is kind of funny because I took Wes Bos for my own personal account, don't add my personal account, I have probably 700 friend requests on my personal account that I will not accept.
Unknown: Yeah.
Wes Bos: And what other kind of social media is there? There's Twitter, Facebook, Instagram, Link me on MySpace. And please don't add me on LinkedIn. Oh my gosh, I have like, I probably have 700 requests. Yeah, on my LinkedIn as well. I know. It's funny what what oh, that's amazing. 704 invitations on my on my LinkedIn right now nice.
Unknown: I periodically I go in every couple weeks and just do accept all like, just to get out of there.
Wes Bos: I wrote a I have a YouTube video where we we write a filter and programmatically click the decline button. If the person's byline says recruiter. No, that's me. Yeah. So like we read programmatically. And then we and then we wrote another thing to automatically accept everybody else. Which is funny because he I go into my like LinkedIn inbox. It's just people being like, congrats on your work anniversary. Congrats. Like what? Why have I worked anniversary? Okay, like, you think that's gonna work? Like getting business or something like that? I have no idea. Yeah, I don't understand that at all. And it's like, also, because it's like a robot response. They just click the button and it was just, you know, it's not even Yeah, even genuine or authentic. It's no, I
Unknown: click the button that says thank you for your work experience. Like, no, I don't get it.
Wes Bos: I also, when people send you in mail you they only pay for in mail if you read it or reply. So always make sure that a reply so they waste their six bucks or whatever they pay to try to send it. Anyways, I think that's it for today. Anything else to say?
Unknown: Got nothing. Got nothing else. All right. We'll see
you next week. All right. Peace.
Head on over to syntax.fm for a full archive of all of our shows. And don't forget to subscribe in your podcast player or drop a review if you like this show.