Scott Tolinski: Welcome to syntax where we deliver tasty treats for web developers.
Wes Bos: Welcome to syntax How's everybody doing? This is the podcast full of tasty treats
Unknown: that tastiest treats.
Wes Bos: So, somebody said that the the whole tasty treats part of the podcast was cringy. So Scott and I are going to double down and make them even tastier. It deeply,
Scott Tolinski: deeply upsets me that that would be cringy. Because I love the tasty treats. That's one of my it's one of the best parts.
Wes Bos: So somebody also sent me a link to the always sunny and Phil Yeah. tasty treats, which I really did not think of. I definitely did not think of when I when we came up with the podcast, tasty treats. But now I am dying at how hilarious that scene is.
Scott Tolinski: I did not think of that. So I didn't jeopardize. I don't want to jeopardize the chance of tasty treats making it into the podcast. So that's like one of my all time Greatest TV episodes of any Oh,
Wes Bos: that's that's fine. One of my favorite episodes. If
Scott Tolinski: you're,
Wes Bos: if you're looking for a laugh, open up YouTube and search tasty treats Sunny, and you're you'll see something funny. So today we're going to talk about our origin stories, which is sort of like how did we get started? And what was the path to becoming web developers and whatnot. So apologize if you've heard me on a podcast sort of talk about this before. You can skip mine. Mine goes a little bit more in depth than I ever have on some podcasts. But I have never heard Scott's so I'm interested in that. So we got a sponsor here today. Thanks so much to fresh books for sponsoring fresh books is a easy to use Cloud accounting software that saves small business owners like you and myself, two days a month in paperwork and get some paid up to five days faster. We'll talk a little bit more about them partway through the show. But head on over to freshbooks comm forward slash syntax for a 30 day free trial. And make sure you enter in syntax in the How did you hear about a section so we can get paid? Cool. So Scott, how did you get started to being a web developer?
Scott Tolinski: Oh, yeah. So I feel like I don't know if this is like a theme or whatever. But I feel like, you know, with with web development, being such a interesting career as it is, I think that you're going to find a huge amount of variability in people's origin stories, if you if you talk to them about how they got started. I mean, most people that I know that are devs have either very interesting or just very unusual, they're different stories, and maybe not like, Oh, I went to study computer science. And now I'm a developer, right? I mean, there's certainly a lot of people. But uh, you know, this industry attracts a lot of different people. So I'm sure if you talk to a lot of people, you're going to get some pretty weird stories. But it's definitely not the most normal, so to say. So I started obviously tinkering around with web technologies back in high school and middle school, just building really basic HTML sites. I had a popular band in high school and like our battle of the bands was like, seriously, gigantic deal, it sold out like a huge auditorium every year. And our, our band got like second place our as freshmen in that, like, didn't happen. Like, if you got second place, one year, it was almost guaranteed you're gonna get first place the next year. So then we ended up getting first place for a couple years. And just like really, you know, our band was like a big deal for us in high school. So, you know, I made our site. And then we kept remaking it all the time, because we wanted it to be cooler. We made it in HTML, and then flash through Angel fire. And, you know, we say occasionally we do these, like really ridiculous flash intros to the site. And I made it with a good friend of mine, who I'll get into a little bit more in this episode, but uh, his name is Devin Booker. He was our bassist in the band. He's a super talented guys, one of the smartest people I know. And so basically, we just mess around with that for a long time. And somehow our bands messageboard became like the hotspot in high school for like digital space. So like, our message board was like, it hadn't I don't know if like, it just became like the message board where people in our school would would just chat. So we maintain this like decent message board for our high school for a little bit. And that was just like, you know, that was basically my introduction to web stuff, right? It was just a lot of fun and we were doing it because we wanted to, you know, goof around. We wanted to put some audio clips on Okay, you've got to learn audio stuff you wanted to have a Ridiculous intro you got to learn flash stuff you you want to, you know, learn CSS, you got to learn all that stuff. Obviously the site was probably terrible. I would love to see what the code looks like right now. I have absolutely no idea what the code would look like for that site. I would really love to see it. So yes, so really, from there, just started my interest in actually, our band's name, I should point this out is set focus from the set focus method in Flash. So we stole our band name from flash. Yeah. It's so yeah, so then I just started like building my site I built like Scotland ski.com. Like, I don't know, a whole bunch built it in high school, just for fun, and messing around on Angel fire and whatever. And then, uh, yeah, so that was pretty much it. I didn't really have any ideas of what I wanted to do in life, really, I just wasn't really that motivated or driven. And the my friend Devin, who was in our band, he had heard about this program at the University of Michigan, which was audio and video engineer. Well, it was audio engineering, it was in the School of Music, and they had several different sort of pathways in this program. And so you there was like three people accepted into each of the four majors a year. And that's it. So it was pretty competitive for these three Hots. Yeah. And I'll tell you, the people who I graduated with in my program are like incredible people. So
the different focuses would be like music technology, with a focus in composition, music technology with a focus in performance. My program was music technology, with a focus on media arts. So like video production, I had to take 18 dance credits, I did take a lot of art. I took like sewing just like a whole bunch of random random classes in college. But my buddy Devin, he took the fourth which was audio engineering with a engineering component. So he actually got a science degree and went on to get his master's and stuff like that. So he definitely went way more into the audio engineering spectrum of everything. And I did much more of the multimedia stuff. So while I was there, I took a bunch of music programming classes, which is like my introduction to higher level programming, whereas building things like I mentioned before, like video theramin, like a projection audio synthesizer, and it was an environment where people were just building wacky stuff like somebody built. It was like a drum machine that was with triggers tied into ping pong paddles, so you'd play ping pong and drum beats would be making it was like, it would just like making Wild Wild stuff. And it was a really good environment to be just super creative, and just try to do something totally wild. So yeah, so that was my, my big introduction to music, or programming in general was through music programming. Other than just, you know, basic, basic web stuff. And through this course of this, I wanted to present myself as like, I wanted to, I was trying to do too many things. I wanted to be like a sound designer, I wanted to be a motion graphics designer, a video editor, you know, Photoshop, but what a web developer and so I had a website that was like showing off all my work in those different aspects. And it was just like, totally all over the place. But I just was up with updated all the time with my work and portfolio and whatever. And yeah, so that was it. I was doing the website because I had to, and I would always find it really fun, right? So I graduated from school, not knowing, you know, sort of what to do, should mention, like I said, the people I graduated with are all doing huge, huge things. So like, the guy that stood next to me is he played guitar for 30 seconds from Mars, or 30 Seconds to Mars, which is Jared Leno's band. So he's like hanging out with Jared Leto all the time. And he was their audio engineer, and now he's in his own band and touring all the time. dude's amazing. The girl who's stood next to me is got second place on the voice, Michelle sham. Well, she's like, amazing. And I mean, we knew she was a good singer in school, but her like, her production and her music was always really good. So we didn't know how amazing of a singer she was. So when she was on this show, we were just like, Wow, she's just absolutely incredible. And then my friend Devin is like, he runs his own audio plugin company where they make audio plugins. He does a bunch of mastering. He did the mastering for like albums that have won Grammys and stuff like that. He's like, the big time in the audio mastering industry. And his plugins are used by all sorts of people like flying lotus and some major major producers. So he's doing it everybody's doing big things, really. So it was a really, really interesting program. So after that, I got to basically I had a job for The Guitar World Magazine, where I'd worked there as an intern for half a year doing video production where like, famous rock star would come in, you'd videotape them, you'd edit that you'd, you know, do some motion graphics, and it would go out on a DVD with the magazine. And I got that gig because my uncle was the editor in chief. So it was a really sweet summer job. And they had offered me a job coming out of school. But after graduating, you know, I had, I had been dating my wife for a little bit, and well, my soon to be wife. And at that time, we had to make like a real choice, like, do I take this career in New York? Or do I stay here? Because she was going to get her master's, and eventually her doctorate in Michigan. And, you know, I wasn't counting on the long distance thing working out. So I made I made the CD after you know, she, she really stressed like, 100% do not make this decision because of me. And it obviously, that's, you know, not going to happen that way. So yeah, I made the decision to stay in Michigan, and I turned down that job full time. So I could have been, you know, I could have been my career would have been totally Audio Video Production based at that point. And I could have stayed there. Instead, took a job as an accountant for a record label, ghostly International, and the ghost International, amazing record label. Yeah, I was an accountant.
Unknown: And money guy.
Scott Tolinski: Yes, I was a math and money guy. I ran the accounting, I was the only accountant for the label for an entire year, I had no accounting background, they were just looking for somebody. Like they're basically like, okay, our books aren't that complicated. We, you know, we we push out royalties this way. You know, you manage the QuickBooks this way. Yeah. Like, we're not looking for someone with like, you know, here's how to, you know, then Bell rover. Yeah, yeah, it was. So, you know, basically just monitoring stuff and make sure there's no alarms going off and making sure the artists get paid. I took the job, not because I wanted to be an accountant. I didn't know anything about it. It was a cool company recommended to me by a friend. I love their music. So I got a free record every single week that I worked there. And I definitely took advantage of that got totally stocked up on their catalogue. But yeah, I eventually took a job as a AV tech at the University of Michigan. And this whole time, I'm working on web stuff, right? Working on web working on web, I worked as an AV technician running projectors for the medical school at the University of Michigan. So you know, there'd be some presentation on some messed up medical disorder with like, gross gnarly pictures, and I would have to just run the projector. And I stayed in the projector booth. And I just brought my computer and I worked on stuff. I took freelance clients, I build websites, I was just working on stuff, learning Photoshop, learning coding better, just because it was fun to me, right? I mean, I had nothing to do sitting in that booth. So my parents, were starting a green tea store. I built them their site in Magento. And had to learn about databases, PHP, all that stuff through building this Magento site. Really definitely, like cut my teeth on a ton of CSS and understanding the differences. And I really struggled through it. I mean, I had no technical web programming background at this point. I'm just like, just totally, how long?
Wes Bos: How long ago was this? Just to give you just to give us an idea, like, how long ago was this? Listen,
Scott Tolinski: I was a, let's see. The T website was probably started in 2009. Okay,
Wes Bos: so yes, quite a while eight years ago,
Scott Tolinski: yeah. So while ago yeah. And, you know, I managed a website and they kept that they kept this T star for quite a while. Before closing it up, actually still have the domain for sale. So if anyone wants to buy blooming t.com you could reach out to me because I'm still not to it. Yeah. So So yeah, I mean, that's where I learned all that stuff. And because I got that confidence through building that site, like oh, I can build an e commerce site and accept payments and all this stuff like that. Like maybe I should just make some extra cash here. So I started taking jobs off Craigslist and minor gigs here in there, didn't know what I was doing, you know, got burned by a few clients who weren't interested in paying you know, that kind of stuff. And and just really learned a little bit more about web technologies. Overall, I was reading a lot of a list apart. I believe the book apart books were starting to come out then. So starting to read all those. And then, you know, I was really unhappy at work because, you know, you go there and I'm literally not doing anything. You turn on a projector and then you sit in a room for an hour until the class is over. And then you turn off the projector and then you turn it back on for the next class. I mean, it was just so Oh, it was just so boring, but it gave me a lot of time to work on stuff. So yeah, around 2011 of march of 2011. To be exact. My wife spotted a job opening for a local web dev shop. By not web dev shop, a local creative agency, like 12 people large agency was a place we had walked by a lot. And you'd see that their branding and their logo and you'd say, like, man, I would kill to work there. Because it's beautiful, right? everything they do is great work. They have big name clients. And I applied for the job because she found the job posting, I didn't even look for it, she found it knew I wasn't happy and was like, you need to, you know, you need to apply for this. I did. I had a phone interview with a guy named Ben chef, who is a huge, amazing mentor of mine. He's just one of the most important people in my career. And he took a chance he like, we had a really great phone conversation. And I knew it seemed like it was going pretty well came in to do the in person interview and they gave me a job. And I, I don't think I was a good enough developer at the time to get that job. But he definitely took a chance on me. And I started like that week, or that first week on the job building Drupal and WordPress sites in a professional environment for real clients. And I didn't know what I was doing. I was, you know, asking Ben every step of the way for you know, what he does for this and this and this. And it really like shaped my understanding of this stuff, and led me to getting to explore a bunch of new techniques, I was at a time when CSS three was really starting to come into being a major player in a way that you could actually use it with the prefixes. So we were using a lot of new fancy stuff. And, you know, you know, some stuff was new for both of us. And we could say, Hey, did you see this? Do you see this? And I mean, we sat next to each other in the same room. So we're constantly sharing web resources and cool tech and cool stuff. And just learning I mean, I feel like that was like a rocket ship. accelerated learning just shot me. Yeah, the, the the tech world in a way that I
Wes Bos: my learning was around that time too. And I remember it just being so. so mad, such a magical time when all that CSS three stuff started coming out. So exciting.
Scott Tolinski: I remember the last site that we had to do an image background to do rounded corners on. Like, I don't remember that technique where you'd have like, Oh, yeah, like a div above a div that was just an image of the rounded corners. I remember the doors It was called, was that what it's
Wes Bos: called? It was called sliding doors where you had like a div. You had like to two or three pieces, and then it would it would go horizontally based on how long the text was. Yeah,
Scott Tolinski: yeah. Okay. Yeah. So we were doing interest. I just remember a lot of that stuff. Yeah. And there was no like, web fonts at that point. It was just a lot of like, really big changes coming into web development. At that time. I remember I remember when we had a, the first site we did with web fonts was using. It's owned by Adobe. Now. I forget what it's used to be a big, big, big player. typekit typekit? Yeah, yeah, I think there's a lot of people using typekit still, but I remember when that wasn't even. I mean, we had a subscription to typekit long before it's owned by Adobe. And that was like a huge mind blower right there. See, I
Wes Bos: remember that. I dropped coupon you ever use coupon before
Scott Tolinski: that or see we never we didn't get into the coupon? Miller? Yeah, yeah, we purposely I didn't in some like private projects and stuff like that. But we did not add q
Wes Bos: just want to take a quick break to recognize our sponsor for syntax FM. Thanks so much to fresh books for sponsoring, I use fresh books myself, I've been using it for about seven years now. And it is cloud accounting, that is some of the best out there. So I just want to talk quick about some of the the parts of fresh books that I really like. And I use myself obviously, it's very, very complex software with a lot of going on in there. First one is obviously I use it to create invoices to send off to people, I don't have to mess around with any Excel documents or whatnot. Just pop the user's information in there, how much they want, what currency it's in, it'll send it off and email it off to them. Then I take all my online payments. We've previously talked about the the pain of accepting payments freshbooks interfaces with all kinds of different payment gateways, including stripe, so all my payments, go right into my stripe account, which make it into my bank account. Project deposits are pretty nice. So if you want to build someone for something you need 20% down before you get going, you can get a nice quick deposit with them. And probably my favorite feature of freshbooks is their their insights that shows you if a client has viewed the invoice or not as often I'll get a client being like, Oh, I didn't get the invoice but you can log in and see they actually did get it and they opened it up and then they open it up two or three times and then close it down. So that way you can tell if the person actually has seen your invoice and see why they're there?
Scott Tolinski: So it's always a great thing. Yeah.
Wes Bos: Yeah, actually, another nice thing about fresh books is they have like a automated, like, if someone doesn't pay will follow up with them. But it's like fresh books that it's like a bot that up, follows up with them. So it's not like you are like, tarnishing your relationship with a client with trying to get paid, which I think is is pretty important. So pretty cool, fresh books, check it out for a 30 day free trial, go to freshbooks.com slash syntax and enter these enter syntax in the How did you hear about us? Thanks so much to fresh books for sponsoring.
Scott Tolinski: So the other company I should mention is called que Ltd or que Ltd, I think their real name is quorum. And it was just 1212 people, we were the only two devs there. And we had some pretty big clients like the SIGGRAPH conference was like our biggest client. So that was a pretty high traffic site. And it was went from like, you know, I was making sites for nobody on Craigslist, really. And now all of a sudden, I'm making sites that are getting massive amounts of traffic, having gotten massive amounts of things and just got a lot better. And I hung out in that job for a while, like two or three years. And Ben Ben left actually to take a job as a dev at the University of Michigan, and left me as the senior developer there. Q So I was the senior dev for about a year with some talented dev working with me. This guy, Mike bondra is out in Seattle, now really talented guy. And he was he was on to a bunch of stuff that I wasn't onto. At this point, we were doing a lot of WordPress and Drupal. And he was on to node j s, which was brand brand new. I mean, we went to meetups and stuff like that, and trying to wrap our heads about what working in Node would even mean, and we didn't have a good work or get a good Git workflow either at this place at the time. Git was popular, but not like, totally everywhere, everywhere. So you know, Mike, Mike, and I set up a total Git workflow. And then we decided to start building and Mongo, express and node. And ej s, I believe the site was in whatever when those major template templating languages at the time. So yeah, so that's where I started to learn a little bit more about node stuff, more server side, backend stuff, and we built a really cool site. So from there, Ben, at University of Michigan was, you know, he was getting paid considerably more than I was to do like, work at U of M. and was like, basically, Hey, man, why don't you come over and work at U of M, I could probably get you a sweet gig here. So there was a little bit up in the air with the future of the company, being a small agency, you're sort of living. It's not paycheck to paycheck, but like, the company is definitely surviving on the clients it's getting, and I wasn't confident in the future of the company. They're still around, and they're doing great work. So you know, I you never know, you know, what's going to happen, but I wasn't quite super Sure, you know, how longer how much longer that opportunity would be there. So I took, took Ben up on his offer and gave got me an interview or killed the interview, and started working at U of M as a web developer for what is an internal ad agency of the University of Michigan, basically, we would only be building sites for U of M. But each department UVM operates like a little country.
Wes Bos: Yeah, it's, it's like ridiculous. Universities are like that. They have to like, apply and
Scott Tolinski: yeah, so we still had to bid on projects. So it was like U of M, it enough. We'd be bidding like against my old company and other other people like that. But, you know, they would, you know, we would have client meetings and whatever. And I found the job to be good for a lot of reasons, but like terrible for others. browser compatibility was a completely different, like, we had to support way, way, way further back like IE, so yeah. And then like q we had already dropped IE eight. I mean, we were able to be progressive on that front, because we were writing the contracts. This is University work. So I'm suddenly like, not able to use a ton of the techniques I was looking to use. When was this then if you're dropped? I ate already? 2014 Okay, 15 out of I would maybe want to double check some of these numbers and 15 things. Yeah,
Wes Bos: what, three ish years ago? Maybe?
Scott Tolinski: Yeah. That doesn't make any sense. Then I would have to check my timeline with at least dropped IE seven. So maybe that was it. And I had to just jump into the back end of the IE seven. Oh, yeah. Either way. So we were at University of Michigan and building these sites and there was like it was getting to be no fun because I couldn't use anything progressive. referred to frequently as a hipster developer buy somebody out there some of the people, I should say that there's a lot of everyone that worked there were super cool. But not everyone was super open to new tech. So like, Yeah, I was the only one for a little bit using sass. Well, actually, I shouldn't say only one Ben was using sass as well. But people were actually frequently ripping on me for using sass. Like, that's not real CSS, that's a crutch. It's just like, that's so dumb. And and actually, enough, some of these people to this day probably aren't using that stuff. And still, like sitting on this style. Like, it's
Wes Bos: funny how, how into it. We are. And then you hear stories from people that like someone emailed me the other day, they're like, they're not allowed to use ESX. Yeah. For and not because like, they have actual reasons. It's just because the team is like, no, that's stupid. Why would we do that? Like we're doing things our way.
Scott Tolinski: I interviewed for a job recently. And I was like, Oh, so using ESX. Without that they were just like, No, I was like, why you're using they're using Webpack. They were using no way they were using I'm sorry, they were using gulp. They were using Gulp as a build system. But like, it's a free ad. And then you get a whole bunch of great features. Like why wouldn't you use it? If you it's like that. They're like, Oh, we don't want to deal with compatibility issues. That's not like a thing. Yeah. If you have a it's,
Wes Bos: it's frustrating to hear hear stories like that. But it is I think it's more common than we actually think when people listen to this podcast. Oh, must be nice. But
Unknown: yeah, we're no way I can. Exactly.
Wes Bos: Yeah. So it's so yeah, you're at U of M creative.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah. And I mean, that's where I got to, like, really experience a lot of these issues where you don't get to work on the stuff you want to work on. I found, like the pace of the projects to be extremely slow, like project manager sitting on sites for months. And it's just like, okay, I've completed all of my work for the next like four months, like, What am I supposed to do other than just sit here? So I started learning a lot of Angular stuff at the time. Yep. And so just really going through the front end framework, I learned backbone, I learned Ember, I didn't learn any of them particularly well, except for Angular. But I did enough to like, I got a tour of the front end frameworks at the time, like Marionette and backbone. Ember, and both Ember data was just starting to be a thing. And I liked Angular the best because it was obviously the easiest, it looked a lot like HTML. And it just felt really nice. Right? Okay, this is data binding is pretty amazing. Because doing that, without Angular would have been a pain in the ass. So yeah, I started making a bunch of stuff for fun in Angular, and I loved it. I really enjoyed it. I really like the super powers it was giving me and then I got a sort of out of the blue job requests through I think it was even through LinkedIn. And they were basically saying, hey, how would you like to build for.com? It's just sort of like, well, this is a it's not, it's not an opportunity to say no to I didn't work at U of M created for an entire year. I don't think I think I only worked there for like, eight months total. And I just booked it out to go build for.com. Because, well, I should say it was also like a double in in paycheck. So it was like a huge, huge opportunity, right? And it fell into my lap. Like, here. You know, the interview was like, really nice and easy. You know, always known interviews going well, when you're talking to like the technical manager about some web tech. And they're like taking notes about the stuff you're saying like, Oh, I didn't know. So I felt really good about the interview, got the gig. And I got put on a team of three really good developers. Well, I should say two really good developers, one of which who couldn't cut it got fired and like the first two weeks, and that like woke me in the sky, Jeff Marcel, who was awesome developer from Detroit, it kind of woke us up a whole ton. Like, okay, don't mess this up. huge opportunity. We started building some major, major interfaces for Ford and Angular. And we got to choose the direction technical direction of this entire project. Like if we wanted to do something some way Yeah, he and I could make these choices. Now the caveat here is our work isn't going on for.com. We're a part of a team of people who were developing design experiments and interface experiments. So we would work with the designers who would come up with something not even super radical, but radical for Ford standards, right? And then yeah, it was our job to quickly prototype this up in a way that was like fully usable with real data, and that we could eventually point the other markets to like, China, whoever to say, Hey, this is how you do it. here's the here's our code. Here's our CSS, whatever. And our whole goal was to build out this like style guide full of Angular code. Opponents that were essentially like, this is how you're supposed to do it. But my physical code did not end up on the site, right? It's ridiculous. They have like 90 some markets for for it right. And all of those markets are on their own platform. Like some of them could be Drupal, some of them could be a custom thing, you literally have no idea what these platforms are. So instead of like building a big platform, they're just like, here, you just write the front end code, and we're pushed out, and we'll leave it to their developers to implement it. The bummer of that is, is that some of those developers didn't implement our stuff very well. Some of them didn't, didn't implement it at all. Some of them just flat out refuse thing. They didn't know how we got people saying, I don't know how to do this. I don't know how to make this. So Wow. Also, at the end of the day, you know, they spent a bunch of money on us to do this really great design, exploitative work, and the designers were awesome. We had a team of like 30, some people. You know, one of the guys who worked on like the Domino's app was on it. Like just like people from the industry in our field that were all super good. Jeff and I as developers are super good. And we brought in another developer, this guy, Bobby, from part of Michigan, that Ben lived in, and he was super good. And so we just have a lot of like, really great talent. And Bobby was like, really super into RX js, he was into react, he was into a lot of functional programming stuff and like sort of blew our minds with some of that stuff. Same time. I'm learning Meteor getting into that. Yeah,
Wes Bos: what when? And when did you start level up? tuts? Obviously at this point, you are going on YouTube, right? Yeah,
Scott Tolinski: I totally glanced over that one. So in 2000, in 2011, back when I worked at that small agency que Ltd, I worked with Ben and Ben and I used to like get so mad. We were doing a ton of Drupal work because that's like what our agency like to do. And yeah, we we would be like, oh, x documented feature isn't documented Great. Well, like, why isn't this documented anywhere? So we were just getting really like mad with the state of Drupal docs, and went through and just started making a bunch of tutorials. Oddly enough, he was doing expression engine tutorials and I was doing work or Drupal tutorials, teaching the stuff that we felt like was overlooked and so we both started level up tuts level up tuts at the time now level up tutorials and the logo was designed by our internet cue Mike McMillan who's like a super good designer like he's he's doing freelance right now. So if you need like really excellent design work Mike McMillan I think his website is Mike Nick chillin. Super cool guy but so he did our he did our logo for us and like a hackathon style. And we just built the site and I'd say Ben maybe recorded like 50 ish tutorials for level up tuts before he had a couple of kids. And life was not super easy to record tutorials all the time, obviously, you know, that's like a, he'd get home from work. And last thing you want to do is record a few tutorials. So he had to hit the to bail out but you know, and honestly, I have like an open door policy for Ben. So if he ever wanted to step in, and like record some cuts, I would be 100% anytime he wants to do that. So you know, he and I put in a ton of work on this thing to get going. And we just had this idea of like, hey, tutorials should be easy. There should be more of them. There should be more documentation. Like why don't we just record 100 tutorials really quickly and get that out there in the world just became a thing I did after some time and even though he stopped I never was super interested in stopping so I just kept hammering it through. I started actually the level of tutorials origin story itself is pretty intense. I got a concussion through breakdancing. I have the video on YouTube. It's not public, but I have the video real basically just like drop myself on my head on like tile floor. It sucks. My head bounces off the floor. It's it's totally gnarly. I ended up I did it the day before our engagement photos for my wife and I and I like woke up the next morning and like half my face was bruised and she was just like, come on, man. So we obviously had to reschedule those. But yeah, so because I had a concussion I was out from February to I was out of commission of like doing activities like working out or you know, dancing from February to September. So by February or by March I had already created level up with Ben so I was just like going stir crazy. I'm kind of like, not totally hyperactive, but I you know got to doing stuff. It's like, Ben, I'm going out here. Let's let's just do this right now. Like we both know, this is good idea. So let's just do it. So I, so those are march of 2000. So 2011 No, that would been march of 2012 that we started this. So we started level up march of 2012. And yeah, that's, that's pretty much it. And I just kept it going. So this whole time I'm working at team Detroit, you can follow this progression along in my tutorials. If you look at the level of tutorials like videos, you can see the progression of exactly all of these jobs that I'm talking about. It's actually kind of ridiculous. I'm working at ACU all the videos are about Drupal, I'm working at U of M, the videos are about WordPress, because I was doing a lot of WordPress, I'm working at Ford, the videos are about Angular, working at, you know, at that same time, I'm doing Meteor stuff. So video start to be about Meteor. And then when the Ford gig is over. By that time, because we were doing all Angular, it's when I dove into react, then a video start to be about react. So the level of tutorials like YouTube videos, like absolutely mirror what I'm working on at work, I would work on stuff all day long, come home, record three cuts or whatever. And then call it an evening, my wife was getting her PhD. So like she's studying and working all evening, she had nothing to like she was like off on her own studying. I had nothing to do other than entertain myself, which I'm pretty good at. So
made 1000 tutorials. That's how I Wow. So yeah. So yeah, after that Ford was just a contract gig project is over. The guy who got it the best out of that was Jeff, who is who got hired on to maintain the style guide. And I should put maintain in quotes, because he just sat and looked at it for like half a year and year and got paid for it while doing freelance work. So I wasn't so lucky. So I branched out and I was already living and we moved to Denver, I actually hilarious story we were I was working in Detroit in Dearborn, right at Ford. And I told them, I was like, so I'm gonna be moving to Denver, like expecting them to give like, that'd be my two weeks notice, right? This is my two weeks notice. And they were just like, yeah, we know. So like, just send the computer back when your contracts over whatever. And I was just like, Wait, what? So they, for some reason, erroneously thought that I had already written into my contract that I would be working remotely at some point. I did all. And I did not correct them. It was just like, Yes, I will be working remotely. And we all know that. Yeah, like, let's just continue this idea. And so because of that, I got to come out here and work on the Ford project for like six more months. And that was nice, because, you know, I got to work was really fun. Got to do that work somewhere. And while I was out here, just decided, hey, you know, when this contracts up, I'm gonna try level up full time, and started recording a lot more tutorials doing more premium content, Iran stuff. Yeah, so and, you know, now that I decided to do the level up full time, it was a lot of decisions about really building my own platform. So in the past level up, tut's had been built on Drupal. And we'd sort of maintained it that way, for a long time, because it was easy, you know, there was built in JSON importers and stuff in the Drupal that would drop your JSON directly into your your schema, essentially. And it was really nice, but you know, Drupal has its issues. It's complex, it's kind of a pain in the ass to do anything custom. I mean, there's a lot of abilities to expand and whatever. But like, I remember, Ben, Ben will find this hilarious. He's listening, because there was like a moment we were at a hackathon, or code party or whatever. We were just working on the level up site. And Mike, our designer was like, Hey, why don't you just do it this way? And we both look at each other. And Ben and I are just like, cuz it's Drupal. And he's like, oh, but I got an idea. How about we do it this other way? And then we're just like, because it's Drupal. Like That was our answer for everything, because there's just like a pain in the ass to do anything. So you know, making that decision to move off of that platform, I decided to build my own suite of sites I built the level of tutorial site as well as the store both is like separate Meteor sites that are like totally custom ecommerce store as well as like a totally custom site, of which I actually have recently merged the two because they were sharing a database anyways. But there I mentioned before, there was a lot of complexities and how they handled sharing things across. I mean, there were several components that I literally had to duplicate just because they're in two code bases. And they don't need to be in two code bases. I didn't want to make them a package because it just added a layer of complexity I wasn't super excited about. So both of these sites were built. You know, with the understanding that it would be able to grow and get fully customized. Obviously, you have to maintain both of those sites on like the only developer on all of this stuff the whole time, I built my e commerce platform in a weekend, just like after struggling through that the idea of Should I build this or not. And then I remember, my wife was in psyched about it, I just like, locked myself in a room for a weekend and like worked my brains out until I had a little e commerce platform that was like, it's getting better and better all the time. But it's obviously missing a ton of stuff at the time, but it worked. So
you know, now it's now it's part of the suite of sites. And I love that control of having these platforms that I built in, you know, one day, I would obviously love to have more developers working on them, you know, we'll see if the level of tutorials can support that at any time, and just be able to grow that way. Because the sites are great. I'm really psyched about them and use it as like a playground to try out all the new stuff. And it's always great thing to have is like this, the site that exists that, you know, you have full control over if I want to use x technology for this, oh, if I want to, oh, let me maybe throw in Apollo in there. Maybe I'll just try it out on one collection and see if it works, right. So, you know, these sites exist as a playground for me, but they're also like a huge learning experience. It was the first time I'd ever built an e commerce site outside of CMS outside of Magento, or WordPress, or anything like that. So yeah, you know, you grow exponentially by these projects that you're able to just get get yourself self motivated by right. I'm motivated to build this stuff, because it's a level up tutorials is my baby, right? So I'm so motivated to build these platforms that I'm going to go nuts learning this technology to make these things nice. So you know, some advice there is really just to, like, again, follow your interests and to let those interest drive you into New Tech. Let those things drive you into really like exploring new things. And just growing that way by just purely sheer excitement, right?
Wes Bos: Yeah, I think that's so important. Don't pick up stuff because you think it's what you should be doing. Just keep following what you're excited about. I think that's one common theme you'll hear over and over in this podcast.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, if you're not excited about something, you're not going to learn it well, and you're not going to be happy doing it. And I've always prioritized personal happiness over like, most things in my work, right? It's like,
Wes Bos: Yeah, well, I think the best way to say that is you can make $150 an hour being a SharePoint developer.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, exactly.
Wes Bos: Yeah. Apologies to the SharePoint developers in the crowd, but no fun.
Scott Tolinski: It's not fun. And then maybe it is fun for some people. But yeah, it's certainly not fun for me. And like, I like having that freedom and being able to explore all the new new fun stuff. And I still I used that like that hipster developer sort of, like slight I was given at my one job is like, I don't know, I wear that as sort of like a, you know, way to like, bash me fraud. Yeah. badge of pride, right. I mean, I'm not like, I don't know. I'm a developer. Yeah, it's like I was into new, new exciting technologies. I what a huge bummer. That is, right. Yeah. Like I was trying new things and not doing the same thing over and over again. Yeah. And, you know, just to give Michigan some Michigan creative some credit to there was another developer there named Wally Colts, who is like, he was into some really, really cool stuff. And I don't feel like enough people are listening to his direction, right. So he was, he was on some like, what was it when Facebook had released their hip hop thing? Do you know what I'm talking about?
Wes Bos: Yeah. php VM?
Scott Tolinski: Yeah. Is it? Is it hip hop for PHP? Is that what it's called? Yeah. So PHP, transpiler. by Facebook, I mean, he was on that, like, the day it was out. And I remember him, like telling us all about it. And like, I didn't really necessarily understand it at the time, but I don't remember anybody else being super excited about it. And that kind of bums me out to write like a series on some Yeah.
Wes Bos: Why would you rewrite PHP? Yeah,
Scott Tolinski: yeah. Well, yeah. But either way, like, I don't know, they're, you know, they're there are those people and like, if you have that person at work, who's on to some, like, really exciting or interesting stuff, I mean, really reach out to them and, and get up on some of that stuff, too. I mean, those people are happy, typically happy to share what they know. So yeah. And yeah, I worked for a startup for about a year echa which is like a full stack thing that I built entirely myself get@yahoo.com it's not like there yet. I think that they need some money to make it go any further. But really, it's it's basically like a really modern booking app. It's like Instagram meets booking, you find a tattoo artist you like, you want to book them directly from their hairstylist you like you want to book them directly from there. Like I said, it needs a little bit more before it crosses that finish line. So we'll we'll see if that ends up. Going into We're not but yeah so for the past year so I've been doing that it was an opportunity given to me by a friend out here. And the whole time level of tut's right level of tut's has just been hanging out and making content all the time. And so now that the startup is not my, my main thing on my plate anymore, there's a lot more content a lot more improvements. And basically, level up tutorials is 100% the forefront once again, and I'm really, really psyched to be doing it all the time now.
Wes Bos: Wow. Yeah. So
Scott Tolinski: that I mean, it's, it's wild, right? It's not non typical stories, right? I worked as an accountant, and an AV tech, Ken Ham projectors. Yeah. I wanted to do motion graphics full time. That was my like, dream job. And then I discovered that I liked programming more. And now that you can do motion graphics in programming, like, I love motion graphics. Oh, man. Yeah.
Wes Bos: I love that. That's like such a good story. Because it really does show that like, you didn't go to school for this and then became a developer. Like you're all over the place. And one thing led to another little interests led to another thing, and, and you're where you're at right now. And that's probably motivating to someone who's just getting started right now. Yeah, 510 years from now, you might you might not know where you're gonna be, right?
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, I was several years out of college before I even got my first programming job. And I honestly credit all of the major like, Major, big things to my wife, because she found the job for the web developer. She also looked at my website and was like, you are trying to do too many things. Like why do you want to be a sound designer or emotion designer, a graphic artist, like what do you want to be all of these things? Like, just pick one. And obviously, I picked the one that was most like, personally satisfying, which was programming, right? You solve a bunch of problems, and you get all that gratification of everything comes in, you fix all these problems, and you feel good about it. So I picked programming because she made me pick something and I couldn't be any happier with that choice.
Wes Bos: It's amazing. Wow. That is pretty cool. I don't know any any final words lessons learned about about your whole journey? Yeah.
Scott Tolinski: Like, you get the places you get because you, you follow the things that make you excited. And so you know, I followed the technologies that made me excited, I went off and went a little bit rogue, right, you know, we're all doing WordPress or whatever work. I was excited by Angular. I did Angular stuff. I was excited by sass I did sass. Nobody told me that I could do that. And if I couldn't do it for a work project, I was doing it in a side gig. So it's like, he let let the things that excite you pull you into new things. And you know, be Don't be afraid to jump on that you don't want to be the guy who's sitting there building a site with, you know, last 10, I don't know, centuries old tech, thinking like, I can do this forever. Right? You're you you're going to be the webmaster exactly right. I
Wes Bos: think I think one thing that that comes from your story is that like your career is not like an incline your your careers more it is obviously it's an incline. But it's what do you call that it's not a smooth transition. It's May there's major steps that you took in your career, and they were all huge steps up for you. So it's not like you were just doing like, every day you got a little bit better. It's that you took these massive risks and these big jumps from job to job to job where your salary had doubled, or you took on an entirely new technology. And I think that if you see people where you're like, how did they even get there? It's it's almost always like, Oh, I was doing this one thing. And then I totally switch to something else. And that was a huge step up in my career.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah. And is the ability to take risks and to jump into those new things. And, you know, I've got some really good advice from my dad who's had a really great career. He's a automotive engineer. And I asked him, you know, when no, one of the jobs came up with just like, I forget what it I think it was the Michigan creative job came up, I'm just like, I don't know what to do. You know, I really love working for this agency, I have all this freedom, I'm gonna have less freedom at this new place. And he was like, I'm not gonna tell you to do anything in particular, but every time I had an opportunity to jump, I jumped. Yeah, not to jump to a new job, but like jump into something new and exciting. If there's something to jump forward. He said, You know, every time I had an opportunity, I took it so you know not to saying you should take it but you know, who knows?
Wes Bos: Yeah, absolutely. That's really cool.
Scott Tolinski: Okay, and now it's time for a sick pics, in which we give our sick pics, basically the sickest of pics. And since I give my story today, I'll be giving a sick pic and in the West Story, which is part two of this episode, he'll be giving his sick pick at the end of his story. So, yes, my sick pick this week is someone I mentioned before. My buddy Devin Kerr, he started his audio plugin with company, which is good hertz.co was the website hertz is spelled H e, r t z. So good hertz.co he makes up some insanely excellent audio plugins. And what I mean by that is these things aren't really things you're going to find anywhere else. And, you know, I say this as even though this guy's like probably my best friend forever. Yeah, I've known him since like the eighth grade. And we went through college together. And, you know, we keep in touch like crazy. But like, regardless if he was the one making these or not, these things are as as real as it gets, like I mentioned before, you know, artists like flying lotus, and people use his plugins, if you're familiar with the band vulfpeck, you'll notice one of his plugins is the volt compressor, which is made with vulfpeck. He's, uh, he did the mastering for the vulfpeck album. So a lot of his work is like, it's just, it's stuff that doesn't exist anywhere else. Like he he did his master's thesis on, like, 3d sound space. So like, basically, you have an interface where you want to put a sound somewhere, right? Like, you have your headphones, it's for headphones, right? It's a thing called can opener. And you can say like, I want this sound to be in the top left up over here, or like five meters away, or I want this down to be bone over here, like 10 meters away. And like I said, he did all this his his masters work on understanding the positional audio. So these plugins are just awesome. And they're not totally useful for all situations. Like, he has the volt compressor, right, which is a compressor. And if you use two audio plugins, it compresses your audio sort of evens out levels, you can think of it doing a sort of like that, but there's both compressor you would not use for her, like spoken word or something like that. Because it's it's supposed to be made for a very specific sound of like 1970s analog compressor emulation. So, you know, there's like all of these have a very specific use, but you won't find anything else like them. So yeah, good. hertz is excellent, excellent stuff also was designed work for them. I don't think he personally did the design, but like the design on all of the plugins is as good as it gets. None of those like fake skeuomorphic knobs that you have to turn on a lot of audio plugins. So
Unknown: yeah,
Scott Tolinski: it's he took a very different approach to it. He's been doing this stuff for a very long time. And obviously, he knows what audio engineers want to see out of their stuff. So yeah, I highly recommend if you're doing any sort of audio work, you're working with recording music or production. Good hertz. The prices are super reasonable. You're getting some like totally unique plugins and packages and stuff like that. Obviously, this isn't an ad. Andy's a good friend, but if neither of those things were true, I'd still be recommending these plugins.
Wes Bos: sec.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, sir Keck. Yup. So join us in the part two, where we give Wes his origin story in here. Wes is sick. Head on over to syntax FM for a full archive of all our shows. Don't forget to subscribe in your podcast player and drop a review if you liked this show. Until next time,