Announcer: Monday Monday Monday open wide dev fans yet ready to stuff your face with JavaScript CSS node module BBQ Tip Get workflow breakdancing soft skill web development hasty as crazy as tasty as web development treats coming in hot here is Sarah CUDA boss and Scott Taylor. Totally in ski.
Scott Tolinski: Whoo, welcome to syntax and this Monday tasty treat, we're going to be talking about our newer laptops. And that is the new MacBook Pro is 16 inch for web development. Specifically, we've seen a lot of people cover this topic in the means of maybe video editing, or audio editing or graphic design. How many Photoshop files can you open with the new MacBook Pros, but we're gonna be approaching it from an entirely different angle as to people who have largely used Mac computers to do all of their web development. Wes Bos and I are going to be talking all about how we have found the new 16 inch MacBook Pro so far for our development workflows. My name is Scott Tolinksi. I'm a developer from Denver, Colorado, and with me, as always, is the West boss. Sup, everybody. So this episode is sponsored by Sentry. Now, if you you want to be able to buy a MacBook Pro yourself, you got to write software that's free of bugs. And to do so you want to have a service like Sentry to catalog and capture all of your bugs. Now one of my favorite features of Sentry is the ability to attach a single bug to a specific software release. And you could even attach that to a specific commit with your source vamps and everything. So the cool thing about that is you can tell exactly which release introduced which bug and how many people that bug is affecting. And then from there, you can fix that bug, you can mark it as fixed. And then if that bug comes up, it's gonna say, hey, there's a regression in this bug because of XYZ commit. And like, really, is there any greater visibility than understanding what you introduced into your code that caused your user some error? So Sentry is the error and Exception Handling tool that we love and use over here at syntax? Check it out@sentry.io use the coupon code at tasty treat all lowercase all one word, and you'll get two months for free. So check it out@sentry.io coupon code tasty. Treat. Cool. So let's get into it here. I think we should start off by maybe talking about why our previous computers sucked. And then we could talk about why we changed or what what you know what's different about them? Yeah, so we both had the last generation MacBook Pro mine was over two years old at the time, and the hardware is still a super fast computer. And I had it plugged into my dock and everything drove on my monitors. And like all of that was awesome. is just the fact that the actual laptop part of it was awful. So you've probably heard there's the keyboards would get like a crumb nature Valley stuck in it. And my battery just ballooned and they had to replace the entire like bottom half of the computer. Apparently, there was no escape key the keyboard was hard to type on. We both had ours in the shop for like a week you've had yours in shop for what like three weeks something like that. Yeah, for three weeks, my my, my command keys stopped working. And because of that, apparently, that was a three week fix, which involved a one of the apple servers texts actually breaking my screen, stashing my computer somewhere in there, their system, and then lying about it. So then Apple came in and gave me a bunch of stuff for free. So that was pretty sweet. Which is actually funny because I bought my computer at the same time that you did those the 2017 or something model. Yeah. And they gave me my computer as our 2018. So did I need this 2016? No, but it was just ruining my life. So many ways that we'll get into what we'll do with our old machines and stuff. But for the most part, it was just it was a huge fiasco. It was an absolute huge fiasco, all because of a darn chrome under a command key. Oh,
yeah, it's super frustrating. So the new ones have will go through the settings, but they have greatly improved, absolutely everything. And spoiler, at least for me, it's awesome. I'm so happy to have a back like this. The I think the MacBook Pro is like a workhorse for a web developer. It's like the laptop. I know that there's like Windows users and Linux users and stuff like that. And we'll talk about why we don't use those. But like, we think that this if you have the money to spend because they're expensive as heck. But if you have the money, this is the laptop I think you should buy as a web developer. So let's let's go into like, what were the specs? What did you get Scott? Yeah,
I learned this thing out man. I loaded it up. So we can talk a little bit about why too but I got the 64 gigs of RAM which is totally overkill, the highest processor which is a 2.2 For eight core i nine, and then the highest video cam or video card which is a dedicated eight gigabytes A and D radium pro five or five the one on the one a 550 hundred m card. I don't know how they the pros say that card name. But man I loaded this thing up and I got the two terabyte hard drive. And I did so for maybe a little bit different reasons I want to play a I have a lot of games on my old hackintosh that used to dual boot. And I haven't gotten to play any of those games in a long time because I took apart my hackintosh. So I loaded this thing up with the specific intent of not only having it be a video master for me, but also with the intent of being able to dual boot and throw windows on here and play some life video games. Which I'm going to do Yeah, awesome. I did not load mine up nearly as much as you did, but it's still insane.
laptop that I have a well I got the 2.838 Core i nine which I got 1000 DMS on Instagram, although I nines run hot, they'll crash. And so part of part of the like Apple had this big thing where they used to throttle the CPU because so they didn't get too hot.
But in the freezer and yeah, yeah. So now apparently that's fixed because the new MacBook is slightly thicker. And I have been running I've just got I've been running it on full blown video export for 24 hours right now. And the thing is, it's hot, but not nearly as hot as my old one would get just browsing the web, which is amazing. Yeah, 32 gigs of RAM on it, which is more than enough for a couple of VS code instances in Chrome. Dev open. I got the one terabyte just because I wanted to be able to revert back to my old one, which is one terabyte as well. If I ever need to just Time Machine backup. I've done that a couple times. I certainly would like another terabyte in there. But no, it helps me have good good hygiene. It's It's frustrating, because like video takes up so much. But like, like one terabyte will probably be enough for the entire world. If you're just a web developer, right? You don't even need one terabyte. I think that is about it. Obviously they're both 16 inch, which is one inch bigger than the old one. I can't really tell the difference on the bigger screen. Can you Yeah, I can. Slightly Yeah, yeah. Especially because I was running them side by side for a minute here. So you know, I'm still migrating whatever. But when I see them side by side, definitely. But another thing that I did with this one verse, My old laptop as I'm running this in the scaled resolution or the like the most zoomed out as possible resolution Yeah, and the display settings, which I wasn't doing before. And I have so much more room for activities now. It is outrageous. It's everything feels way bigger to me, but it's also probably a little bit of that as well. I do like how the screen reaches further to the edges. That looks very nice to me.
Yeah, I love that too. It's just nice. A lot of space. What I usually do with my resolution is I'll bump it down as low or as as low as it can go maybe one up from there and then all of the like yeah, and then just just scale up tax because that's all I really need. Like I don't want the tabs and all that stuff to get in the way that just leads for lots and lots of room to work with.
Yeah, like the toolbar up top and whatever. Did you get applecare on yours? Of course Yeah, I got dude after my my fiasco with Apple not getting anything without Apple care. Because Yeah, I To be honest, I've had enough issues I believe it or not the last time it wasn't even the first time that Apple's given me an entirely new computer one time I bought the very first gen MacBook Pro like the very first when they went from power book to MacBook Pro. Yeah. And they like slathered, an insane amount of thermal paste in those there was a huge thermal paste issue. And my computer had like three logic boards die and all sorts of issues, the power cord caught on fire. And so one time I went into the Apple store, and I was like, Listen, this computer has given me a lot of trouble over the past two years. Like I just need a new computer. And they're like no, we don't do that. And then they were like well, let's just pull up your your Apple sheet and it was four pages long of repairs. And they're just like, oh, crap, like, we got to do something here. So despite all of your all of your issues, they've always made it right yeah, yeah, you still think it's like the best laptop you can buy us I'm sure there's some people listening right there being like Oh, I got lots of troubles. Yeah, right. What are the what I'm going to do run Windows?
Announcer: No, no, I
Scott Tolinski: would honestly probably not mind running Linux if there was actually support or it like Don't know Linux people get mad about that. But
yeah, what's like video editing is our kind of our job right? And like, I need like a rock solid. And no, you can do video editing on Linux. But honestly, I just I'm not worth I'm not interested in babysitting something like that. And having to like that was younger Wes, I just need the thing to work mostly. Yeah, let's back up, just in case. Um, what else the keyboard on this thing, they switch back to the butterfly keys, which feels exactly like the magic keyboard, which is what I use all day long. And honestly, that was the best keyboard ever. I love it so much. I'm so happy that it's back. I can type way faster, Make way less mistakes on this thing.
So far, I've noticed the type thing has been a great experience for me as well. really liking it. One thing that's taken a little bit getting used to is the Escape key is back right we have a physical key for an escape key, but I got so used to just lightly touching it even though I Oh, I hated the touch bar. But I found myself like three or four times just touching the key and not actually pushing it. And then like oh yeah, you have to push it now. Which is kind of funny that I've been like trained to you know, not push the Escape key. But I like that it's back. I like the Touch ID a lot better on this one. You can actually like find it since it's its own dedicated little module rather than just being like part of the strip.
Yeah, it's tactile, especially because like I have mine docked over to the left of me. And I love using Touch ID so over typing in my password all the time. And I have to just like throw my hand over there and touch it. While I'm like looking at what's going on on the screen. And having it as a tactile button is so much better. Big fan of that. The touch ID is just awesome. In general, I
kind of bombed that they didn't go for face ID in the new ones. The cameras are gonna be getting a bump, probably in the next one. If you think about it. They're so old and laggy behind. Yeah, the cameras are what 720 p it's not very good. They're from the dinosaur age. I have no idea. Like
I run I just attend ADP webcam from Logitech. And it looks good, but I really want just like a really nice 4k webcam without having to do what you're doing, which is hook up a DSLR and pipe that in. It's not a DSLR West. It's a mirrorless Okay, is that Oh, yes. I mean, it's a Sony Alpha, Alpha seven, three,
Unknown: or whatever it is.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah. And yes, I am running a 4k webcam and I love it. But it's not really a webcam. What else? speed the computer is very fast. Oh my god. Yeah, very fast. And yeah, I haven't even come close to using all of the RAM and anything in my I love I step menus up, they're telling me Oh, you have used 5% of your CPU or 5% of your RAM. So that's pretty good. For me. The trackpad is always is just the best. That's you know, that's sort of like a killer feature for me on the Mac is that I've never had a trackpad on a PC, a Chromebook or anything that's felt anything like the trackpad on a Mac. And I'm a trackpad fan. Like I don't use the mouse. I'm sorry, most people. But even as my like external mouse is the Magic Trackpad. Just because I like I really love the trackpad. I don't know how to express that, for some reason that I've just always been very into the feel of the trackpad. So big fan, I found that it's super fast as well. I never had any speed issues with my old one. My old one is almost two and a half years old. And it was still like flying like, Yeah, mine was outrageous. Yeah, if it wasn't for the like, like these laptops, the amount you pay, you should have them for at least four, maybe five years for how much you pay. And in that thing, if it wasn't bad, like keyboard and hardware, the things we talked about that thing would have lasted forever. Like I still have my I still have my the good one with the HDMI ports. And that thing is like six, six years old, and I booted it up the other day, and it's just flying. It's still super fast, like, like, I think like we're at a point, especially for web developers that the pace of these things is outpacing kind of what we need, which is good because like as a web developer, you should also be able to just go and buy a $400 laptop as well and get up and running. It's just that I think like Scott and I since we do media, and podcasts and all this stuff, we do need something a little bit more beefy. Yeah, it's really nice to be able to screen capture in 4k, record a video stream in 4k and record my audio or whatever. I'll do all of those things without the computer even thinking right? Just like Okay, sure. So, you know, for me, this kind of beefy system is absolutely required for what I'm doing. The amount of video editing a video production, all that stuff. They said, Look, the render times are sliced in half between this computer and even the last model. So we're several models behind that. So the amount of performance gains we're getting is really sort of game changing along with the keyboard right we're screen casting, and anybody who's watched any Level Up tutorials in the past year will note that I do apologize for my keyboard when I goofs up on me like you can't really help it because it's like the keyboard occasionally does double presses and this or that. And, man, I can't have that stuff in my content I just straight up can have it. Yeah. Other things that didn't upgrade the ports, which is unfortunate. So they're still just four USBC. They're technically Thunderbolt, which is faster, but they're the same port as USBC. And that sucks at the carry. I have like a really nice little dongle I carry around. But the fact that I have to carry around a dongle, like how many times have I been like, Oh, I don't have a USB C converter on me right now. And I need to charge this thing or I need to plug it in. And it's so annoying. And like I get that USB C is the future. But I've had a USB C computer for almost three years now. And I still every day run into that might just give me one regular USB a port. And that would be enough for me to for those little situations. But totally fortunately, they're not going to give it to us.
Unknown: No, never, never.
Scott Tolinski: Let's go into some why nots. So why not a Windows computer, Scott, I just hate windows. I'm sorry, I tried. And I actually have Windows installed on this machine. So it's not like I haven't used it. I use Windows frequently. But man, there's just something about Windows where like, half of the icons are from Windows 98 still are like, I don't know what it is with the experience. But like, I don't know if they haven't done this or what but they need to start from scratch. Like they need to have, like a totally fresh operating system, that where everything is where it is. But like there's so many weird things to get into Device Manager, you got to click on this and this and this and this. And it all looks like you're in 1994, you went into a time machine. That's it. I do like the base thing of Windows 10. I like where the star bar is. I like the way that it functions with their little dock. I like a lot of the features in Windows, but I cannot see myself running Windows. They're doing obviously Microsoft's doing better things than they were before. But this it's still on. It's still windows, I can't I can't do it. Yeah, I have. So I've got a Surface Book that Microsoft gave me. Try to coax me over to Windows and I love it for recording windows parts of my tutorials. That's great. I love it for testing. And I spent a lot of time getting all of the windows subsystem Linux stuff, because I'm like, if I'm going to move to Windows, I need like my, my terminal, I need all my commands. And all of that stuff just worked. It was amazing. But I think it's part, I don't want to relearn something because I got enough on my plate right now. And like, I'm not 17 anymore, and I don't have time to tinker around with. And also like anytime we have an app like Alfred, people are like, what's the Windows version and the replies on Twitter and someone's like, hey, there's this but like, ask, it's not as good. You know, like, ah, and I ran into that with Android to where like, I love Android as an operating system. But there'd be so many times I'd be like, Oh, this doesn't exist for Android Nexus for Windows. And it makes me very upset, you know? Yeah, so I don't know, I just don't have time to move over to it. I'm sure it's great. I'm sure there's a lot of people that love it for for what they do or make do. But I just I'm so engrained in having Mac and how fast it is, and, and my workflow and all my keyboard shortcuts that is I'm just not going to move over to that. Totally. Next up, why not a hackintosh I had a hackintosh do I have it. I haven't booted it up in a long time. And it was super reliable, super fast. But then, like, every time a new update came, he had to like find the new kexts and all the drivers and everything like that and upgrade the thing and like it was a really fun hobby because I like doing that sort of thing. But I just need a machine that is fast and that I can bring to the geniuses when it breaks. Yeah. And then just go backwards on my other one. Will they fix it? Like I need almost zero downtime was my job. And I can't afford to fuss around with something like that. Even though it was it's I think it's much more reliable than then people think it is. Totally. Yeah, absolutely. And my hackintosh was great. I ran one for so many years. But again, anytime an update came out you had to spend a weekend making sure everything was fine on it. Like he said if something breaks like that used to just like absolutely, totally disrupt my entire life and when level up tutorials was a side project. Sure that worked but a little tutorials is my entire business and livelihood so I can't trust a hackintosh to do that right now. And why not an iMac which is ah, I've had desktop computers in the past and you know what my very first computer was an iMac g4 and you know what I did? I sold it and bought a netbook pro because I just I loved having the the beef Enos of a desktop computer, but at the end of the day, man nothing beats being able to take this beast with me. Take it to a Coffee Shop, I'm not going to be that hipster who's walking around holding on their iMac and bringing into a coffee shop, that's not going to happen. Things got 64 gigs of RAM and eight gigs of video. memory. So like, I don't know, man, it's a pretty beast.
I have a desktop computer and it's my laptop plugged into my doc. I don't want to computers because I need to I go and teach workshops, I go to conferences, I go to the coffee shop every now and then I just need to be able to bring my computer somewhere else. And I don't want to have to fuss around with having two instances of things and I forgot to get push and the sink didn't work or I closed the laptop before the sink updated or, or any of that stuff. I just don't want two computers. It's it's expensive. And it's it's too much to fuss with. I just want one rock solid computer, which is why I think we've we've put so much money into these things. It just works pretty well.
Totally cool. Well, that's all I got. I'm excited to see where this thing goes. I'm gonna see how many chrome tabs I can get open at once. That should be pretty sweet. Awesome. Thanks for tuning in. We will catch you on Wednesday later these days.
Announcer: Head on over to syntax.fm
Unknown: for a full archive of all of our shows.
Scott Tolinski: And don't forget to subscribe in your podcast player or drop a review if you like this show.