Unknown: You're listening to syntax the mind cast with the tastiest web development treats out there. strap yourself in and get ready. Here is Scott, ski and West boss.
Wes Bos: Welcome to syntax. This is the podcast with the tastiest web development tricks. Today we're gonna be talking all about the ups and downs of school boot camp self learning, part time learning with a mentor, what is the best way? Or what are the the pros and cons to learning in different ways? I know there's a lot of talk where people say like, you don't need a comp side degree or should you go to school for this versus like, is a boot camp worth all that money? It seems like a lot of money and to spend in such a short amount of time, are you actually going to get a job from that sort of thing. So we actually have experience in I think almost all of these situations, I think we're pretty well we're pretty well placed to talk about this. And I've also talked to a lot of people that actually work in the industry, and they've all come up in different ways. So it's gonna be an interesting topic with me. Today's is a guest, Scott Tolinksi Gate now. The co host of this podcast How you doing? Scott?
Unknown: I'm doing good. I'm doing real good. Ready to go? You know, it's it's early March. I'm 33. I'm feeling 33 Yeah,
Wes Bos: happy birthday.
Unknown: Hey, thank you.
I'm ready to go, man.
Wes Bos: I'm just, I got a lot of new features. I just released a new course. And I'm like, I'm ready to plug in on some code for a little bit. I'm ready to start recording my next series. I already have it all planned out. I'm going to get ahead of this one by a little bit here. So that you know I can start working even on April Siri. So by the time the baby comes, I'll be you know, nice, nice and good here. So I am ready. I'm ready for this week, ready for next week already for everything. So yeah. How you doing? Awesome. I'm doing really good. I had an extremely productive week last week working on my beginner JavaScript fundamentals course no one sure what I'm gonna call it and it's looking really good. I'm really happy. It's It's been a long time of just compiling information and building lots of examples. And, and now I'm at a point where I'm like, I took this like, I have this app that's called mind node. Have you ever heard of this? It's like mind mapping software. I see like all of these apps, but I don't let me see. Yeah, there's tons of them out there. I asked on Twitter the other day, and a lot of people said to use my note, it was expensive, like 50 bucks. But it was it was amazing to just like dump everything that I'm hoping to teach and then just like drag it around into this, like nice mind mapping into different sections and making sure and anytime I'm like, oh, like truthy and falsy. Did I get that? And I can just quickly look up? Oh, yeah, that's in the logic and flow control section. And I know that anytime I think of a topic, I just checked the mind map. And I know that it's going to be hopefully somewhere on there. If not, then I can figure out where to put it really easily. So a big fan of this mind mapping software I've never used before. I feel like my napping would go perfectly into notion. I mean, they have all those other tools that do some like, it might be a little intense for notion, but like, man, I feel like that'd be right up their alley. So yeah, maybe we should send them up. Not a poor request. A feature request is a request, please add this. Today, we are sponsored by two awesome companies. First one is Sanity. sanity.io is a headless CMS or a boice. Bring Your Own front end. And we have the armory, which is a men's clothing and accessories retailer. They're both online and in New York. And Scott and I both really like it. So we all talk about both of these companies partway through the episode. So let's get into it.
Unknown: Yeah,
Wes Bos: we're talking about boot camps. Our boot camps are rip off, should you pay for this? Some people even think like, why would you even pay for online course, if you can just read the documentation, you get kind of really low level with this kind of thing. And obviously, at a certain point in your life, it probably makes sense to invest some of your time or your money or both into some sort of education. So we're going to go through the differences between boot camps, part time programs, self learning, going to actual school, all of those different ones. But But first, before we even get into that, let's just talk real quick about our experiences. Like how did we get to we're both professional, full time developers. How did how did you get to your where you are Scott? Yeah. So I you know, I mean, I started learning web development in high school, but it wasn't like focused learning. And it definitely was an in an attempt to get a career. So I wouldn't necessarily even count that. I went to the University of Michigan for music. So I went to college, to study music. And so I got the college experience. And you know, actually, my, my program was a music technology. And there was a lot of programming and engineering courses within the music class, or curriculum here for me. So I did have experienced to that sort of thing in college. Once I graduated, I sort of worked odd jobs while self teaching. So even though I did get some training from college, it wasn't like I was totally decided that I was going to be a programmer. And then I came out of college right to be a web dev, the web dev classes that we're going to get into UVM. We're certainly terrible. So I'm not going to Give them any credit for my eventual career. But I ended up working, you know, just weird jobs. I was an accountant, I was an AV tech. And all of the while here, I was teaching myself to code. My AV tech job involves me just turning on a projector at the beginning and ending of a day and just sitting in a projection room for the rest of the day. And so I wasn't allowed to bring my own computer. So I didn't have like a, you know, I didn't have a computer to waste time on what I had was a crappy computer that I could read and learn and experiment a little bit with code to get up and running. And then what I did was I took that time I got some freelance clients, I grew a little bit and I got a job as a web dev. And then I learned via my boss being an amazing mentor to me, Ben chef, he was an incredible boss and mentor and taught me a whole time while I worked as a junior developer, which led me to have my eventual progression in web development. And then I started teaching myself in 2012, via level up tutorials, which was really soon after I got my first web dev job. And it's not because I felt like I had a ton to teach. But it's like, I felt like there were things that were being underrepresented in educational material, especially for people like me, who were brand new into web development. And people who thought like me, I wanted less jargony technical content and more down to earth real content. So that's why I started levelup tutorials in 2012. And here we are today. Beauty. So I went to you actually, I have a quick question. What kind of beer Did you drink in college? Um, you know, whatever. Honestly, it depends on like, cuz typically, you'd go to like a house party in it's whatever they had going in the keg. But if we were buying, I mean, Michigan has a really good beer scene. So we would be buying a lot of bells, pretty much bells, I would say anything bells. I mean, hopslam is my favorite thing in the entire world. But there's, there's a lot of different stuff. It's interesting. When I was in university as before, that like sort of awesome beer scene had come to Canada and also beers, like really expensive in Canada. I know. Like, you can go to the gas station in the states and buy like a 30 of Natty light for like 12 bucks or something like that. But we were drinking that what's called the Clay's at the time and right and then near the end of university as when Pabst Blue Ribbon started to become super popular in the college scene. Well, we had so my breakdancing crew, we had an official 40 and it was Mickey's so Mickey's was the official 40 of Robo tops. And so we we would do the we'd do power hour or Edward 40 hands or that kind of thing with somebody that was very common. We would do the wizards where you drink a beer. And then if you have a new beer, you duct tape it to the top of your empty can. And then by the end of the night you have like but yeah, but I can't I can't drink that much beer I drink like two or three and I get sleepy. So I just got the recycling and then just tape. You just you got to pick the phone a little bit. You
got to fake it till you get it. Exactly. I'm still thinking that these days. Yeah. Anyways, my experience in this was I went to university for what's called Business Technology Management at Ryerson University in Toronto. And that was more focused on like how to be a manager of technical people not really focused on like, coding or anything like that is more like implementing systems and making purchase orders, things like that. So I'm entirely self taught. As a coder, I sort of just picked that I've been coding since I was like 15 or so. And then I did it all through university. And then by the time I was done university, I was just working for myself being a consultant. So that's my experience with college didn't take comp site or anything like that. And then on the bootcamp side of things, I actually led a whole bunch. So there is a boot camp in Toronto called hacker U. And they first initially started, I think, like maybe six years ago, we initially started it was I created all the content. And I led the first part time class, which was HTML and CSS. And then out of that a couple years later was the the first boot camp came along. And I led that and created a whole bunch of the content for that. And then shortly after that, we did another part time, JavaScript part time at hacker u as well. So I've led, I don't know, hundreds and hundreds of people through boot camps or through part time classes. And now they're they're huge. I think they have a whole bunch of employees, I went out for coffee with Heather, who runs it the other day, and they've got some amazing instructors there. So Wow, I have a pretty good, pretty good outlook over boot camps in general, specifically hacker you I know runs a really tight ship. But I've also talked to a lot of students who, who go through other ones. And then finally, I've also been offered a bunch of jobs at colleges and universities. So I have a bit of insight into how that works and what the benefits are. And at least the ones that I've been offered jobs and part time classes that they they don't seem to pay very well. They seem to have tons and tons of students and tons of marking, which is one thing that tends to get a lot of teachers down. So that's kind of my outlook on the these different things. So we're going to Start with school. What are the pros and cons of school? You know, kick that off? Oh, yeah. Well,
Unknown: so I actually, I thought this would be a little, little funny thing. We could have each one of these have a little bit of a, what do they call that on on Yelp? Or on Google reviews? Where there's like $1 sign amount?
Wes Bos: Oh, yeah, the price, the little little price, I would say that school is gonna earn our highest rating of $3 signs in terms of university or, or anything like that, because colleges are expensive. And you know, I Well, I paid off my student loans A while ago, but Courtney was still paying hers off, or we were still paying Courtney's off until a little while. So you know, I'm, I'm 32. And we just paid off some of her student loans. And now granted, she has a PhD, but colleges are expensive. And it definitely, if I worked a full time job while I was at college, and it still was expensive for me. So depending on where you go, it can be very expensive. So that is the $3 sign option. Well, let's get into the pros, though. So for pros, for me, I thought like one of the best things that I got out of college was sort of life skills that were unrelated to programming, living on my own how to function, that sort of thing that I got in sort of a controlled environment, you couldn't mess up too much, you still had a schedule, you still had places to be, but you had a lot of freedom and a lot less restriction. And you had a lot of room to explore life in different ways. And to me, that was one of the huge upsides about college is that I got a lot of social skills and social abilities that sure you know, I wasn't you know, I had social skills coming out of high school, but it's completely different. It's, it's a more professional world, it's more like that. So I learned quite a bit from college and that degree. Yeah, I agree. I often would have just like conferences as part of school, I would have these like, meet and greets all the time, where you meet with the professors, and I learned a lot about communication and how to talk to people and how to tie a tie. And because I went to like Business School, right, like I yeah, I had like a tie on like, probably at least once a week for some sort of event. And I think really though, when I think about school, for me, it was the best thing that happened was that I had like unrestricted free time to just figure things out, right? Because like, school is busy. And I know like a lot of people have to have a job as well. But there's like really low risk in spending your your evening just trying to figure something out. Like, for me, it was just teaching myself WordPress are playing around with CSS and trying to fix things. And there wasn't a whole lot of pressure, I was getting paid for most of the stuff that I was doing. But it was just the sort of like free time to figure out what it is that I like. And I think that if I were to have skipped school entirely, and went directly into being a web developer, I think the pressure of it being a job and the pressure of trying to meet all my bills in the pressure of trying to make it a thing because this is your job now would be so much more. And I don't think I would have enjoyed it as much as just like, being able to I'll figure it out and try to be a web developer. Yeah, so in school, I had a bunch of different co ops. And I think the CO ops are just like these, like summer jobs that you get in school. And that really, really helped me in figuring out what it is that I do and do not like about working for different employers. And then ultimately, after doing all of my costs that ultimately led me to decide that I want to work for myself, because I don't like working for anybody else. Yeah, you know, one of the things that I really loved about college was being exposed to people and ideas. So, for instance, you know, the University of Michigan is hard to get into I it's a miracle that I got in, I don't even understand how I got in. But at that kind of institution, you have very, very high functioning people. Almost every single person I met at college was amazing at something they were they were good at what they were doing. They were very smart. They were applying themselves in all sorts of different ways. And especially in the School of Music, you have a lot of talent, where people are just some of the most insanely talented people that you'll ever meet. They're doing this, they're doing that they're designing these things, they're designing these things. Meanwhile, they're also you know, world class musician in these regards. They were world class artists in these regards. But people are very surprising, very smart and very good at what they do. And I've never felt more inadequate at any place than when I first started talking to people and finding out just how much less accomplished I was in so many of these people. Now granted, I'm obviously not the least accomplished person who's ever gone to school there but like when you talk to people at the school, it was just constantly feeling like Oh, man, I really have to step up my game. I feel like I'm in still in high school and these people are graduating college already. And we're we're colleagues here we're both going to school were peers. So it what it did is for me, it was definitely an eye opener in terms of what I needed to get on track and how I needed to focus more.
Let's talk about computer science in general. So both of us went to school but neither of us went to school for for computer science. And it seems like every day, there's a new tweet thread on Twitter where someone says you don't need a computer science degree to be a web developer. Yeah. And I think I agree with that. But that's not to demean anyone who actually does go through with a computer science degree because I think there are much harder problems that can be solved past creating a UI with react or building a crud back end update. Like, I think sometimes we were developers put ourselves on a pedestal still, like we're the creators of the universe. We're the web developers, we know everything. And the reality is that there's like probably some guy that doesn't have Twitter that's working on like a medical breathing device or Yeah, right, trying to like, figure out how can we get the most juice out of this really slow processor, so that we can deploy weather balloons or something like that, like there's much harder problems, and then web development being solved. And I'm very glad that people have computer science degrees for solving those problems. I don't think being a web developer is necessarily something that you do need a computer science degree for. I really wish I had a computer science degree. There's so many times when I was a freshman or sophomore at U of M worse thinking, you know what I should transfer to engineering, because I'm not going to be a musician. I should transfer to computer science, and I should just do it. Now. Yeah, I never did. Yeah, it was like, I almost you know, I don't want to say it's the regret, because I don't regret anything. Because without it, the path I took, I wouldn't end up where I am. But I really do. If I going back and having another opportunity, I would have tried to transfer into computer science or engineering, they're like really quickly, you know, and go that route. Because I think there's a lot of important skills that you pick up in a CS degree. They it's hard to pick, it's harder to pick up when you are self teaching yourself. Yeah, I've never met somebody that has a computer science degree that regrets the time on that thing, right? Yeah, yeah, yeah. Other things I'll say about school in general, not necessarily computer science is that a lot of companies won't hire you unless you have some sort of bachelor degree. So I think specifically, I think Google, they might have might have changed this or not Google, or you. Yeah, I think Facebook will hire you. And I know that there's some folks on the React team that don't have anything like that. But there are a lot of companies out there, that's just part of their procedure, and they're not able to hire you, especially if you're trying to do like some sort of visa. A lot of times when companies fly you from or the import you, that's not a good word. Well, it may be it's for a JavaScript job, they will. But yes, a lot of times when you immigrate into the US or into Canada, in order for them to actually get you like landed residency in they have to make sure that they could not find somebody with similar skill from inside of the country first, and often having some sort of bachelor's degree or some sort of degree from a school is part of showing that that's the reason why they had to move you from some other country back into into the US or into Canada.
Yeah. You know, one of the low key things that I got out of college that they say you're going to get out of college, and then people say that you don't is professional networking, which doesn't seem like it's that amazing. But there are schools like the University of Michigan have a big network. And there's been so many times where I've met people, and the connection to the University of Michigan has helped me out. I've gotten not web dev, actually, no, I got one of my very first web dev job. And my second web dev job, I got them really not because of but the fact that I went to the University of Michigan, and the owner of the first company I worked for, along with, you know, several of the designers all graduated from the University of Michigan. So then I get to have that on my resume, we get to have that in common. We got to talk about that. My second job was actually at the University of Michigan, and that sure, definitely did help get a job there. So the professional networking really can help. I mean, absolutely, it's one of those things that they they tell you exists. And if you use it correctly, it certainly can. So let's get into the cons here because I think we hit all of the pros, right? So okay, so we obviously have the $3 signs, that's a big con, spending a lot of money. And potentially, yeah, you might not come out of it with the same kind of skills you would a boot camp or any of the stuff that we'll get into later. But I think some of the the main cons at least the cons that I experienced, were bad, outdated, course material to instructors who didn't necessarily stay up to date with things my very first web dev course ever in college at a college level used Adobe. Ah, what is this app called? Dreamweaver, before they bought Dreamweaver. It was back when Trump Macromedia Yeah, it's back when is Macromedia but it was Adobe in I don't know, in touch. I don't know what the heck it is. And it was the old Adobe web dev software that was a pre buying Macromedia. They had like a grid based visual designer to learn how to code and it was sort of you drag everything on a grid and it just works. And of course, you open it up in the browser and it looks terrible because they're just like position absolutely everything and it didn't it just it worked inside of their own preview editor. And that's pretty much it. So nice. To say it was not exactly super helpful in terms of learning to actually code. And I felt like I probably hurt myself by spending so much time in an application like that, that was focused less on the nuts and bolts of HTML and CSS than it was dragging and dropping and trying to be a Photoshop. Yeah, I should say also, I know that there's probably a lot of like college professors or college, just course, leaders listening right now. And I've gotten emails from lots of people who actually some of them who even paid their own money, just to take my course with their students, which is cool. So there are a lot of like teachers out there that that care a lot about it. But in my experience, going through, like I've taken a couple in university, I took a couple like HTML, CSS JavaScript courses, just as as electives. And, and almost always, the teacher had no idea what was going on, they don't actually write this stuff for the real job. I've been asked many times to lead different courses because my my email got on some sort of like list of people who could potentially lead courses at university, I get all the time my email. So if people are like, Hey, I was wondering if you'd like to lead a video editing course, or we're looking for someone who can do the we're looking to do print, or like, or they have this course that's like multimedia. And they try to like cram in, like web development, video editing, game development, and like all of these things until like, a six week course. And I just think like that, combined with like, the pay, web developers get paid pretty well. And generally, the pay for these things was much less than I could do. I could get just paying for, for like making a website for somebody else outside of it, right? Yeah. So there's, there's that frustration, you've heard it many times over with people in a university or a college program saying like, they taught me nothing, all of the stuff was super out of date, the programs we were using was silly. So I think that's really frustrating to evil. They're paying they're they're good, hard earned money. And when it comes to technical spaces, like web development, it's really hard to keep the content up to date. And a lot of times these they're not allowed to change the content, the the people that are leading these courses, because it's been approved by like the ministry or something like that. So I definitely see a lot of people saying that sort of thing.
Yeah, no. And I'll echo what you were saying about. I mean, obviously, not all of them are, are bad, because they're certainly some very good ones. And in fact, I'm on the advisory board for the University of Florida for their curriculum, along with several other people like Kyle Simpson. And so they actually reached out to developers in the space, and showed us their curriculum and asked us how we could improve their curriculum, what we would change about it, how to make it more modern, what we could do differently. And the they were very receptive to everyone's suggestions. They had people from the design professionals, they had JavaScript developers, they had all sorts of different people in the industry. And they took the advice very seriously. So there certainly are universities there are looking to up their game in that regard. And you know, it's potentially an issue, but it's not always an issue. All right, let's get now into boot camps, which is sort of for a lot of people entering into a boot camp, which generally the way that the boot camps work is is you go for anywhere from, I don't know, seven, eight weeks to some of them are up to 12 weeks, and you go there, generally nine to five every single day, Monday through Friday, often people are staying behind often people are working on weekends. And it's just this crazy, intense way of learning all that is in web development, and building lots and lots of projects. So I myself have have led one, I think when I did it was something like eight weeks, nine weeks, something like that. And we go through the whole thing of HTML, CSS, your text editor command line tools. And at the time, it was WordPress, but it had since been replaced with just much more JavaScript. And I think that came upon because of job requirements. People like the jobs that these students were getting into wanted much stronger JavaScript and not necessarily as much WordPress. And so that was one and also WordPress, or JavaScript in general is just too hard to teach. I think we were doing two weeks at the time. And I think now it's it's up maybe four weeks or something like that. So that's generally the way that these these boot camps work. There's a lot of pros to boot camp is a lot of cons as well. I think probably the best one. I think that this is the reason why a lot of people should take a boot camp is that you can get up to speed extremely quickly. So any of these these choices that you picked in here, whether it's going to school was going to boot camp, self learning, you're unless you are a self learner, you're going to fall flat once you finish whatever program it is that you want. So I think a boot camp is just a really quick way to get up to speed and to immerse yourself in this industry. There's you're not going to learn absolutely everything in JavaScript. And people often say like, oh, there's no way you could learn web development. Then nine weeks. And it's true, you can't learn all of web development in nine weeks. But I think you're gonna learn enough, you get the sort of like initial push by going through the boot camp. And then as soon as you graduate, it's really important that you you keep learning by doing self study, as well as I think people get jobs right out of a boot camp, because employers can say like, Oh, I'm going to hire this Junior. And I think that if I can mold them over the next six months, a year, they will be a really good employee. Yeah. And boot camps. Okay. So I would say boot camps are $2 sign. I mean, they're less expensive than going to college, but they're certainly not exactly. Super Duper cheap. Yeah, they can be like, anywhere from like, seven grand to 12 grand for like a couple of months program. Yeah. And one of the, I think one of the most amazing things about boot camps is just how focused some of them can be. I went to a boot camp to speak about my career in Denver was galvanized, and the instructors were amazing. The instructors had everybody go around in a circle, and they just like, I was just so impressed. They'd be like, Alright, this array method, what does it do when you point to a random person and they shout out, alright, blah, blah, blah, this blah, blah, blah, shout it out. And they'd only been I mean, it was an immersive, intensive program. But these people were already up to speed with stuff that it takes a lot of people a long time to get up to speed with just because how Fast Furious focus the learning is. And if you have a good instructor, these things can be just totally immersive and totally exciting to listen to. And again, I think one of the the big things that you come out of a boot camp with is that the boot camp is entirely focused on getting you a job, which is a very important thing. They're they're not focused on teaching you the skills that are going to make you happy in life, they're going to be focused on teaching you the skills that are going to make you employable, you can then work on those those things, whatever your personal direction is, after you're out at the boot camp, but these things are going to give you the skills to set up for foundational for job interviews, or I just was so impressed, because we did a little QA and the questions that these developers were asking me, were just so beyond where I was at that stage in my career, that I think would they can be a really good way to rocket ship you to a good place.
If I were to look at what was taught and what was learned in nine weeks of a bootcamp like that easily eclipsed probably the first year and a half of my career of just getting to that point at that time. So it's amazing. And like, you might be asking, like, why is it is it does it go so fast. And I think a huge portion of it is that the material is incredibly well selected as to what you should be learning, it's hand picked as to, these are the things we need to focus on. And these are things you do not necessarily need to know about just yet. And then there's also just like lots and lots of teachers and mentors available at any given moment that if you have a question, you can get that solved within 10 minutes, rather than or you can like sit together with your your schoolmates and fix these things. Versus like if you're if you're learning by yourself, you might, you might be out of three hours or if you're learning in like a university, you've got your three hours, once a week, you better wait a week, or go to office hours at a certain point to get help with that sort of thing. And that can be frustrating to people in the search just man, whatever, I'll get my mark and move along. Yeah, that's a big thing. We'll talk a lot about mentorship a little bit later. But I think it's Yeah, that aspect is if you are the type of person who likes to ask questions, which there's definitely a type of person if you are that type of person. Boot Camps can be amazing. Because if you were it takes a little bit of self self learning self direction, but if you can go for that and you will be up and running in no time. And eventually you're going to be earning the big bucks. And when you earn the big bucks, you get to buy nice clothes and outfit your life in a way that is going to make you feel really good and take advantage of some of these places that you get to put yourself in and by by making yourself feel in looks super nice. Now one of our sponsors is the newest sponsor to syntax, which is the armory now this is spelled with a u so it's a RMU ROI. And we'll have a link to that in our course notes. But the armory is a high end men's clothing store based out of New York and their stuff is incredible. Yeah, this is definitely a brand for not someone who's looking for like a like a suit with a huge name on it. It's someone who's looking for a suit or sport jacket or a sweater or even even a nice hat that is made with quality so you're not necessarily paying for the brand name on these clothes you're paying for the quality and the sort of life that you're going to get out of out of this stuff. So the armory is a men's clothing and accessories retailer. And even though it is fairly expensive, it's it's good value for the price. So these are the sorts of things this is my wife is all about this. She talks to me all the time. She always used the word investing in in pieces, which is I always find funny because like your clothing is not gonna make you more money although maybe maybe it will. It If you if you wear this to an interview, yeah, right, yeah, you spend the money up front. And then you have these specific clothes for for years and years to come. It's kind of the anti fast fashion. And they believe that clothing is a self expression. So you should dress to yourself not just a photocopy of something that you've maybe seen on, like the Reddit of dressing or something like that male
fashion advice. Male fashion advice. That's the one. It's so funny. Sometimes you see somebody walking around around the street and say that person subscribes to male fashion advice on Reddit. So it's a pretty small little boutique, they have shops in New York City and Hong Kong. So if you want to visit them there otherwise, you can shop online at the armory calm. One thing I do want to mention to us if you're interested in just getting more involved in fashion in general, follow their Instagram. It's the armory NYC. And it's kind of cool, because you can just like every couple days, you'll see a new photo from them. And at a certain point, you'll say like, I've got to have that. What is the safari jacket that you have Scott? Yeah, I love that Safari jacket. Yeah, absolutely. So Scott got this like Safari jacket from the armory, I got a really nice cashmere buttoned up, which is super comfy, a really nice wool hat. been loving it myself, we got we got this stuff months and months ago. And then we were just sort of wearing it for the last couple months, so that we can actually talk about the quality of it and make sure that it's not just some other expensive hat that you're gonna buy, and it'll fall apart on you. So it's definitely good quality, I'd recommend it. Thanks so much to the armory for sponsoring and check them out at the armory.com word. Cool. So let's get back into it with the cons of boot camps. The boot camps are not for everyone, it does require a certain level of self directedness. And it requires a certain level of let's go get it, let's go dive into this career, I'm ready to go. Because you're gonna have to self learn, you're going to have to ask a lot of questions. And you're have to be excited about the stuff you're learning. Otherwise, the pace of it, and the intensity of the program is not going to do good things for you. So that is definitely an important aspect, you you kind of better really want it for the boot camp to work. Yeah, I think after I've I first taught my first boot camp over five years ago, and it's really interesting, because I'll often see my past students at conferences, and they are now like senior developers, they have a team under them, a lot of them are making really good money over $100,000 a year. But at the same time, you also see people who who took the bootcamp and after the boot camps over, they fall flat, they don't self learn, they're not self motivated. And I think in general, it really just comes down to to personality, that type of person, you can, you can almost see the type of person who goes through one of these things, you can see if they're they're going to do well or not actually, that's part of the the process. I know specifically, hacker does not just let anybody into these these boot camps. Because like, while it would be great just to take everyone's money, there is a certain personality type that should not be taking this because they're not going to see the benefit of it. And then you're going to be out all this specific money. But I guess that gets into the next con, which is some boot camps will take anybody and they will just take your money. And they're not gonna think twice about it because they don't exist to teach people they exist to make money. And there is definitely a I don't want to say it's a large portion of boot camps. But there are definitely is a small portion of boot camps out there that are money making outfits that the quality is going to be low, you're the instructors aren't going to be great. And you're probably not going to be prepared for a career after the boot camps over. So there is a positive side is that the good boot camps are really good and the bad boot camps are going to take your money and you're probably not going to get a whole ton out of it.
Yeah, I think probably two good ways that you can vet a boot camp is first find somebody who's gone through boot camp and just go out for a coffee with them. Almost always someone who has gone through this entire process is willing to to help you through yours because it is an intense experience. And they are super grateful to anyone who has helped them. So they want to sort of pay that forward. So find somebody you can often find people on Reddit, or even just looking at the past students and tweeting them and emailing them saying hey, can I grab a coffee? I just want to hear what your thoughts are on this. And then also find out who the instructors are because at the end of the day, there's a couple things that make a really good boot camp. I think like one of them is the people who make the content. The the curriculum is really, really important. Second, I think it's the instructors find out who is teaching it because a good instructor can really make or break whether you find enjoyment out of a specific thing. And then third, I think another thing that isn't often talked about is that a lot of these boot camps will have like career development surfaces because they have to try to get you a job after it. Some of them will just say good luck. But a lot of them will actually like train you for interviewing they'll bring in people Lawyers in they will try to schedule interviews, they'll teach you how to negotiate a salary when you actually get an offer. So being able to ask like, what are you going to do after I've learned how to create a react application to place me in a place? Because I think that's, that's just as important. If you're paying all this money, you should definitely get some sort of help in the career space.
Unknown: Yeah,
Wes Bos: absolutely. I guess the last con, as we've mentioned, is that a pro, as well, it's not great for people who can't handle the pace. Again, you I mentioned before, you have to want it. But in terms of just wanting it, it's also very, very fast. So you want to make sure that you can keep up with the pace of it. It's the the quickness is definitely a thing. I remember, I took a Japanese class at the University of Michigan, and it was five credits, and it was superduper. Fast. And I felt like that was fast. And then I found out that there was a summer intensive course that gives you 10 credits, 10 credits for one class, to teach Japanese over the course of the summer. And I remember thinking like, there is no chance I'm ever going to keep up with the pace of this course, even though I had the desire to learn language, it just wasn't going to be there for me. So you have to have that ability to know that you're going to be able to keep up with this beat. Now granted in a good instructor in a good environment, know that with all the questions involved, as long as you're self directed, and have that drive, you should be fine. I think the probably the biggest one that I forgot to say is you have to quit your job, or take some sort of sabbatical from your job in order to do this. And most people, they quit their job, I don't think I've seen anybody take the boot camp while they've maintained like a serving job or a part time job anywhere. because it requires your full attention, you're going to be absolutely exhausted by the end of it. So you need to make sure that you're you're ready for this entire experience to happen. And you don't have a whole lot go else elsewhere going on in your life. Yeah, you have to look at it as like a college experience, except for you're not a college, when people are in boot camp, like give them the educational discount to level up tutorials, because that, to me is the same experience as being a student. So cool. So let's get into the $1 sign option, which is self teaching yourself. I know you have part time programs here, but I kind of want to save it for after the big three here. So the big three are really self teaching boot camps and university. So self teaching is clearly the cheapest option, because you couldn't do it primarily through YouTube, if you want to do i mean granted my $10 I mean, I have 1000 videos on YouTube teaching web development. If I have 1000 videos on YouTube, there's probably 10,000 hundred billion other videos teaching you web development on YouTube as well. So you can do it or very, very cheap, if not free. And that is a it's the first one where the dollar cent has been in the pros column. So it's very, very cheap. So this is really for our self directed self starting core sort of people, the people who wake up in the morning are like, Yeah, what can I do today to make myself a better human being and ready to learn a bunch of new stuff, those kinds of people are going to do well and the self directed, self taught thing. Another one is that you can do it while you're at another job potentially, while you're working at a job. You don't have to quit your job. You can do it nights and weekends. You can you can spend that time and devote it and if you're like me, and you had a super menial job, like turning on a projector, you could literally do it at work, because that's how I self taught myself how to program. I turned on the projector. And then as long as that projector stayed on, I was teaching myself programming, which is sort of ridiculous. And yeah, yeah, if you're not looking to go as fast as a boot camp, I definitely think self teaching is a really good option. Like Scott said, it's extremely cheap, it can be a supplement to your job. So I know a lot of people who take my courses are already web developers, or they are in a technical role. Maybe a lot of them are just like the people who maintain the website from data point of view. So they're just like maintaining the CMS. And sometimes they get it right, a little bit of code, but they love to upgrade and get that pay bump that comes along with being a full web developer. So you can buy a couple courses, take a couple of YouTube courses, whatever it is that you find works for you. And it's a nice little supplemental way to just increase your job. Often employers are more than willing to spend a couple hundred dollars on courses. A lot of people have training budgets, and they pay for those because it will just I don't know, I would pay a couple hundred dollars to invest in my own employees and make them a bit better. Yeah. And you should ask that's a big thing you should ask. A lot of times, these companies will tell you yes, you have this much amount to spend on courses or conferences or whatever for the year. But sometimes they don't tell you. And I think it's important to head to your boss and say, hey, these courses are going to make me a better developer. For these reasons. I'd really like to take these can we get it covered. And you should tell your employers to go buy some level up tutorials and Wes Bos courses
Unknown: They might say yes, no, but just joking. I want to get to Sally over here. Don't
Wes Bos: get to Sally ami sigh I'm drifting.
Unknown: But But yeah, so
Wes Bos: one of the things that I really loved about self teaching myself is that you could get real world experience while you were learning that could direct where you were learning where you're spending that time learning, I would often take a freelance gig and just say, Yes, I can do it, and then have to figure it out while I was doing it. Now, granted, I wasn't, I wasn't batting out of my league. But if they needed a specific site with certain functionality I knew was possible in WordPress, but I had never done it, I would say, let me do it, I'm going to take the time, I'm gonna spend that time learning, and I'm gonna get paid to learn a little bit. So self learning can definitely it can be directed specifically by what you're doing in your Freelancer or any of that sort of work. Yeah, I'm a big, obviously, I'm self taught myself. And I think probably the biggest tip that I can have for someone who is self taught is that the learning material is really only half of it. And the other half is actually building stuff. So you can take as many courses and watch as many talks and read as many medium blog posts as you want. But for every minute you're spending doing those things, you should also be spending a minute building an application that scratches your own edge or doing a freelance client or whatever. And I think that's where you're really gonna cut your teeth and go and we answered this, I think last week on the potluck, where someone said, like, will that make me job ready taking a cup of courses? Absolutely not. Is is University going to make you job? Ready? No, no way. You're, once you once you graduate, you actually have to start building stuff and actually cut your teeth on this in order to refine your real world experience.
Unknown: Yeah, cool.
Wes Bos: So let's get into the cons of self teaching yourself. Because there are definitely certainly cons. I mean, when you get something for free like this, there's definitely gonna be a lot of cons and cons specifically for self teaching, or it's not for everyone, it really is not, you need to be ready to go, you need to be the type of person who wants to learn this stuff and doesn't need somebody to tell them, here's what to do next, it can be difficult, I mean, that can be really difficult to self motivate, especially when there might not necessarily be an immediate, you know, at the end of the rainbow here for you, you might not immediately see the results of the work you're putting in. But if you put in a little bit of work every single day, you're going to see the results in a year or a couple years or even a few months. But it's not going to be an immediate feedback here, it's definitely a little bit longer of a road to getting up and running. Another con that we have is it's hard to get help. Sometimes, if you are stuck on something you can hopefully reach out maybe there's a slack group, maybe there is a spectrum, maybe there's a GitHub issue. But that stuff isn't always immediate, there might not be anybody in the chat room, there might not be anyone that respond, it can often take like 45 minutes to just like put together what is what it is that you're having a problem with. Whereas Sometimes I wish I could just grab someone's laptop, hit Inspect Element, and I could fix it in three seconds, whereas they probably took 45 minutes to get that thing like web ready and social, you're working on something locally, and there's a database involved. So that can be that can be extremely frustrating for people where it's hard to get help, what I have seen work really well is people just have like friends in a slack room, or they have a small slack room that has just a couple people who you can depend on or you meet up every Saturday for coffee with a bunch of people that they'll take my JavaScript 30 course together some sort of community where you can reach out to people when you get stuck. And it doesn't necessarily even have to be an expert. Often people will email me and say, can you be my mentor? Or can I do three hours a week with you? And it just really needs to be somebody who's like 15 minutes ahead of you. Yeah. Who has been through those problems and can explain it to you? Yeah, and and shout out to the level up tutorials slack room, if you want to join that it's the links in the footer of level up tutorials. You can just join that with the no invite necessarily. We have a nice community of people willing to help you out. I know, Wes, you have one for your courses as well. But Slack, things like that can be extremely helpful. I wish it wouldn't the start. When I first started the slack room for level up. I was doing a lot of help myself. And now a ton of the users are always coming to the aid of anybody else. And it's like really amazing to see this a community of people just there to help each other out. Absolutely. I should say right now before everyone emails me, my slack is not open unless you buy a course. Yeah. And there's like 23,000 people in there right now. But don't email me asking how to get in. You receive an invite when you when you buy a course there's that there's a red rope, and you have to lay
Unknown: out a red rope and you have to be invited. You have to be on the list. Exclusive exclusive. Yeah. It's also potentially discouraging if you had a problem
Wes Bos: and you don't know how to solve it. And again, you might not have that network that we just talked about. You could get very frustrated and you could quit. You could also start spend a lot of time learning something that is really unimportant to what you're trying to do. I mean, that that is like a big thing where you maybe think that this is the correct solution of the problem. And since you don't know any better, you spend a lot of time going down the wrong wrong path. And well, you just wasted maybe a month, maybe you wasted a week, maybe you wasted a couple hours, but it's still wasted time that you could have spent learning something else. And if you don't want to waste any time setting up your data for your front end application, then you're gonna want to check out sanity@sanity.io is the amazing boys bring your own front end back end system for you. That is, let me tell you really superduper cool, they put together a little demo for us with our syntax episodes, and we had our icons in there. And it's just really super cool. So we've talked about Sanity, a whole bunch. And one of the kind of cool things about Sanity is that you can upload your own react components to their back end, meaning that you can make custom interface for a hosted solution. They have all kinds of like a cool little add ons there. And if you go to sanity.io, forward slash syntax, they also have posted the code that is migrating the syntax feed that is the RSS feed, and they built a little migration tool. So specifically, if you say, Okay, I want to try Sanity, but I already have my data in something else, how do I move it to there, they have lots of like good migration tools. And at the end of the day, just show me the cool, show me the code. They've got some examples on GitHub called the podcast to Sanity. They have a link to the the syntax studio and the syntax front end mouth. So they actually wrote a script to import our podcasts from our RSS feed into Sanity, they wrote a script there, they wrote a back end for Sanity that you can just log in and check out. And then they also have, they took our website, which is open source and then just changed it. So the data is coming straight from Sanity, rather than the the markdown static generation that we have right now. So if you want to check that out, go to sanity.io forward slash syntax, scroll to the bottom, you'll see the links to those specific ones.
Unknown: Yeah. Nice. So thank you so much for Sanity for sponsoring. Really, really cool service. All right, next up,
Wes Bos: we have part time programs, we'll go over this one pretty quickly. A lot of these boot camp providers will also offer part time programs, as well as colleges and universities will offer just like a single course that you can go ahead and take, I think this is a fantastic way to get up to speed with a new new tech, I really enjoyed the pace of these specifically, when I was doing part time JavaScript, it was twice a week for three hours, I think six to nine or 639 30, something like that. And that was like often enough that you wouldn't get out of the headspace of JavaScript, but slow enough that you could have a couple nights in between to test it out and to build your own thing. And I would often show up a half an hour hour before class students would show up and say like, these are the things that I'm working on. I feel like it was a really good balance of learning quick enough, like learning JavaScript in I think it was like three months or something like that. But slow enough that if you get overwhelmed, things will stop for a couple days. And you could try to catch up with that specific thing. Yeah, yeah, I don't have any experience with these. But they again, it seems Low, low risk, and a definitely might be a good way to pick up some additional skills. So the cons you have listed here as quality as all over the map, and might not be as fast which both seem pretty reasonable. Again, it's not going to be the breakneck pace that a bootcamp will be and again, just like boot camps, you don't really know about the quality unless you really get into talking to some people about, you know, the course reviewers, the instructors are the quality if at all. Yeah, and for the quality one, often what can happen and this was at hacker U is we would have demo night and you can just anybody can come in the students would demo what they built in the class. So often it would be people who were checking the program out, and they just want to see like, what are people actually building? What do they have to say, and you should be able to talk to someone who's gone through the program to get an idea of what it is whereas like just going in blind, maybe with a course syllabus from something that would be a little dubious, I don't know, I don't necessarily know I plunked down money for something like that. And then the speed, I don't even think that's a con i think the speed of a part time program is really, really good, especially for someone like you might have kids, you can't quit your job, but you can for for three months of your life, you can devote a couple evenings a week to the sort of thing and we Scott and I have been telling people that all the time, just take you got to find some time and that might be in the evenings to figure this stuff out. And if you have an actual program, it's a lot easier just to show up and do the work then it might be to like, oh, maybe tonight I'll work on myself led course. Maybe I won't. I'm feeling tired or whatever the bachelor is on. Yeah, okay, well, let's get into our last one. And we're gonna get through this pretty quickly because this is really just an augmented version of self learning but just mentored self learning. mentored self learning is also $1 sign super duper cheap. It's best Do with a mentor on the job because you're working, you're working with that person, chances are they're a senior Dev, they can guide you a little bit. So it can be really, really nice to have an excellent boss mentor you this is one of the things that really advanced me and my career. mentor can help steer you where to spend your time and your free time, they might notice you have some some problems, spots in your education or maybe some gaps that you need. And they can toss you projects, maybe even work projects or say, hey, maybe you need to spend some time on this. So they have a good vision of where you are, where you need to be. And they can guide you a little bit. And it's also a great place to ask a lot of questions, which is the thing that I took advantage of most with my mentor, I asked so many questions, I probably annoyed the hell out of him, but just saying, Hey, man, I broke this, can you fix it? And it always, always helped. And you know, by the time that you know, you know, we were ended up being coworkers, eventually, we were asking each other the same kind of questions and getting each other up to speed on stuff. So that's how these kind of relationships work. And asking a ton of questions. And going back and forth is really super important. I
think one of the number one questions I get, like every day open on my Instagram, and I have people's life stories and a DM Yeah, asking for advice. And it's frustrating to me, because I can't spend all this time getting into people's lives and asking all these questions and then and then recommending a path forward. Whereas like, I think that there's a lot of really competent developers probably listening to this right now. And I think that at the very least, you should reach out to somebody who is looking for a mentor, and offer to have a quick call with them or just to be available. Like I remember when I first started coding, my friend, Darcy was always on chat. And whenever I hit a roadblock, I would just message him and he would help me out. And I thought that was that was so good, because I was able to get unstuck really quickly. And I think that it would be a really cool thing. If you are a developer right now. And specifically, if maybe even like make it a point of reaching out to somebody who is underrepresented in our industry and say, Hey, if anyone's looking for a mentor, I would be able to put in an hour an hour and a half per week. And in helping you through that. Because I think a mentor is such an awesome way to get through it. Yeah, definitely. But the cons, I guess for here would be that it can't be done without someone who's willing to mentor you. And yeah, I mean, we get requests to mentor people all the time. And as much as I would like, if I had no career right now, if I had nothing else to do, I would be happy to mentor every person. But I think I'm doing the best I can to mentor people through my courses. And that's really all I have the availability for. So only approach a mentor if you know that they have the ability to take you on as a student, because it is it's a big ask. But again, it's an important one. That's why I think having a boss that is a good mentor is a good way to go for that one. So I guess we want to wrap this up with what approach? Would you take Wes, after getting through all these pros and cons? What's your what's your approach? After all of this, I think that if you're young enough to go through school, it's probably worth going through some sort of program that interests you and keeping up with development, whether it's it tangentially related, or whether it's it's something totally different, because you might not end up liking web development, you might move to a totally different industry. But from what I hear a lot of people listening this podcast are maybe not in a spot where they can, they can go through school, and they're looking for a better way to get up to speed quickly. And if that was me, and I could afford a boot camp, I would definitely plunk down my money. I think that if you have found your yourself being able to go through an online learning course, or you find yourself with some success in web development, I wouldn't sweat the the money that you may have to take out a loan or borrow from family to do that sort of boot camp, because you will probably do well in this industry. So if that was me, I would take the bootcamp and then immediately start self supplementing after that. And you might have to self supplement for a couple years after graduation or probably if you're a web developer, you have to self supplement for your entire life. Yeah, right with with learning. So that's that's how I do it probably the fastest. But again, I'm totally self taught. I didn't take any boot camp. I didn't take any school. And it definitely can be done that way as well. Yeah, I would most likely agree with you. If you're the type of person who needs a little bit more exploration in their life, then college is probably a good option. If you're the type of person who's like I, I know what I want, and I want it now I want a web development career, then boot camp is a great way to go. It's cheaper, you can plunk down that money. Just make sure it's a good boot camp. Go through it, take all that stuff. And then again, you're going to want to self direct learning as much as possible. Get that job learn on the job keep growing build that career. And next thing you know it's gonna be yacht life. Yeah, life. One more thing I totally forgot to address that people ask me all the time. Do you think that there's going to be way more developers than there are jobs is it worth taking a bootcamp anymore? Because like there's like hundreds of boot camps cranking out hundreds of people every single month, and all sudden we're going to have thousands of these little babies that we birthed from these boot camps. And they all need homes and jobs and things like that. And I do think that our industry is still in a pretty big boom stage right now, there definitely is more demand for advanced people than there is for beginner jobs. But you can simply just go on a lot of these boot camps and take a look at their placement rates. And if the boot camp is not reporting what their placement rate is, like six months after graduation, I think 70 80% of the people who probably should have a job. And if they're not reporting that or they have a really low placement rate, then that probably reflects something on the bootcamp as well. Either they're letting in people who shouldn't have been let in, or they're not doing a good job at getting these people career ready.
Yeah. Cool. So I think that really covers it. This was a good one that we've been wanting to do for a long time. So I'm glad we not Yeah, now, definitely one of the longer episodes. Now we're going to get into the section of the show where we talk about things that we like, they can be anything, they could be podcasts, they can be books, they can be products, they can be website, services, literally anything stuff that we think is sick, this is our sick picks. And I have a sick pick for you today. It's a book called Digital minimalism from our one of our favorite authors, Cal Newport. You You read deep work by Cal Newport. Yeah, he has a new book out. Now he has a new book called Digital minimalism. It was released February 5 2019. And I read it February 5 2019. And I really loved it. Now this book is for those of you who maybe were inspired by the Marie Kondo sort of stuff, where you're looking to simplify your life and a little bit of way, and this is talking a little bit about digital minimalism, spending time away from your screens, spending time away from your devices, sort of impact it can have on your life. But not only that, how to make the time on those devices better. It was really nice. I liked it. It wasn't like, it wasn't transformative. I didn't read it and be like, wow, I'm a different person now. But I read it. And I really enjoyed it. And I really enjoyed the message. And it's a along with some of the konmari whatever stuff is really helping me simplify my life right now. And in teaching me a little bit about spending time on social media things, I actually set up my my digital wellness settings on my Android phone immediately after reading this book. And Android has built in like app time limiters. So you can say, you know, I only want to spend 15 minutes on Instagram all day. And then it Gray's out the icon, it's built into the OS. It's super nice. So I set that up immediately. And I've been limiting my time on social media, certain apps that I spend my I find myself drifting on to are just picking up and scrolling. He talks about something that was like, you know, when people first start to do this to block apps, they'll find themselves opening up apps like the weather app, and then just mindlessly scrolling through the weather app. And I had that exact same experience. I was picking up apps that I did not care about just to scroll through them. And it was really sort of eye opening in that regard. Like oh man, I really got to fix this. So digital minimalism really great book, loved it, Cal Newport does a good stuff. Cool. I'm gonna check that out. You've been on fire with your book recommendations. Lately, I've been taking almost every one that you recommend. I think we should have a page on our website that lists all of the books and maybe all of the sick pics because somebody I don't know what it is right now someone built a tool that scraped all of our markdown files for the sick pics and compiled them into a service. But specifically the books would be nice to just have because I often find myself being like, Hi, I need something new. Yes. Yeah, yeah, let's, let's build it. Let's do it. Cool. So my second pick is going to be a book as well. The other day, I was on a flight to Paris and I thought like, I've listened to so many of these like self help books. And I was like, I just don't feel like listening to another one right now. And I want something that's a little bit more interesting. Specifically, because you've been recommending that. What's the podcast that's about? He talks like this? And swindle the person was swindled Yeah, yeah, so I'm not gonna get out based on that. So I've been loving, swindled, and you recommended like, probably a year ago, the kingpin book, The American kingpin. Yeah. And it's the story of the, the guy who ran the Silk Road, which is this like Tor based private selling drugs through the mail website, and what a crazy story and I had heard a bunch of podcasts about the entire Silk Road story. And I thought that I know that story, but I listened to it anyway. And it was so good. It almost takes it as like it narrates, like, what he was doing what the weather was like. And fantastic. Just riveting story about this little geek who built this is kind of scary, because it's scary. I'm like, right. I know what he like I could have built that thing. You know, obviously I read up in it. Yeah, cuz it's it because I That's like one of us. You know, like one of us could have built the Silk Road because we he's just like a PHP Dev and slinging the stuff on tour. So I thought it was pretty interesting. Check it out. It's called the American kingpin.
Yeah. Cool. So, shameless plugs, I have a new course react hooks for everyone. If you want to learn hooks, build custom hooks, build non custom hooks use state whatever. We didn't do some really practical examples like very practical, we're building some some stuff that the hooks that you can take with you. We're building all of the things that teach you the ins and outs of all of the basics of hooks and just how to use them effectively in your applications. And we even get to some little third party hooks at the end it's really super nice. So check it out at level up tutorials.com forward slash pro sign up for the year save 25% it is react hooks for everyone is the latest course and we got a new excellent course for all you view fans coming out in March can be a view March so well, more view episode Scott, are we ever gonna do a view episode you tell me was you tell me I'm ready to go. I've been viewing so awesome. All right, I'm going to shamelessly plug all of my courses Wes bos.com for slash courses. If you want to learn anything, check it on out, dough. Peace. Thanks for tuning in. Please. Head on over to syntax.fm for a full archive of all of our shows. And don't forget to subscribe in your podcast player or drop a review if you like this show.