Unknown: You're listening to syntax
the podcast with the tastiest web development treats out there,
strap yourself in and get ready to live ski and Wes Bos.
Wes Bos: Welcome to syntax. This is the 2019 year end show. It's definitely not a clip show. So we're not gonna do what everyone does they call it in, you know, you watch a show on TV and they call it in and just show you clips from all the other episodes No, we are going to talk to you about what were the most popular syntax episodes. What we've got planned for next year, some personal staff what went on with us this year, what we got done what we learned a whole bunch of interesting stuff like that. So buckle up and get ready. Today's episode is sponsored by Prismic, which is a headless CMS and fresh books, which is cloud accounting software talking about both of them partway through the episode. My name is Wes Bos, thanks for tuning in with me, as always, is Scott to Lynskey. How you doing today, Scott? Hey,
Scott Tolinski: I'm doing good, I'm doing good, I'm doing good. It's getting near that time near the end of the year, you know, it's like, like a thing where people get ready to do all their resolutions and get ready to be hyped up for the next year of their life. I've always tried to do the resolution thing on like a more monthly basis. But this year has been nice, as you probably know, and as we're going to talk about. So. Yeah, there's a lot to talk about this year. And uh, you know, I'm looking forward to this renewed sense of energy you get every sort of January. I'm looking forward to just moving on with 2020. We all know 2020 is going to be a better year than 2019. Because that's just how the positive mindset works. Cool. So
Wes Bos: there you go.
Scott Tolinski: That's all I got really, yeah. Nice little intro.
Wes Bos: Let's start with next year. So we plan to do a live episode of syntax in March at react a THON we did one last year. And it was absolutely hilarious. We did the live coding, where we did like the tag team coding we did.
Scott Tolinski: What else did we do? We did something like the asking the audience, we had the real or fake where we made up things and you had to guess whether or not they were in the library. The the master chef coding thing was so exquisitely hilarious. And it worked out so perfectly, that neither of us were on the same page for that. If you haven't watched it, find the clip on YouTube West posted on his YouTube, we can make a link available to that. And while you're at it, just hit that subscribe button so we can get West as YouTube numbers up. But uh,
Unknown: we, uh,
Scott Tolinski: we did this thing where we did this back and forth coding, and it just so turns out, we had very different ideas of what we should code. It's absolutely hilarious. You should check out the React athon website as well. I think it's, it's new, or it's live with some of the new speakers that are going to be there this year, like Ryan Florence and Cassidy Williams. It's gonna be really cool. They're just starting to start to talk about some of the speakers who are there next year you'll see Wess photo up there but you won't see mine just yet. Hopefully they're gonna put me up there soon.
Wes Bos: Well, they got a drop they get it when tickets sales start to Peter off then they drop the big bomb who dropped the
Scott Tolinski: ski, right?
Wes Bos: Yeah. And then then they sell it out. So they're they're waiting to drop it.
Unknown: Yeah, no, I understand.
Wes Bos: Yeah, Erectus on was an awesome conference. It definitely felt like a very, I don't know how to describe it felt like a very like community conference, like a lot of people that were at the conference were pretty, like advanced in the React that they were using, like hooks had been out for like a couple weeks at by the last year. And they had already been almost everybody there was already using them, which is pretty cool. Yeah, people were shouting out how to properly write the code that we were trying to write during our our
Scott Tolinski: math. Yeah, thing. No, that was a great event. I had a great time. And I'm looking forward to next year's in, in seeing what we can come up for more live show antics because both of our live shows have been absolutely, totally super fun. And I'm just excited to do more of those.
Wes Bos: Yeah. What else has begun? Well, this year, the Twitter syntax FM on Twitter has done really well. We've are almost at 30,000 followers, which is pretty significant, I think. And I think that just comes from us, constantly plugging it every single show and then also using it as a medium not for us to push out information that we make, but using it as a medium for the people who listen to this podcast to share tips and tricks and thoughts and opinions and whatever it is. And I've really liked. I think like we've sort of hit the sweet spot on that this year, with the Twitter account basically just retweeting other things because it's hard when you're just like listening to a podcast and you're probably screaming at the screaming at your iPod or car or whatever it is that you're listening to mean like know that you're wrong about that or there's there is a better package for that and giving everybody a voice which is the syntax FM Twitter account has worked out really well. So big fan of that I'm impressed.
Scott Tolinski: And that's really why we're working Doing everything is for everyone to learn, right? That's why we're here. And that's why we're, we're talking about this. So we rely on the joint knowledge of the community more than anything for people to share what they're working on, share what they know and improve the knowledge of everybody together. So if you're not on Twitter, or you're not following us on Twitter, get on that right now. Because we really like to share a lot of tasty treats there for not just us, but the the rest of the community. Yeah. But yeah, in the syntax community overall, is absolutely incredible. Can we just talk about how, you know, we, we have sponsors on the show, and it's obviously we use, they're the sponsors that we use on the show are products that we like, products that we use products that we know a lot about, we're not just pushing you Harry's razors, or whatever, Taco Bell, obviously,
Wes Bos: although I would take Taco Bell in a second if they were Yes.
Scott Tolinski: We're not just shoving this stuff on the user. Yeah. Taco Bell. Get at us Lacroix. Yeah, get at us, please. Um, but for the most part, the whole audience just does such an amazing job of letting our sponsors know where they heard about their things. And let me tell you, that just helps us do this show. so incredibly much, you're all amazing. If you're sitting at your desk, just start giving yourself a round of applause. And have everybody look at you in the office, just let him know that we will we want you we want to support you, you know,
Wes Bos: yeah, yeah. And we actually have sold out all the sponsors for next year. And there was a number of companies that wanted to sponsor but weren't like a really good fit, like it felt like it would have been like kind of forced first guy to have him on. And we're lucky enough to be able to say no to that. And, and just bring on companies that we are we're really excited about and we want to see grow and things like that. So I'm feeling like really good about that as well. Because like, when you're bringing money into something that is very community oriented, it sometimes gets a little achy. And I feel like really good about the the space where we're sitting at with being able to make money off of this thing and pay our bills and make it worth our time, but also not get to Sally and things like that. Yeah, it did. I
Scott Tolinski: mean, it's a thing I know, we both have grown up with like punk rock music. But to me, honestly, that sort of punk rock mindset, in a way has never really left me. And I've always like, been a huge fan of, you know, record labels and people who have done it all themselves. And if, you know, they're, they're really going for it without necessarily, quote unquote, selling out. So yeah, we do have advertisers on here, but again, they're companies that we know and love, and I would never feel comfortable, like really pushing something I didn't believe in anyways, especially in that medium just because of, you know, like I said, my background, and that is just how I've always viewed things.
Wes Bos: Yeah, you know, what I thought was really funny is that like the skateboarding culture is very much about the brands and very much about the sponsorship. And I was like, I was
Scott Tolinski: like watching. They're all small companies with the sponsorship isn't for like Nike, and whoever. But yeah, a lot of them are skate skater owned small companies.
Wes Bos: Totally. And I know a lot of the companies that we have are, obviously some of them are huge companies. But they've all started from, like actual developers trying to trying to solve a problem, like you look at Netlify or
Scott Tolinski: just any of them. Literally any of them.
Wes Bos: Yeah, all of them are have developers at that, like the all of the founders of the companies were developers, at some point, looking to solve something in the space, which is really cool. So I don't know, for skateboarding culture, I'm not necessarily going to start wearing around a Freshbooks t shirt. Actually, I do have a Freshbooks teacher. Maybe I will start wearing around a Freshbooks t shirt.
Scott Tolinski: But those books get me I don't get one. So I
Wes Bos: when we had our first baby Freshbooks sent me a blanket that has fresh button. This is before they even our sponsor, they are just a customer. And I don't know how they ate Freshbooks is like a Toronto company. So maybe they saw on Twitter, I forget how they, how they found out that I had a baby, but they sent me a blanket. And now I have this Freshbooks blanket that my daughter uses. That's awesome.
Scott Tolinski: That is awesome. Yeah, that's super cool. baby blankets,
Wes Bos: that would be really cool. Um, next, what we're going to do is we're going to count down the 10 most popular episodes in syntax, we'll go from the 10th most popular down to the most popular, and we'll started just talking about why we think it did well, and any other thoughts that we have. So you want to take number 10 number
Scott Tolinski: 10 number 10 in this episode makes sense that it would be on this list because it was the very first episode that we released in 2019. It's funny that it's number 10. You know, this was a look forward to 2019. I know I probably want to do another look forward episode. I don't know how you feel about that. But yeah, talking about like our personal lives and our businesses and all that stuff. And this is sort of a look back So maybe in the next episode we should do should be a look forward just like this one. And so give that episode a listen, if you want to see, just go back in time a little bit and see how our lives were on January 1 2019.
Wes Bos: Next one number nine. This was probably personally one of my favorite episodes I
Scott Tolinski: cuz I wasn't there is that why is that why you're saying? Oh,
Wes Bos: you I forgot that you weren't even part of that one. Yeah, maybe we should do that more often
Scott Tolinski: mega dis was negative?
Wes Bos: No. So it was number nine SPGs was Sarah Sweden. Probably butchered that again, but not as much as I butchered it in the actual episode. And this was just like a total eye opening episode. Just there's so much in the SVG world. And if you go to my beginner JavaScript course, I'm using this SVG mask. So you can use the SVG as a mask, the drips on the website are using SVG masks. And I had learned about that from having Sarah on the episode. It's just like, it's just action packed full hour of amazing stuff, you probably want to listen to that one a couple times over. Just make sure you delete the mp3 and then download it again, if you listen to it a second time, so keep those numbers up.
Scott Tolinski: Nice. All right. Number eight, how to build an API. Now this is one of our newer episodes. This one came in August 27. So this is probably the most, is it the most? Yes, the most recent episode, yeah, arrive on our list here, which shows that it was a very popular episode, it hasn't had the time to really grow as much as some of these. So how to build an API was a lot of fun. We talked about the different ways that API's are from rest, to graph qL, that sort of stuff, and talked a little bit about interacting and working with them.
Wes Bos: If then occation, things like that. That was a, those episodes are always my favorite. We can't do every episode. That's a huge explainer like that. Because there's certainly just I don't know that many things. But that was one that we have been working on for a while just sort of putting things in as we thought about it. And really happy about that one, because it's like, it's almost a tutorial. With that one, just understanding all of the the moving parts. And that's something that sometimes the tutorial doesn't necessarily teach you. Because the tutorials is more focused on the nuts and the bolts and the coding. But because of the podcasts, we can't tell you what to type. So it really just focuses on the ideas and everything like that. And I was even listening to a podcast, the Free Code Camp podcast. And they were saying like, one of the ways that they stay up to date is by listening to syntax. And I was like, that's exactly what I want. Because like, there's this other part of web development that is not writing code, but it is just understanding how things work, what things are what they do, just to get a bit of a headspace as to what things are. So I think that that's why that episode did so well. I bet that will be one of our most popular episodes ever. If we were to look back at it in a year.
Scott Tolinski: Totally. Yeah. Next is number seven.
Wes Bos: css the cool parts. Yeah,
Scott Tolinski: super cool. I love this,
Wes Bos: when this episode went into some of the neat stuff that you can do with CSS and surprisingly well supported things like clip path filters, background mixed blend mode, border images, using hex codes with alpha. So RGB a Oh, no, that's is that how Yeah, that's how it works. RGB ba Yeah. So using eight characters instead of six when you're doing hex codes, radial gradients, viewport units, CSS variables, new text decoration. Some of these stuff were like, I don't know. Like nobody is googling new updates, detect decoration, text decoration. But yeah, there is news. There's new stuff to text decoration. So learn about it. Yeah, that was a we should probably give the episode numbers here too. That was Episode 146.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, this is this the cool parts was really one of my favorite episodes, because I'm using so many of these things right now with custom properties and all the new stuff in CSS, and I love it. So very much. I've always been a CSS head. And you know, this stuff just really is what I'm passionate about right now beyond just JavaScript and those kind of things. So the next episode, which is what number six in the list here, six most popular episode is episode number 130. The Vue JS show, Scott teaches Well, this one's not really surprised to me considering just about everybody was asking for the show for over a year. And Wes dragged his feet so hard that they left a permanent indentations in the floor of his office. So when we finally did it, it was after I had done my view course, I had done a course on the grid some so I had been spending a bunch of time in the Vue JS land, and I decided to talk about my understanding Have the interiors of view and how it's different from react in a syntax way and maybe give us a little bit of a knowledge on, you know what the differences are, what the what and why why people like it so much because it is such a popular framework nowadays.
Wes Bos: Next one we have the fifth most popular episode this year is what's new in web development, where we talked about the new promise methods, promise dot race, promise all settled promise that any lazy loading images, there's a new attribute on the image tag that is just lazy. And that will only request the resource once you've loaded once you've scrolled into view. Or once it's close enough to view I'm not sure what the I have to go back to that episode and look it up. css Houdini, we got to do an episode next year. Yeah. Once we actually build something with CSS Houdini, that's pretty cool sub grid. We did an entire episode on sub grid last year, did we? We did sub grid. We did it on January 14, so that one of the first episodes on 2019 was sub grid. And we said in that episode, it's about a year out and we caught some heat for that. Because a couple people said it's not a year out. And here we are almost a year later, and we don't have it just yet. No, I bet I bet it will. And pretty soon,
Scott Tolinski: actually, I think it did land in Firefox, the latest for it in it. I think it did. I don't We'll see. Up sub grid. I think I just read that headline in the latest version of Firefox.
Wes Bos: You're right Firefox 71 released December two. So it was 11 months from the time of recording that it got launched. And it looks like it's in Firefox 71, which is good. Everybody has fired off 71. That's the most stable and it is not in any other browsers not even behind flags. No at the moment. But once it hits in Chrome, every other browser runs on Chrome now. So we'll start to see I'm really excited to get that and I've got handfuls of little, even building my beginner jazz site. I've ran into two or three little things. I'm like, oh, give me some sub grid right now.
Scott Tolinski: You know what I want more than sub grid, why element queries? I have react, what
Unknown: the heck, what the heck
Scott Tolinski: I use, I use a JavaScript library for element queries. And it's like been giving me a lot of guff with my server side rendering, because it's like now you got to tell it to relook at the the sizes of everything on Mt and Reno rehydrating all that stuff is just no fun. So I really want element queries, please.
Wes Bos: Yeah. I don't even know what the where it's at right now.
Scott Tolinski: I don't know if it's anywhere. I mentioned it on Twitter. But yeah, no, no, no, it's it's it's not a lot of fun to do them as they are right now. But yeah, okay. So let's get into the next one, which is the the fourth most popular episode. And that's a boot camps at verse school verse self learning. This episode aired on March 13. And let me see what episode that was March 13. This is Episode 126. We talked about what we did, I went to college, West went to a university for business tech. So I went to school for music. We didn't necessarily take typical career paths of getting like a CS degree or necessarily a bootcamp. But we're both largely self taught web development. And we talked a little bit about the pros and cons of self teaching versus going to college versus taking a bootcamp from our perspective. So yeah, that was a really good episode. I knew that one was another one people had been asking for a lot. Yeah, I had a lot to say about that. And it's something that I've been thinking about with our kids, right now that our kids are alive. It's sort of like, well, when they when they're old enough to go to college, like, what is the landscape of going to school to do it? Like, would I go to college if I had to do it again? So these are all questions that I'm largely thinking about right now for myself.
Wes Bos: Yeah, I think we were really well placed to do that episode, because like, obviously, we're both self taught. We both went to higher education. And I have taught a number of different boot camps. I've taught hundreds of people in real life. And I've now seen them go on to, like some of them are. A lot of them are smarter than I am. You see this type of stuff that they're working on is pretty incredible. So go back and listen to that episode. 126. I'm pretty proud of that one. Yeah, me too. Next one we have here is the fundamentals. So something that we set off to do in our home a couple of months ago is to do a bunch of fundamentals episodes and sort of break down not to teach you the fundamentals. But to break down what are the fundamentals in we did one on HTML and CSS. We did one on JavaScript. We did one on server side and we did one on design. And the the fundamentals for CSS is number three. That's episode number 158. And we just broke broke down like what What are the different things that you need to learn? Because, like we always chant, learn the fundamentals. And like, don't just focus on the fundamentals in here, like a lot of people are like, well, what are they? Like? Do you have a list of things that I could focus on? And we made the list? So check it out. That is episode number 158. Yeah, those
Scott Tolinski: fundamentals episodes were all very well received. People seem to really, really like them. So check out all of the all of the episodes in that series. This next one arrived, February 20. And this one is absolutely no surprise to me. This is the second most popular episode of the year. It's Episode 120, Gatsby verse. Next j. s. I see people linked to this episode all the time. Whenever anybody's asking about what's the differences here? What are these platforms? What do they do for us? When would you use each one? That's such a huge question I see it asked on on Reddit all the time. And I'm so thankful that, you know, one of our viewers almost always post the link to that episode and says, this is a great explainer for why you would use each of them. And granted, it's changed a little bit in turn, maybe we should be doing like a 2020 version of Gatsby verse next week, because both the platforms have evolved quite a bit. Gatsby got themes next JS got API routes and static static building. So both of the platforms are evolving, and maybe we should do a follow up. Gatsby verse next to Electric Boogaloo.
Wes Bos: 2020 that's actually going to be a wicked search term. We should jump on Gatsby vs. Next. 2020 2020
Scott Tolinski: don't steal it. Anybody.
Wes Bos: That's always the modifier. We gotta roll it out. All right, and the number one episode of 2019 it was actually released. what's what's the seventh month of the year? I always do this,
Scott Tolinski: too. I'm so glad that you don't know that. Because I don't know. It's It's July,
Wes Bos: July.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, I always go to one that I know. Okay, so I know may is five. So then I can count up a couple and I can't get there. People who are actually normal are probably like, come on. You don't know, though, the month just don't
Wes Bos: do it. Anyways, uh, that episode is episode number 162. And it's the fundamentals of JavaScript. And that this one is way ahead, almost almost 10,000 more listens on that episode, then number two, which is incredible. And I'm really proud of this episode as well, because we basically just broke it down. I was luckily lucky enough to spend the entire year working on a layout for a beginner JavaScript course. So we could lend a lot of that to the episode. And just breaking down the different parts of JavaScript is what you should focus on. What are the fundamentals so very proud of that episode as well. I'm quite surprised that even though it was released, what five months ago? It's by far the most popular episodes that one will probably go down as one of the top episodes ever,
Unknown: ever.
Wes Bos: We should look real quick. What is our most popular episode ever?
Scott Tolinski: Look,
Wes Bos: let me look it up.
Scott Tolinski: Most Popular episode ever is react hooks. That true. It doesn't include this Spotify listens but
Wes Bos: yeah, most popular episode ever is react hooks. Which ship fundamentals of j s is just like 2000 listens on now.
Unknown: Wow.
Wes Bos: So yeah, amazing that fundamentals one is gonna is gonna go fire man props who sponsored that one? They're lucky funnels of JavaScript Log Rocket and Freshbooks. Greg got a deal there.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah.
Wes Bos: Oh, that's good. So
Scott Tolinski: speaking of Log Rocket, and Freshbooks, one of our sponsors today is Freshbooks. So they're going to help us with especially right now year, the end of the year is such a huge time for bookkeeping, services and software. And this is where companies like Freshbooks really excel because they make a lot of this stuff. Yeah, I don't know if you've ever used QuickBooks. But I opened up QuickBooks for the first time when I was like 20 years old. And I was like, wow, this application is hard to use. And so so many of these bookkeeping applications that are modern, like fresh books have come out now trying to solve that problem and just make things easier. It's the absolute best kind of software for this if you're doing any sort of freelance business where you need to pay people track invoices, that is something that I hate doing is keeping track of my invoices. And I love it when my software lets me know that, hey, this person paid hasn't paid here. Do you want to resend this? Do you want to give them a little little slight little nudge? It says hey, do you want to you want to pay for this? So check out fresh books. They're a longtime sponsor here at syntax now, you know, it's the end of the year. I want to thank all of our sponsors. I want to thank Freshbooks but specifically they've been one of our first sponsors and been with us for a long time so head on over to a fresh freshbooks.com forward slash syntax and put syntax in the How did you hear about a section? We know you love to do that. So please head on over to freshbooks.com forward slash syntax coupon code or let them know that you heard about us syntax.
Wes Bos: Awesome. Alright, so next up, we're gonna talk about personal stuff. So what did 2019 look like? Like both professionally, but also personally, I think that those two things sort of meld each other together, just because of this podcast. We talk a lot about our lives, we also talk a lot about what we're working on. So you want to give us a rundown of 2019 there, Scott? Yeah, let
Scott Tolinski: me just start off and say 2019 was absolutely bananas. It was absolutely bananas. So we have a two year old and Landon, he is amazing, right. But I wouldn't necessarily call myself the most experienced parent at this point, because we had one child, and he was just a great, great little baby. But there's two of us work, you know, being able to watch him. So our daughter, Brooklyn arrived in May, and it was a, it was a huge event. For me. It was huge. Because now all of a sudden, our family is where we want it to be. I don't think we're gonna have any more kids. And we're just very happy to be where we are. But at the same time, you don't sleep, you are constantly. Now with two kids, it's so much harder to get that personal time that my wife and I both like whether that's in the gym, we're doing coding outside of work, or for me just simply running my business. So everything had to become more flexible, as it became more chaotic. And now Brooklyn is absolutely amazing. She's an incredible baby. I love her so very much. But it has made life an absolute chaos fest. It's just been just been bananas. So a lot of this year has been a complete blur to me, I don't really even know where the time went because most of the time was spent chasing kids around or getting business going. But I somehow managed to produce and release 12 courses on level up tutorials.com. And that was no small feat, it was really difficult. And there were some months where I was very concerned about being able to actually get the courses out. So for those of you who don't know, level up tutorials is kind of like a magazine subscription, where you get a new tutorial series each month. It's like 20 videos long. But I managed to do a couple courses on TypeScript. A couple of courses on Gatsby animating react, React Native, we had a couple of guest authors for the first time, Travis Nielsen and Spencer, Carly, and soon to be James quick people that I really love their content. So it was just absolutely huge year for me in terms of growth. I launched this new, newish version of the level of tutorial site, a lot of changes in the codebase. My gosh, just like looking back and thinking about how much effort went into this. It's just unbelievable. The huge production value changes, I got a new camera new lighting system, I completely redid my office and to be like a set in that has been huge for me what else the codebase. and level up tutorials is completely different ending this year. This version isn't released yet, but it's like 99% done. The codebase is now 100% TypeScript, whether that's the API is TypeScript. The front end is now TSX. And TypeScript. The framework is now using next j s instead of Meteor. That's a huge change that's going to go up and one that I am being very careful about finishing. It's now using mongoose instead of Meteor, it uses a new account system. And we now are going to have server side rendering for all logged in users and all that amazing stuff that next gives you I just can't believe how far the site has progressed, how many things I was able to put out, while being in a complete daze of not sleeping, and all that stuff. So that was my year. And it was it was absolutely wild and incredible. And somehow we managed to release two episodes of syntax every single week on top of that, so
Wes Bos: it's true. I don't think we missed one. No,
Scott Tolinski: no, no, we don't miss was call us. Who's the sharpshooter? I don't know.
Wes Bos: I don't know anything Coby shooting Colby Colby. Yeah, that's amazing. Actually, I'm, that's amazing that we have capped out two episodes every single week. And I don't think anything else in my whole life has been that consistent, other than putting out this podcast, and it's totally just because like, I have to do it because God's showing up. And we sold the sponsorship spots, and Scott has to do because I'm showing up you know, and like we just sort of keep each other accountable for this type of thing. So it also hasn't felt like too much of a slog either like some days where like, oh man like it's Monday already with the record again. But but generally it's just been like, Oh, this is kind of fun to do. I always like leave recording this podcast been like That was a good one. I
Scott Tolinski: enjoyed that. Oh, totally. The caffeine has been something that's propelled me to do each episode. I like to think I would like to thank my lovely wife, Courtney, my amazing co host, Wes and caffeine.
Unknown: Thank you.
Scott Tolinski: pushing me through.
Wes Bos: All right, 2019. For me, 2019 was similar to Scott it was, it was a really tough year for me just in terms of feeling like I was not getting as much done as I had hoped to get done in the year. And feeling like I wasn't as productive as possible. Because I think like, every year before this, I've always had big leaps and bounds whether it's huge increase in numbers in my email list or launching new courses, something like that, in 2019 was really hard for a number of reasons. One of them was we had a new baby in June as well. And that was amazing. We're really excited about that. But that paired with one of my daughters who does not sleep Hmm, is just absolutely I was just just like a zombie for a good chunk of the year.
Scott Tolinski: And we talked about how not sleeping is just absolutely devastating to every Yeah, you get your your temper is a little shorter. You don't your energy levels are down your intellect is down. not sleeping is absolutely a huge killer.
Wes Bos: Yeah, like I had a good sleep last night. I went to the gym this morning. And I feel like on it right now, like, just ready to take on the world. And huge to do list. I'm going to sleep through it. But a lot of the days were spent sort of half capacity, which is really frustrating. And, like I feel I feel for people who have it worse than I do. Because I certainly have it very comfy work from home, I work for myself. I don't have to commute things like that, like I certainly have it really good. Imagine being a single parent to
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, I thought about that. That would be so incredibly hard shout out to the single parents who be PBL are amazing.
Wes Bos: I think one of the episodes I want to do next year is like talk to a mother who has learned to code after having kids because I certainly heard from a few people and like yes, do that. That's that's that's really tough. So we're gonna bring someone on in the new year to do that, that shorter sort of show.
Scott Tolinski: If that sounds like you, and you want to even show on the show and chat with us. Oh, you have people in mind?
Wes Bos: Yeah, well, I've got a couple of people. But if you sounds like you as well, like maybe even having a couple of people on to, to share how they did it would be interesting. So get in there. Yeah. So what else we had a new baby in June, which is amazing. Personally, we bought a cottage, which was a long term goal of ours, we intentionally bought like moved to a cheaper city, so that we could divert some of our housing funds to buying a cottage just because we work for ourselves, I want to be able to go up there in the summer and things like that. And that was a huge, a huge goal for me. And we hit it and we're so happy about it. And as we sort of lined up with the baby, so I took a three month maternity leave, which was amazing. I always see a lot of these people who work for like Facebook and whatever taking paternity leave. And we don't get that as self employed people because because of we choose not to pay into employment insurance. And because of that, we don't get maternity leave, we don't get paternity leave, we don't get top up or anything like that. So it was kind of cool to be able to just say, you know what, taking three months off, so like I cut my, I cut a third or sorry, a fourth of my year out just by doing that. And I don't regret that at all. I'm very glad I did that I got to spend a whole bunch of time with my kids in the summer, we made some amazing memories. And that's probably one of the things I'm most proud of this year as being able to just disconnect like, go to my GitHub and look at my GitHub, you can clearly see where I took time off.
Scott Tolinski: That's a my biggest thing of FOMO is your I guess this is an iPhone mine. Oh, no. But you're you're seeing your college. I'm so Tgn over that cottage. That's Oh, yeah. Amazing. And you Congratulations.
Wes Bos: That's amazing. Thank you. This one company on a shout them out. Get dev dev mugs. It's dev mugs.com. They sent me my GitHub history on a mug, which is cool. I kind of want to get another one that shows my gap. And just like like, like, hold on to that and be like, yeah, that was cool. Because like, we're not gonna have any more kids. That was my one chance. And I'm really glad that I did it. What else here, I made the biggest course I've ever made in my life this year, which was my beginner JavaScript course. And this is by far the hardest course I've ever had to make. Because teaching beginner stuff, at least I think is much harder than intermediate or advanced stuff. Because Yeah, you can't assume anything. You have to start from the ground up. And taking something which is not linear, like learning to code is you do a little bit here, you learn a bit here you do, of course here you here sort of going all over the place and trying to convert that into a linear course where you try to build upon what you've learned, but sometimes you need to look ahead Things you don't necessarily know. So just basically laying that thing out and investigating what it is that you should teach a beginner and making it fun and making all these exercises and styling them. And that was a slog. It was it was really hard. There's a lot of times where I didn't it felt like homework to me. And that's when I say I felt like homework. I mean, there's that feeling in my life where it's Sunday night. And I don't want to do this. Yeah, yeah. And I very rarely get that feeling in my career. We're talking to my wife. And we're like, we both love Mondays. I love Mondays, I love Mondays. Yeah. And sometimes I was just like, man, I got like six more months of this thing. And I want it to be good. So I'm spending a lot of time on it. And luckily, I could just keep chipping away, keep chipping away, keep building stuff, investigating how to best teach this stuff, talking to a lot of people who are struggling with it. And the course is massive, like I spent, I spent the like my earliest notes date back like three years on this thing. But basically the entire year, every single day, I just sat down and worked on this thing. And I finally was able to launch it a couple weeks ago. And it's done really well. And now I look back on it and go like, Oh, that was great. I'm so glad I spent all that time on it. But during it, it was like, Oh, this is this is hard. Like I really committed to this, this really big thing. But now that it's out, I'm really happy. I think it's going to be like one of these fundamental building blocks of learning JavaScript. So that was a huge milestone for me this year. And now I'm back, we're really recording my advanced react course right now. And I'm, I'm slinging graph QL. And like, that's really fun to me to be able to get back into the more advanced stuff as well,
Scott Tolinski: totally.
Wes Bos: What else a lot of this year was spent on I was working with the developer Louis, I know he listens to this podcast, rewriting a lot of my course platform to next .js unfortunately, is not launched yet, just because I haven't been able to give it my attention. And I think that's my like biggest downfall of this year is that my attention was kind of sharted meaning that like or, like sharded sharted. Like in shards? Yes, I didn't short. It was not sharded. But basically, there's like a lot of things that need my attention. And I'm very good at not caring about a lot of other stuff. Because I know I have this one task at hand. And I don't let busy work get the best of me, which is a good quality to have. But also, sometimes I need to spend an entire day doing email or accounting or looking at the other areas that I've sort of been neglecting so early next year, and we'll get this thing launched. I'm really excited. It's amazing. There's a lot of like little bugs on the course platform that this will fix as well. So that was my 2019 a lot of ups and downs. But overall, I look back at it. And I say wow, I'm proud of of what I had accomplished.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, I am very proud of of what I've accomplished this year. And
Wes Bos: you did 12 more courses or 11 more courses than I did. Oh
Scott Tolinski: my gosh, it was very difficult. Yeah, it was very difficult. Cool. So do you want to get into the next sponsor, which is one of the things that I really want to dive into more this next year, which is Prismic.
Wes Bos: Yes. So Prismic is a headless CMS that makes it easy to build website pages as a set of components, you break your pages into sections of components, and then using react view or whatever you like, you make corresponding slices in Prismic. Start building the dynamically. So take your website, slice it up into different sections, create your types on the Prismic back end, and then pull in that data with a graph qL API into Prismic. They've got lots of examples with next and Knox and you you get the point all of those front end frameworks, you want to check it out@prismic.io forward slash syntax. And again, this is an absolutely hilarious landing page to go. There's animated GIFs of Scott Nye, there's team West and team Scott, you just need to check it out. prismic.io forward slash syntax and try it out. Maybe around the holidays in the new year. You want to build a website. try this out. Yeah,
Scott Tolinski: try it out. Cool. So let's get into the last section of this is stuff that we've learned this year. And let me tell you, I have learned a ton of stuff turns out when you do 12 courses a lot. And this is this has been great for me. What are the things I learned that I actually don't have on this list is I learned to be a better speaker. I've done now a few talks. I hadn't done that many talks in the past, but I've done a few talks and this most recent talk I did a develop Denver, I felt like I was just really comfortable for the very first time and just felt very, very good with it. So that was a skill that I picked up this year is to just feel it feeling more confident in my speaking. I learned a lot.
Wes Bos: Do you think that's because you do the podcast podcast. I can't even say The
Scott Tolinski: well the podcast for me has been. No, I'm used to talking in front of a microphone Anyways, this
Unknown: point like that. Oh, yeah, thank
Scott Tolinski: you. No, I never I hated doing, like stand up book reports or whatever. In school I hated doing that stuff. I really hated speaking in front of crowds. And to be honest, I think I got, I think it just by pushing myself into the deep end and making myself do it, I think it was just like, remove the scary element of it for me, and is more like, I have these things of value. And people want to hear me speak them. So there's no reason to be nervous about it. And to be honest, I don't know. I think it was just a practice thing.
Wes Bos: Yeah, that's good. I find that as well. Like I've been, I've been doing speaking engagements for probably almost 10 years now. And I always like I'm in the, in my hotel room trying to practice because it's not very good. And then once I get up there just banging, right, like doing so well, I just get such energy from the crowd. And I'm so happy to be in a place like that. Because I remember certainly, like, even at my wedding, being like a little bit afraid to do like the, like the speech and that and now everybody asked me to emcee their wedding.
Scott Tolinski: Oh my god. Yeah, I did. Like I did. My brothers. You know, my brother's wedding. I you know, did the best man speech. And yeah, I was very, very nervous for that. I think I would be much better at that. If I were to do it again. Yeah, so Okay, I learned a tech wise, I learned a lot of TypeScript. I did lots of TypeScript. And I taught two courses on TypeScript, one with react and one, just straight up TypeScript. But more importantly, I got my hands really dirty. And I rewrote my entire application in TypeScript. There's so many dang files. My whole API is in TypeScript. Now. My whole front end is react and TypeScript. And let me tell you, I absolutely love it. I think there was a episode maybe like midway through the year, where I was like, I don't know, we'll see. I'm not totally you know, sold on any of them. But I am sold on it. I like it a lot. It works really well, it it finds all the bugs for me. And it makes me feel good. So next thing I learned was I learned how to be better at debugging, Wes taught me about the debugger in the browser, but I also learned about the using the debugger in Node. More importantly, I got better at every single tab in the dev tools to solve my issues. And I really feel like I'm at my, my very best in terms of being able to solve problems. What's something that you made, let's do a little bit of back and forth instead of me rattling all these off?
Wes Bos: Yeah, I got really good at the just vanilla JavaScript Dom API. Because of building this beginner JavaScript course I my idea was don't use any frameworks or anything like that, just JavaScript. And I didn't want to just like console log things all day long. I want to actually build interaction and learn about events and event delegation and all those things. And in order to do that, we need to actually build things. So I got really good at the vanilla JavaScript Dom API, I was already pretty good at it because of my JavaScript 30 course. But I feel like I can pretty much build anything. And I had all these tweet tips over the year of things that I learned while doing it. And I don't know, I just feel like I'm I'm really on it with that stuff. And it's not all that useful to me in my production applications, because I mostly use like a react in my production application. But it it does teach me just to be a better JavaScript developer in general. Yeah, you're
Scott Tolinski: not gonna be relying on the the framework, quote, unquote, as much totally whatever framework that is,
Wes Bos: yeah. What else I did react hooks and suspense. Yeah, I learned a lot about both of those things. Even though suspense is still not out. It might not ever be out, it probably will be at some point. But I totally shifting the thinking of how to approach your react application, more so with react hooks. And then the suspense stuff will be pretty interesting as well, when it comes to loading data and loader screens, things like that. I'm excited for that to come out. I'm really excited for that to come out because it's going to give me another excuse to refactor my code base. Now, I
Scott Tolinski: really love react hooks and I, I learned so much about react hooks this year, rewrote nearly all of my application to function based components, there's still a couple that I haven't. But in the process of it, you learn about, you know, the benefits of using hooks and how they can make your code cleaner. I wrote so many custom hooks, and I absolutely love to use them. There's so many things that have gotten easier for me by abstracting it out into a hook and being able to push it somewhere else. So that's something that I really spent a lot of time on this year with react hooks as well.
Wes Bos: Um, other things I learned I finally learned about the audio visualization API or not, basically there's a huge Audio API in the browser. And I've always wanted to make really, really for the the syntax website. I wanted to make one of those like dancing bars based on the frequency and time waves and I've never there's like two problems. First of all, I didn't understand the audio Audio API. And second of all, I don't understand how audio works.
Scott Tolinski: You could ask your your buddy who went to school for audio engineering,
Wes Bos: yeah, I should have. But I learned enough about both of those things much better at the JavaScript part than actually understanding the audio. But I certainly understood frequency and time waves. And one of the things we build in my beginner JavaScript course, is this really cool visualization. And that's something I've been wanting to do for years, I probably tried, like six times over the past years, and finally got it and where I understand every line of code.
Scott Tolinski: One thing that I really spend some time on was felt, especially towards the end of the year, when spelt three dropped. I really like it. I'm not using it for anything important or anything, but the amount of code and you know, typing, it saves us really great. For the most part, I found everything to just work in terms of examples and documentation. Let me tell you, spelt is the gold standard, like react really needs to learn from this. So it is you because they have this huge examples page, where it just shows you how to do basically all of the stuff that you would want to do. But since Veldt is a little bit more, I want to say opinionated than react because react just sort of like, Well, you know, there is no react way to do you know, let's say drag and drop, or animations or whatever, you will use these libraries. So you have to go somewhere else, but was felt in the examples. It shows you all of that stuff, and more. So okay, here's how you work with props, here's how you work. And they're all editable, essentially examples that run live in the browser. And if you want to learn animations, or spring based animations, hey, there's an example. And here's the spilt way to do it, because Phil has a package. So because of that, it's a little bit more opinionated, and it's so easy to learn, so easy to look at a huge, huge fan, I'll probably be doing more svelte in 2020.
Wes Bos: Another thing I looked into a lot is some upcoming API's around shape detection. So if you want to be able to do things like face detection, barcode detection, whether it's a QR code or, or just something on the side of a package, if you want to look up nutrition information, and text detection, there's these new API's that are coming to the browser surrounding that. And I think they're pretty cool. Fortunately, they stopped working. So I couldn't include them in my course. But hopefully, once they are up and running all I'll add a video on them. Other things I've been really looking into this year are just like headless CMS is. So that's obviously a very popular thing right now if a couple of them sponsor this podcast. So I've just been trying them out. And one, one dream I have is I want to make a GitHub repo that shows how to use all of these different headless CMS is with like Gatsby or something like that, right. And like that would be a really cool because you could have like, I have some some notes written somewhere where like, create three different data types relate two of them, like one to many, and then many to one relationship, and then just have the ability to just to pull in this data route from page to page, fetch the data and display it on the page, like very simple, but very good example of showing how to use all these different API. So I personally tried out Prismic Sanity, WordPress with the graph qL API, Keystone j s Hasura, Prisma. Obviously, Prisma. Two, I've had some, it's not out yet, but I've had some calls with them. Just kind of looking at that. So the headless CMS space is certainly one thing that is going to be on my mind in coming up in the 2020 as well.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, absolutely. There's just so many good ones out there. And this is the space that we all want to watch for 2020. And could really, really changed a lot of people's workflows. The last one for me is I learned just a lot about not necessarily JavaScript itself, but how to write good JavaScript, how to write good code, my programming skills in general got better. I had a problem in the past where I, you know, when I'm developing things, something comes to mind, you need to name something, I would just pick something on the spot, things wouldn't be necessarily organized in the right way. And this year, I learned so much about organizing, naming, making things very clear writing better comments, writing better organized and looking code when to abstract things and when abstracting is going to cause you trouble. And I learned it all kind of the hard way by experiencing troubles in my code. And I still find things I just found a I found a variable yesterday in my code that was like, Man, what was it was so it was like the visibility set or something. And I'm like, No, that's a Boolean. It's a true or false it needs to be is is whatever this is modal open. This whole system and I saw this one, and it made me really upset when I saw it. So I'm still finding these things in my code to improve. And I think overall, I'm just writing better code at the end of this year. And I guess you say that every year, as long as you're progressing, you look at your code you wrote last year, and you absolutely hate it. And that's a sign of growth in your programming. So I guess it's where I'm at.
Wes Bos: Yeah, I read to you every year. I like it's funny. The better you get a programming, the more you realize how awful you were before, like five years ago, I thought it was pretty good at JavaScript. And now, now I look back at it and be like, Oh, man, I was I was awful.
Scott Tolinski: Really, like I want to like put myself in my 2011 shoes doing the JavaScript I know now. And I think about like all the things that we hired and like Freelancer to do that, like are just so simple in my brain now, but at the time seemed like they were impossible.
Wes Bos: Mm hmm. I'd certainly learned a lot about the nitty gritty of JavaScript the past year just doing research for this thing like nothing teaches you to get really good at something then trying to teach it to other people. So absolutely. closures and hoisting and objects and the this keyword and the new keyword, all of the ins and outs and all of the little edge cases of how these things work. I feel like I have a really good a good handle on that stuff. Just because I've had to record a bunch of videos on it. I wanted to make sure I was dead set on understanding it before I went forward and taught it. So that is 2019 a year in review filed definitely not a clip shows a good year hard year for both of us. But looking forward to 2021 to thank everybody for tuning in and listening to this podcast. It's been a hoot we did well over 100 episodes this year of this podcast, you may feel like one of our best friends because we talk to you for a couple hours a week every every week.
Scott Tolinski: I hope so. I feel like I'm a pretty good friend. So yeah, be be friends with us because that's cool. Um, yeah, so this is the hardest show if this is your first episode, if your first episode then you might be a little bit confused about the show. But if this is your first episode, we do sick pics at the end stuff that we like it can be really anything. I have another podcast people loving my podcast pics. I you know, I get a lot of comments about how people love these. They're sort of like, I don't know, shady people podcast. There's like swindle and then darknet diaries and all these ones. So this is a podcast I've actually had as a sick pick before. But here's why I'm sick picking and again, the season two of this podcast just launched and I had actually unsubscribed since I thought it was a one off thing. No, this podcast is back. It's the dream. The dream was all about multi level marketing schemes for the first is sort of like here's how these companies get Jay. Here's their influence and here's how they're terrible. Well the dream is back with Season Two focusing on the wellness industry. Instead of multi level marketing. They're focusing on crap you know, just supplements that don't do anything vitamins, probiotics, there's gonna be a whole episode. The first episode was on essential oils. Let me tell you, I love this podcast. And I'm so glad they're taking on this industry because it's an industry that I feel like I have a little bit of knowledge on I you know, I work out and I do supplements and stuff like that. So I'm very interested in the season and I'm excited to have them debunk a bunch of stuff that I have thought to be true. Wow,
Wes Bos: I had unsubscribed from that one too, because I thought it was over. And I just I think of all the time how much I love that podcast. so so good. Just just subscribed. Good. Yeah, I'm in a sick pic. Synology diskstation dS 918 Plus,
Scott Tolinski: I got one of those. Yeah, man, I
Wes Bos: for the longest time, I've been just using these little passport drives to backup my stuff. And then I've been mirroring it to backblaze b two. And they just got sick of doing it because it just takes so freakin long. Like I wanted to delete one of my old courses from my laptop, but I won't do it until I have two copies somewhere else right and I need one on my hard drive. And the neat one uploaded and my internet upload is so brutally slow that it takes like, I don't know, 200 gig course takes like a day or two to upload. And like I can't close my laptop. And so I finally buckled down and got the diskstation it put 16 terabytes in the sucker and I set it up with raid. So if one of the drives dies, then you could just swap it out and put a new one in. And it's amazing like this. This thing is great. Like I have these different folders on it. And I can just drag all my old courses onto this thing. It's fast as heck because I'm on a wired gigabit connection. Yeah, so it takes like a couple minutes to move over 200 gig course. And then over the next couple days it will upload it automatically to backblaze for me, so it'll duplicate that on up for me and that's amazing. And then I'm also running like Plex and MB and some auto downloading software. Where and we'll do a whole episode on like, what our backup strategies are. But, man, I can't believe how awesome this thing is like it. It all just works. Like I had some trouble with the backblaze where it wasn't backing everything up, but I just restarted it fresh and it seems to be working perfectly fine. So super cool that Synology diskstation dS 918 I know they're smaller ones.
Scott Tolinski: What do you use for the backups on that you use time machine or what do you use to do the automatic backups
Wes Bos: I don't have automatic so what I'm using it as it's like a it's like a cold storage where if I'm done with a course I drag it off you can use it as a time machine. But in my experience Time Machine over a network has never been reliable. It's always like worked for a month or two and then it gives you some weird error time machine in general is not very good piece of software but
Scott Tolinski: that's why I was wondering because I was that I have a time machine on my Synology but I don't like it and I was looking to maybe do something else.
Wes Bos: Yeah, instead of that I've just been using like one of these $50 passport two terabyte drives. And that works really well for me and then the the benefit of that is when I want to if I need to restore I just put the drive into another computer and and restart it what we should do people have been asking if we can do a show on our backup strategies. And I also have been doing a whole bunch of networking equipment recently as well. So we'll we'll have to plan those for the new year. Sounds good. All right, thanks so much for tuning in. We just the last episode of there
Scott Tolinski: we got one more next one the next case or hasty will be but all right, this is the last tasty or tape that my arm getting messed up with these namings. This is last tasty of the year. So I hope it was in fact tasty
Unknown: face, please
Scott Tolinski: head on over to syntax.fm for a full archive of all of our shows. And don't forget to subscribe in your podcast player or drop a review if you like this show.