Unknown: Monday, Monday, Monday, open wide dev fans yet ready to stuff your face with JavaScript CSS node module, BBQ Tip Get workflow breakdancing soft skill web development hasty as crazy as tasty as web development treats coming in hot here is Sarah CUDA, and Scott.
Totally at ski.
Oh, welcome to syntax. In this hasty tree, we're all going to be talking about something that, you know is very important in our community that I think often goes under looked and that is positivity and how it can affect both you your work your organization and everyone around you all the communities that you are a part of. So this is syntax, the podcast with the tastiest, tastiest webdevelopment treats coming in. And with me, as always is West boss. What's up everybody? Hey, I am Scott Dylan ski. And Wes and I were just talking this is going to be a fairly hasty, hasty treat.
We were saying that that some of the hasty treats have gotten a little tastier than hasty or lately, so this one might be not super fast, but it's gonna be trimmed down. And what we're gonna be doing is just really diving into how positivity can affect you in your workplace, your communities, all that stuff. This episode is sponsored by a new sponsor the show and one that is really super cool. You're all in one, check out his native script, if you have not heard of native script, it is, well very much akin to other tools like React Native or something like that. But let me tell you why it will. It allows you to build real native apps using either Angular view, or vanilla j s. So you're not locked into a specific platform. You can use Angular view, you can use TypeScript, you can use normal JavaScript, and you can actually build native apps, you know, some tools like PhoneGap, or Cordova, what they do is they throw your stuff in a web, it's like a web view, right? In the in the application. It's actually like a little mini browser. And the application just allows you to connect to API's on the device. Well, native script is not that this is actually building you into real native device, you get native performance, you don't you it's not using web views like that, you're actually using real device API's. It's cross platform. So you can deploy to iOS and Android, it is just really super cool. And you know, one of the things we love about Native script, like so many of our other sponsors is that is 100% open source. So it's 100% open source, it's free to use and it's easy to learn. So head over to native script.org forward slash syntax and get started today. Seriously, it native script is a great way to take your front end skills and move them into real native app territory. This is I love stuff like this, because it's the convergence of what we already know, with some stuff that is difficult to do. And it makes everyone's lives easier. So native script, has a great website, lots of great documentation, check it out. Native script.org is super, super cool. Awesome. So let's jump right into it. We're gonna be talking about positivity in our web development industry. And you might think that's a little bit cheesy. But as Scott said, I think it's really important thing to, to get into and to understand. I'm also often very proud of the web development industry and our community that we have, because we're often like, I feel like if I compare our industry to some friends who work in other industries, I think we're on a bit of a forefront in terms of pushing for things like mental health awareness and, and now and positivity. So we saw we talked about last week, which is StackOverflow has has changed their ways because people have been complaining for years about about all of the negativity and the way that people approach these questions. It's funny because Scott messaged me this morning and said, Hey, what do you think about doing signing on positivity as a hasee? tree? And I said, Oh, yeah. Did you see the Linus Torvalds stuff? And he said, No, what? And it's perfect timing because Linus Torvalds, I think, as I say, Torvalds he's the guy behind Linux and get right like, he's the guy that created Linux. That's why Linux is called Linux because his name is Linus. Yeah. And then he took some time off and built this thing called Get that everyone and use this. So obviously, a huge, huge figure in the industry. And he sort of had this reputation as like he's obviously an absolute genius, but he's had this reputation of not being the most nice guy he's had the reputation of not being very empathetic as to driving people away, that are in the industry and just being very, very brash, very aggressive, very, I would even go as a to be mean to others.
members of the community. And it's funny because we have this word for people who who run these open source projects called BD FL benevolent dictator for life where somebody who just like runs the project for absolutely forever. And it's the people have sort of excused it for a long time because he's such a genius. He, you kind of say, oh, like, Oh, that's, that's Linus or I get like he made Linux. I guess he can be a dick. Right. But Steve Jobs, same treatment, too. Because Yeah, I mean, you heard about that book that his daughter wrote that it was horrifying. I mean, he Yeah, Dick. Yeah, absolutely. So he came out with this letter on on the the Linux kernel mailing list, which was, I want to apologize for people that might behavior, personal behavior that has hurt and possibly drove people away, I'm going to take some time off and get some assistance on how to understand people's emotions and respond appropriately. So I think that's amazing that he stepped up and said this, I think it's really cool that our industry has drove him to understand that it's not okay to to be this even if you are this genius, because like I'm just thinking about like, there's so many open source authors out there that are like a Dan Abramov comes to mind. Immediately, where, obviously genius, amazing. He's one of the lead devs behind react, he has this amazing story about how he didn't know how to program. If you ever listened to his story on a couple different podcasts. It's amazing. And now he's like, one of the core devs to react. And he's the nicest guy in the world. And I think that he's the perfect example of like, a genius, running a very popular open source framework catches a lot of flack from people who have opinions to throw at them. But still, they'll push us forward in the nicest way possible. Yeah. And I mean, you don't have to go very far outside of like GitHub issues to really see the problem occasionally, when people will just come in and just be rude to one people that they're using software that they're not, they're not paying these people to use their software, but they're acting like they're entitled to all of these things, right. And if it doesn't go 100% correctly, for them, they throw essentially a temper tantrum and a GitHub issue. And I would not have the restraint that so many of these open source maintainers have, it's it's unbelievable. Sometimes when I see somebody leave just an extremely rude comment about essentially what is your your hard work, and then they come in and respond very rationally, very reasonably. And sometimes the other person will come in and apologize or something like that. But like, really, it's it's so impressive. It is like a very, I don't know, it's a very honorable skill. It's one of those things that you can only just be appreciative that these people exist that have these abilities, because otherwise it could just turn into a shouting match. And so many times on the internet, it does when people you know, get behind their keyboards and their fingers start tapping, everybody gets a little bit of a no, it is, yeah, it's like a little bit a little bit fiery and fiery, you can probably point the finger at me in no time. Because, like, I know, I've been there many times, if you are having a bad day, or you're being piled on on the internet, sometimes, like, I have 140,000 Twitter followers, and if you say something that people don't agree with, or something that is slightly wrong or out of line, then you get piled on, right. And it's not always the intention of everybody. But the fact that 300 people do it can not, that's not a normal thing to have. And you can sometimes let a little snarky tweet go or say something that you may have regretted it. And I think that's like positivity is something that I'm always striving for in the development industry, because I think that like I see some people who do it to a tee. And I think that it's such so good for our industry, and so good for pushing the web forward. Yeah. Again, it's I don't know what it is without like communities. I mean, whether or not it's Hacker News, or it's Reddit, or it's Twitter or whatever, but when communities of people get together and just start dogpiling. Like, I feel like it might be a good opportunity, anytime you see that dog piling going on, to just stand up for anything, right just to be like, Listen, is this really is this really necessary to be this aggressive? Or to be this angry about something right? That honestly probably doesn't matter? Yeah, yeah. I often see that like, oh, I'll chime in. I like pull Twitter up on the weekend. And I'll see people fighting about CSS again. And CSS modules and whether it's a good idea or not, I'm like, what, what are you doing, like, go build something, go do something constructive. Some people just love to. It's not my personality to have conflict. It's not my personality to forever debate something. I'm very much
Have the personality be like like, Fine, go, I don't care what you use. And this is what I'm using and like, like, I care about why you think that this is the wrong way to approach it. Because obviously, you're likely a smart person to have some good opinions. But when it turns into something where people are just kind of piling on and trying to argue their point to the death, there's a certain point where it just kind of walk away like fine. Live your life, you do you joke, me and my wife always always have each other when, when we don't agree with each other. We just say you do You are laughing? Like, what's gonna win this? Yeah, but just do you live your life to the fullest? Yeah, and whoever wins, I know, this is you're not you and your wife on argue on the internet. But whoever wins internet arguments, like nobody wins internet, are you? No, no. And the only people that do are the people who are charismatic enough to inspire the other person to change, you're not going to win anything by being aggressive, or by being angry, or by being rude. Like, and I get it. Some people even just do it to troll because they want to get a rise out of other people. But like, yeah, that's the world you want to live in, where everyone's just like, aggressive and rude to each other all the time. And like, I get no, yeah, right. People could then take that and be like, Okay, well, this generation is getting soft, or something like that. But like, dang. And like, I just I want to I want to live in a world where people are nice to each other. Like, I want to, I want to see that. You know, I don't it's not that I can't take negativity, it's that I, I'd rather see positivity, on the same point that we're not saying that everybody has to be nice and like, not ever approach something and not ever disagree with someone, because that is how our industry moves forward is that we have discussions about the best way to approach something. And I think that there's very healthy ways to to approach it like another really good example I have right now is john David Dalton, who's author of lodash. And he was very controversial when he came out with lodash. Because underscore already did that. But right now what's happening and like, I think he did it very in a very respectful way. And I think what was cool is he's working on one of the most controversial things right now, which is trying to figure out how to get ESX modules into node. And if you haven't followed this, it's this huge thing where if you want to be able to import and export, like you are doing in browser code, there's a whole bunch of gotchas in how common j s, which is the export default and import that works. It's, it's there's all these trade offs. And he's working on this thing called ESM, which is basically just showing that it can be done. It can be done properly without having these trade offs. And, but he's also on the the the committee that is trying to figure out how to do this. And he's making sure that like, I want to hear from node authors, I want to hear from browser authors, I want to hear from people that aren't necessarily so invested in the JavaScript community, but maybe are a little bit outside. I think it's the best way to approach something that's so controversial, rather than just having a huge tweet storm about why you think something like he's leading meetings and and actually writing code to see if we could solve this in a certain way. So it's really interesting to see that and I think it's very healthy for the community. Yeah, no, definitely. Hey, I, you had a really nice little note here, which, which is like, never assume malice. And this just like, Yeah, really. I mean, anytime that Courtney and I ever have an argument, by all means, we don't even argue that much. But when we do, it's almost 100% of the time because of just some miscommunication. And like miscommunication This is between two people talking in real real time, right? But think about how how many of those human sort of elements are left out of a conversation when you're on the internet, right? And so oftentimes, you're not picking up on body language, you're not picking up on tone, you're not picking up on sarcasm, and and it's easy to miss communicate in real life, just imagine how much more easily it is to just have these miscommunications when you're talking with no tone or any of that sort of stuff. So don't always assume that the way somebody is saying something is, you know, coming off harsher or aggressive or whatever, unless of course, they're personally attacking you, then you can probably assume that they're intending to do that. But like, no, for the most part, like I don't know if you've ever read two sentences, like I could read the same sentence on two different days and on one day, I'm having a terrible day and other day I'm fine and I can read the sentence and I can't give an example off the top of my head but like, okay, here's the here's a good one. Here's a total like, some viewer could comment on my video. your background is blue, and I could respond. Oh, it's blue. Hmm. You think it's blue? Like I have a bad day like is it is grayish? Like I could get really angry but no, like, or I could read that. Yeah, it is blue. Like it just totally depends on your mindset, how you interpret these things. And and if you always just assume
The best rather than for the worst, at least as much as your possibility, then I think, like interactions just become that much easier. Totally. I get questions all the time where people say, Why didn't you use Redux? or Why didn't you use x, y and z? So you could read that as Why didn't you use Redux? You idiot? Or the question is almost always, hey, curious, why didn't you use Redux? Because I would love to hear your opinion. I value it. And I think that would be interesting to hear why you approached it in such a way. And that's almost always the second way. Yeah, I can, like quickly read a tweet or quickly read, especially if it ends in a wink that always gets me for some reason, in a way, like a big FAQ, you know, it doesn't
like finger emoji. Yeah. But it's it's so funny because like the person that's, that's like, saying, it might just be like a little,
like, trying to be funny with me. And you always have to, like, read something over a couple times and be like, I understand. And we talked about a couple episodes ago, where if someone doesn't speak English, they might not know how to properly phrase something. And like, I'm sorry, they obviously speak English. But if the English is not the first language, all of that can be lost. All of that can be thrown up that are never mind all of the stuff that is lost just because it's the internet. So definitely something to think about when you are interacting with someone online. Almost always they are in coming from really good space. Yeah. And if you are on the person, like the side of the person asking that question, like, do keep that in mind. If you're asking Wes why he uses Redux. Maybe don't throw in the word idiot or like, like, Don't Don't make it aggressive. Right? If you actually want to get an answer, that's the whole thing. I'm not convinced that the people who are that rude like, actually want an answer. I think they're just yeah, to be like a look at what I know, kind of thing. And again, what is that doing? That's not doing anything for you? It just makes you look bad publicly. So I don't know. Yeah, keep that in mind when you are asking questions, if you like, actually want an answer how this thing could be perceived. Let's go ahead. And let's go ahead and talk a little bit about I don't know, I think one of the things that I'm so impressed with occasionally is, again, people that I see on a public spaces, whether or not these are celebrities, or other developers, or people who are just really good at maintaining sort of like a positive outlook and things is that they always, essentially RS inspiring people to be better, right? They're inspiring people to change, even the people that are aggressive and rude to them, instead of responding back with rudeness, or aggressiveness, they're responding in a way that is going to make the person who came at you with that heat, it's gonna make that person feel bad for coming at you with that heat. So I think that's such a big thing is that you want to you want to be the person that diffuses the situation if there is is a fire and you want to inspire people to want to be better? Absolutely be the Be the change you want to see. Is that the that's the saying inspired the change that you want to see. Yeah, I think that like that, that's I really, really important to see, because I think that the as much as the negativity is the disease, I think that positivity is very contagious. And if we sort of all work together to to make it to change the tone of voice, whether it's GitHub or Twitter, or, or whatever it is it like even just even just conference talks, sometimes people see people slamming, slamming specific technologies, or I once said at a talk and I said, like, no one uses just CSS like as like, like, I was trying to like, explain, like, I was thinking I was doing a tooling talk, you know? Yeah, like, I was like, so so many people use CSS, or so many people use sass or whatever, right. And I was like, no one uses CSS. And then like, people got all angry about that, because they're like, well, I use CSS, am I a garbage developer? And I had to, like, be careful. Like, obviously, that's not what I meant. I was, I meant to say that a lot of people use pre processors. Yeah, and I didn't mean any malice from that, but people got all up in arms about it. And which is funny because and even especially if you get like a, someone takes a picture of just one slide out of context and, and tweets that out, and then people will gang up. It's thankfully never happened to me, but it's something that can really happen. And it is almost never the intention. So I think if if that was something like that, figure out the intention, and and and try to be positive, but inspire the change that you want to see. Yeah, I mean, your example was just so good because almost everything that you're going to say that's like going to slam something else could be more effective if you take the opposite approach to like, re raise up the things that you support, rather than to put down the things you don't support. Totally, totally awesome. I think that's it for today. If you have any other tips or also if you if you know anyone in the industry. I have some here Chris coiour Addy, osmani, Sarah dresner all these people I look up to and say like you
are amazing for the amount of the amount of heat that you much cut, the amount of conversations you're pulled into. And just handling it really, really well i think is amazing. So if you know of somebody who is awesome at that, make sure you tweet it at syntax FM, because it's it's also worth that these people should hear that they are doing a good job, because it's likely that they've made a decision at some point in their life to push forward this positivity. Yeah, absolutely. Cool. Well, I think that's it again, be excellent to each other and just finish it off on a bill and Ted quote there. But yeah, I don't have anything else that this is a pretty hasty, hasty treat. hasty. Thanks for tuning in. And we'll see you Wednesday, whose face
head on over to syntax.fm for a full archive of all of our shows. And don't forget to subscribe in your podcast player or drop a review if you like this show.