Unknown: Monday, Monday Monday open wide dev fans yet ready to stuff your face with JavaScript CSS node module BBQ Tip Get workflow breakdancing soft skill web development hasty as crazy as tasty as web development treats coming in hot here is Sarah CUDA boss and Scott Taylor.
Totally in ski.
Scott Tolinski: Welcome to syntax in this Monday hasty treat, we are going to be doing something we haven't done before. This is an ask us anything or ask me anything. A UVA ama, where we have compiled a bunch of tasty questions for you. And these are going to be sort of personal questions. They range on all sorts of different stuff could be really personal technical, as Wes has here, the sky is the limit. So my name is Katelyn ski. And with me, as always, is at West boss,
Wes Bos: everybody. I'm excited to answer some of your questions today, this is gonna be a little bit different than the typical potluck as these ones are a little bit, they tend to skew a little bit more personal. So it should be fun.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, this should be a blast. So do you want to get into it by first talking a little bit about our sponsor today? Which is long? Yes.
Wes Bos: Yeah, we so Log Rocket sponsors, tons and tons of our episodes. And as you know, they do all of your error and exception tracking. And one kind of cool thing that they do is they have like this playback, where you'll be able to see what did the user do did in order to actually cause that error. And one of the real thing I want to focus in on this episode is their on prem, which are is on premises, because sometimes, maybe Scott and I forget that, like companies can't necessarily just reach for any old library or any old hosting provider, any cloud, these things definitely need to be approved. And especially if you are sending data outside of your application to a third party service. So one thing that Log Rocket does offer is what's called on premises mean that like, you can even get like GitHub on premises and companies that don't want their data going outside of their own servers, then you can get Log Rocket installed on your own server and on your own on your own premises and run it from there. So that's absolutely something that they offer. And if you want to check it out, go to Log Rocket, that's logrockt.com forward slash syntax, you'll get 14 days for free. Thanks so much to Log Rocket for sponsoring.
Scott Tolinski: Cool. So let's get into it. Some of these Ask me anything questions now? The highest voted ones? One we're going to take on? It says, besides coding and teaching, do you have any other source of income like stocks, bonds, crypto, etc? Me personally? No.
Unknown: Try to think about this. I
Scott Tolinski: don't think so. No, it's it's just what I do for work. We do have some real I mean, we have retirement accounts that are all invested. But I don't personally hold any stocks. I actually do it. I take that back. I hold some athyrium. But I mean, you know, I I'm not, I'm just holding on to it for the future. Or if it does anything, I'm not I'm not actually actualizing any of those things. So technically, it's not making any money. But no, I don't I don't have any additional income. You know, we've thought about owning rental properties or anything like that. But right now, we're just in a financial situation where we're, you know, we're just paying for our stuff. We just paid off student loans. And, you know, just trying to build a nice retirement little base here.
Wes Bos: Yeah, my wife and I bought an income property, I don't know, maybe three years ago, four years ago, and we're all excited about it. And it was good we bought like a rent out house Actually, that's how we met the contractor that works on our own house. We bought a totally rented house and move tenants in and everything like that, and I'm fairly handy and I can I can fix stuff and we had it for about three years and we started getting sick of just the owning a rental just because of things that pop up and having to like deal with like the furnace breaking and plumbing issues and I know that you can get like a what's it called property manager, but we were we were just kind of sick of it and also the the place that we did buy appreciated significantly like a third of the price that we paid nice, it just went up and we were really happy about that. So we're like, well, let's just kind of like take our huge appreciation and and run with it. We actually just bought a a cottage up north in Canada, which is kind of like a vacation property on a little lake and we took the money from that and we put that into to that so that's kind of one thing we are considering doing renting out the cottage but we have we don't even have it yet so we haven't gotten that far into it. So that's one source of income. I've flipped bikes on Kijiji, so I buy older road bikes and then fix them up and then sell them. So that's kind of one thing I do for a little bit of pocket money. And then investments I've I had a bunch of crypto before it got popular because people Bought products off of me early on in Korea. Like, like, I probably got, like, I don't know, $400 worth of sales. And it went up to like four or $5,000 at the height of it. And then I bought a whole bunch more at the height of it and then took a bath on that. So pretty much. I still have a bunch. I have a bunch of Bitcoin, but it's it's went down significantly. I'm sorry, I think I've sort of like evened out based on the amount I earned and the amount I lost. I think Bitcoin is really cool. But it's so every time I use it, it seems like such a pain in the butt. It seems like a huge, it's too technical. Yeah. And I tried to talk about this on Twitter, and I just got assaulted by all these like hardcore Bitcoin people, or crypto people and say you're using the wrong one or whatever. And like, if I can't figure it out, if I'm I'm very technical if if it's frustrating for me, there's no way that it's going to catch on for for other people. So I'm very I wish that this whole crypto wouldn't become a big thing. And I'm still very bullish on it. But right now, I'm not putting any more of my money or time into it.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, yeah, you just put it into it. And then if it does take off, and you'll you'll take that when and whatever. We've just had so much high interest debt for so long that it's like, like a high interest that was doing loans. My wife has a PhD. So that is like I have a mat or not a Master's, I had a just a bachelor's degree. And she has a PhD. So we both had student loan debt, and my student loan debt was okay. But hers ventured into sort of high interest territory in some regards. And there was a lot of it. So, you know, we just been focusing on paying that off so hard. And then we had a, for our mortgage, we had a like another supplemental loan, that was also a variable rate, and the rate just kept going up. So we've just been like, focused on getting rid of that stuff. And we just refinanced our mortgage. And like, I think, honestly, what is it may may, here is the first month where we don't have any high interest debt. For the first time since I've gone into college. I mean, it's amazing. I don't have any other loan or anything, and Courtney's just leasing hers right now. But we're like, oh, we're happy to be out of that. Now. It's like, okay, we get to figure out what we get to do next, and, you know, shove every year of retirement accounts and think about the future and that sort of stuff.
Wes Bos: I'm very anti debt. And like, I was, I was very lucky to like, when I was a kid, I saved all of my money. And then I have a job and a really well paying Co Op all through school. And I paid off all of my student debt by the time I graduated, because I was building websites for people, which is really, I know, super lucky, because I think I got off on a bit of a head start, my wife had a whole bunch of debt. But we paid that down pretty quickly after we got married. And now all of our investments, we have a whole bunch of different types of investments for the business, like just cash that we have sitting in the business, investment or retirement, stuff like that. And almost all of that is sitting in what's called index funds, which is a mix of stocks and bonds. You can look up Canadian couch potato, if you're interested in how that works. I know that they have a similar thing in the states as well.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah. Yeah, it's been a big thing for for us. I mean, I've always, you know, at any job I've ever taken, taken the max contribution limits and all my retirement accounts, when I worked at U of M, this is actually kind of outrageous. When I worked at the University of Michigan, when I first started working there, they had a match and double for the retirement account. So they matched your contribution and then doubled it, which is outrageous. I hardly made any money. When I worked there. I was making like, you know, 24,000 a year or something and my retirement account, like bubbled up just because of how much the University of Michigan was contributing. They didn't stop that practice. Unfortunately, I think they were losing way too much on it. But I think that was really a cool thing that they did.
Wes Bos: That's awesome. Let's see what other question we have here. That was 10 minutes. For a tasty treat. That's fine. We can do we can do lots of these if we really wanted to. Oh, yeah. Next question we have is from petite. Thank you for the pronunciation on that. How do I build my online presence? I never know what to tweet or to write about on my blog. And this is the third most popular question. So a lot. I think a lot of people are feeling this as well. What do you think, Scott? How do you build an online presence?
Scott Tolinski: I think you build an online presence through quality content and consistency. That'd be the way you provide value for people and you do it consistently. And it will pay off. One of the things that that I really focused on again, when I was first starting was you don't want to think about how do I get 10,000 followers tomorrow? You want to think how do I put out something every single week at a certain schedule at a certain time so that people start to latch on to it. And the people who succeed are going to be the people who do that for 10 months. And if they don't see any growth after 10 months, when they may not they don't see a growth but if they don't see explosive growth after 10 months or five months or whatever, they just keep doing it and they keep providing value because as long as you're providing value and you're doing a good job, and you're growing and you're you're continuing to do this stuff at a regular consistency, you will find that footing, you know, it just takes that effort to do it and to grow day after day, week after week, week after week, and then you'll look up and like I almost have 300,000 followers on YouTube. Now, how the heck did that happen? I have no idea. I never thought about that. It was just like, Okay, I got 100. I got 10,000. I got 50,000. I got 150,000. Now I'm almost at 300,000. And again, I don't I almost don't even look at the numbers, because it's not important. It's about the content and consistency. Yeah, I
Wes Bos: think obviously, that I think that's probably the most important one is that just day in day out, keep doing that that thing. I think a lot of people also think that the tweeting is about them. If you look at all of the stuff that does well, for me, it's always How do I help people who are following me? And that's why Scott's videos, Scott has 300,000 people on YouTube. It's not because he's talking about, like, what he's building or how awesome a developer he is. He's like he's legit trying to help people move forward in their careers and make them better web developers. And I think if you're very selfless about, like helping other people, there's so much that could possibly be there. If you don't know what to tweet, like, What problems do you run into? What How did you solve them? And how can you help other people with that, I think also tried different types of content, I sort of stumbled into the hot tip, which is how I got a majority of my Twitter following is just, I just like, posted something and it sort of did well. And then I posted a couple more. And those did super well. And I was like, wow, like this is actually an approach. Whereas like I had been tweeting probably like four or five years before that, and I had moderate success. But once once I tried different types of content, you're gonna hit a nerve with something and then that's going to be your thing. Don't just copy whatever other people are doing because I think if somebody is already doing that, you see us on youtube all the time, people are putting little red circles around things or looking shocked in this
Scott Tolinski: thing like I want to go on a quick rant about those shocking is definitely is my least favorite thing in this entire planet. If you were to if you were to say what is your your most annoying thing to you? It's the like Macaulay Culkin look on the YouTube thumbnail. Like I can't believe this happened. Like, oh my god, I could rant about this forever. It is so annoying to me. I wish there was a report button that says this thumbnail makes me upset because like I would report all of those videos for making me upset. Yeah, I saw
Wes Bos: an article the other day that that YouTube is attempting to make the results more useful. And I think that they catch on to stuff like that, like I guarantee there's someone at Google writing a algorithm right now checks how shocked the person is. And, and they'd write an algorithm for little red circles that they put around things or, or highlights like these things, their tricks, somebody figured it out. And someone went a long way with that little trick. But almost always these things are, are sort of tapped out by now,
Scott Tolinski: hopefully. So this next one is from Steven, this is a fun one. What is your favorite tasty treat as in actual food. And before I get into it, my actual favorite food is I'm going to share one of my most embarrassing stories with all of you because this is maybe an a hilarious moments in my life that everyone else gets to laugh at. And I can laugh at now. I was taking Japanese in college in my sophomore year of college and we had one lecture a week that was in a large auditorium classroom, if you've ever seen those, it's like the giant auditorium. And this thing was filled it had, you know, I don't know a couple hundred people in a class. It's it's a big class. It's not a terrarium. And there was an instructor who was a really cool guy. I'm gonna say he's a cool guy. And he was just asking questions, and I happened to be not paying attention that day. I was coding. Like, in one of my music tech classes, I was really into this music tech programming thing that I was working on. So I wasn't thinking about Japanese. And he signals me out in front of everybody in the entire class, this entire auditorium. He picks me and he points at me. And he says, What is your favorite food? And I say shrimp in Japanese. And he's like, oh, shrimp is your favorite food. And I was like, yeah, shrimp, and the entire classroom starts laughing. I mean, keep in mind, he's asking this in Japanese. So the entire class is laughing. And at this point, I'm like, Ah, oh, no. What are they laughing about? What did I do wrong? Well, he didn't ask me what my favorite food was. He asked me what my favorite thing was. What's your favorite thing? And I said shrimp. And everyone's like, he's like, so your favorite thing is shrimp. And I was just like, yeah, shrimp of vari I love shrimp. And he's just like, everybody found that hilarious. And then I had to like once I got through everybody laughing at me. You know, I poked my my friend next to me and I was just like, what did I just say? Like what what just happened? there? My favorite fruit is not shrimp at the time that's the only thing I could think of. I think my favorite food is honestly sushi I go to sushi a lot and sushi at the CG market in Tokyo I we have this sushi place and in Denver here that I live by that has they fly it in Daly from Tokyo and the fish is just amazing. So if I could pick anything sushi, I love me some fatty tuna. Any of the just the sashimi. Is there any of that stuff? I'm all in? I'm 100% in. Yeah,
Wes Bos: it's it's so hard for me to pick a favorite i think is sushi probably in my top five as well. But if if I were to say like anything, it would probably be like a nice charcuterie board. Yeah, Salamis for shooto Yeah, nice cheese's. Along with that. It's probably what I my favorite food would be.
Scott Tolinski: I mean, that's got to be up there for me too. I'm a big fan of the meats.
Wes Bos: Got these meats? If you not have not ever seen people, like almost every day somebody sends me this YouTube video of Mark Zuckerberg. Have you seen that? burgers, smoking meats? Like a like an eight hour live stream on Facebook and somebody cut all of the times are these meats, smoking these meats, smoked meats, I love some good meats. And it's just like, oh, you're talking about meats? Yeah, just google Mark Zuckerberg meats. And you'll see he'll just laugh your pants off. Let me find another good one here. This is one one question I've answered a couple times I don't think I've ever talked about in the podcast West, let's talk about the plus or the cross symbol on the start of your prompt for the cobalt to what's up with that. So on my Zed sh prompt, I forked it from I think like the agnostic or and the agnostic had like a prompt that was like a lightning bolt or something. And I swapped that out to be a cross because I'm a Christian. And I thought like, Oh, just swap that out to be a cross as I didn't really want the lightning bolt. And I just left it at that. And then the theme itself got really popular. And everybody just left it there. And if people are just kind of like, what's the deal with this, this cross in the thing. And I've been meaning to make it like an environmental variable. So you can swap it out to whatever it is that you want, or just like fork it yourself, but I just never have gotten around to it. So there's no much else to towards that as I thought it would be cool one day and it sort of caught on.
Scott Tolinski: I love the I use a lot of emojis in mine. And like I've actually it's funny because I was using fish shell for a while. And then when I got my new computer, I decided to go back to z sh, as we say and really add and I went back to z sh and I installed a bunch of plugins to make it behave like fish. One of the things I really loved about fish was like the auto completion and the history stuff that it gave you. But you can get all that stuff through plugins for for z sh. The reason why I went back was specifically because fish has like really strict ways of doing everything. So if you were to copy a command that was written in bash and paste it in, it would work in NZ sh and bash, but it wouldn't work in fish. So I always found myself having to rewrite with the fish syntax. That'd be a giant pain in the butt. So now that I've configured my csh correctly to use those fish features, and like it's made me it's made me a little bit happier.
Wes Bos: Welcome back. Yeah, good sign.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, I know the fish is great. I still love it. I'm using a but to be honest, z sh feels nice to be back. I was on it for a long time. And I'm happy to be here.
Wes Bos: In Canada, we call it Zed. Sh.
Scott Tolinski: I yes. And you're wrong. Because that is too hard to say.
Wes Bos: It is too hard. I agree.
Scott Tolinski: Here's one from Arthur, how do you get out of a rut? How do you get out of it, right? Because here's how I get out of a rut. I, I change it up, I switch it up. So if I'm in a rut, I'm not feeling like the work I'm doing today is very positive. When I'm not focusing or I'm not in it, I'll change my environment, I'll go somewhere else. So I'll work at a coffee shop. When we used to work at an agency. And like there were some days you're just like really feeling it really feeling heavy, you get a little bit of a bad posture lean on because you're maybe getting a little sleep, go for a walk, change it up, switch it up. We used to just say, oh, okay, let's actually work from a different part of the office. Or maybe let's work at a coffee shop. I mean, the other Dev, we would hop hop on over and just walk to a different coffee shop and get some work done for a little bit. And oftentimes that will change an environment can pull you out of a rut. If you're in a deeper rut, a rut that like takes a lot of time. Some of the things that we've talked about before in terms of self care can be really important. My wife often talks about these strategies. She is a doctor of psychology. So she is very smart when it comes to these things. So she will tell me if you're feeling like this. What you need to do is get up get dressed, make the bed, get yourself ready for the day as in, do your hair. Don't just throw on sweatpants and a hat. Oddly enough, I'm wearing sweat pants in a hat right now. But don't just throw in sweat pants to the hat, do your hair, do put on some nice clothes and just feel like if you're not feeling outwardly good, you want to look outwardly good, because it may not seem like it will do a lot, but it does a lot. You have to respect yourself in those sorts of ways. And it will do a little bit of work to help pull you out of that rut.
Wes Bos: Yeah, I think I'm in a really good place where if I'm feeling in a rut with the work that I'm doing, I just switch to something totally different. I'll go record a YouTube video, I'll start building something that is I basically is like, like, what would I do if I had absolutely nothing to do right now good. Sometimes I'm sitting there. I'm like, Alright, I'm two months in on working on this course I have 5000 emails I need to reply to someone on Twitter is being a jerk. And I'm like, Ah, this is all black right now. And then for me, that's a rat, where I'm like, I don't feel like working on this thing right now. And everything else is making me angry. So what I do is I just like switch to like all the stuff that Scott said, but also just switch to doing something that's absolutely totally different. Maybe I'll work on a personal website, I'll record a YouTube video, I'll explore some new technology that is interested in and for me, that's always just enough to sort of reignite whatever passion that I have. And also, I think sometimes it's just a break. Like, I can't tell you the amount of times where I've just like, quit a day at 330. And then the next day, I come back at it, and I feel a lot better. So for me, it's just sort of getting away from whatever it is. And I understand not everyone is able to do that. There's people that like, I see the next month of my work, and it's all the exact same thing. And I'm so sick of it. And I don't want to get into it. And for those people, I would say like maybe try to do a tutorial, have some sort of side project, talk to your boss about going to some sort of meetup or something like that, because I think that will really go a long way.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, I think you're I mean, I think it's important to get away in those sort of ways. And we had a environment. One of the offices that I worked in was like a huge, like 3000 person office. And it was a giant building and it was right next to the highway and there was nowhere to go. So you were just sort of stuck in this office. And like one of the things I like to do to get away in that office was to simply just pick up my computer and go work in the lobby or the cafeteria or somewhere else I got away from my environment that I was in and change it even though it wasn't like a drastic change. It still made a difference. All right. Well, that's it for this Ask me anything. We are going to pick back up with some more of these questions and an episode in a couple of weeks. So if you didn't hear your Ask me anything question answered, No worries. We have another one coming in. If you enjoyed this, let us know we will do more of these asked me any things where you can ask us some more personal questions, maybe less technical questions. Otherwise we will see you on Wednesday, where we are going to be answering your technical questions in a potluck episode. So thanks so much for listening and we will see you on Wednesday base please head on over to syntax.fm for a full archive of all of our shows. And don't forget to subscribe in your podcast player or drop a review if you like this show.