Unknown: You're listening to syntax the podcast with the tastiest web development treats out there, strap yourself in and get ready to live ski and West boss.
Wes Bos: Welcome to syntax and Happy New Year to everybody. I know that our first show of 2019. But it is the episode where we're going to take a look back at what happened in 2018. In the web development world, as well as what are we looking forward to both our own personal goals as well as our predictions for what will happen in 2019. Today's episode is sponsored by two awesome companies. The first is century which is going to track all of your client side and server side errors and exceptions and provide you a whole bunch of data around what happened when this error happened. As well as Manning books. They've got a 40% discount for all of y'all at deals.manning.com. For slash web dev. Today we are spotlighting a book called electron in actions design I get a question about all the time. Do you have an electron course I don't. But this looks like a fantastic book to learn how electron works electron is the would you describe electron now Scott?
Scott Tolinski: electron is basically a way that you can publish desktop apps for both Mac Linux windows, whatever via the front end tools that we know and love like JavaScript and node j s. Well, I guess no J's is not a front end tool, but JavaScript, HTML, CSS, that sort of stuff to build actual legit applications. What's awesome about electron is that you can reuse components that you've built and things like that and react and, and oftentimes it makes having a web app and turn into a desktop app very, very easy. I love electron. It's one of those things that we often maybe talk a little bit about sometimes is like, maybe these apps are eating up the CPU or something like that. But a well made electron app is a well made app. I mean, VS code is is proof of that.
Wes Bos: Yeah. Awesome. So check those out. So How you doing today, Scott?
Scott Tolinski: I'm doing good drinking water from a giant boot. And I'm loving 2019 living the 2019 life,
Wes Bos: even though it's still 2018 on our recording this. This is one of the last of that energy, though. I'm
Scott Tolinski: feeling the 2019 energy. Yeah, we're not not just writing the show notes for this. This episode got me really hyped to start this year off, right? How about Yeah,
Wes Bos: yeah, totally. Me too, as well. It's it's nice to like, look back at the year and see everything that you've accomplished, as well as where we've moved as an industry in general, in webphone. I look back at the last year's version of this episode. And I was just looking at like, it was very like, not early days, but a lot of people were starting to notice things like next and Gatsby and one of our predictions was that tooling will get better. And I'm just like, ah, we've read a year is not really all that long. But we've really come a long way in terms of our industry, and just just a year. So let's get on into it. The first one is we're going to talk about what was hot in 2018. We'll take a look back. And then we'll take a look at forward what what looks what 2019 is looking. So you want to kick it off there? Oh, yeah.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah. And it's funny, because you I mean, you you just briefly mentioned it. But one of the things that I think was hot in 2018 was just really that tooling overall got a lot better. I mean, everything from mean, you think about even the improvements to things like create react app, and view csli. Next JS Gatsby parcel Webpack. For made it configurations easier to get started. I mean, there's just so many things built around this that have just again, like we even predicted, and we said that this kind of stuff would happen. Because you know, honestly, you don't need to write Webpack config from scratch for every single project, right? I mean, you've probably written one. And sometimes this stuff can be abstracted out into its own ideas or platforms, like create react app. And these, these things have totally grown in 2018 and even grown within themselves and just improved, improved, improved. And we recently just saw the crate react app to come out, which made a lot of things a little bit nicer and easier for everyone. So this was a big theme, I think, in 2018. And the amount of time that I spent about tooling is gotten way, way less than and many times now when I'm starting a project or even like maybe a quick code example or something like this. I do one of two things. I either just fire a parcel, because it's superduper easy. You just include a file and then it just starts doing its thing or I had to an online platform like code sandbox or something like that, and just fired up there. But almost never Am I thinking about tooling to start a project. Or maybe even it's Gatsby, I guess the most sites I did for client work or for myself this year was in Gatsby. And again, you're not thinking about the tooling there.
Wes Bos: Yeah, I'm just thinking back to everything I built this year and I did a workshop on progressive web apps that use parcel I built a bunch of sites using next JS I'm starting my own Gatsby base site right now, I don't think that I wrote an entire line of a config, I probably wrote a little bit of Babel config here or there. Yeah, I did write a little bit of Babel config in my advanced react course. But like, I think that was one of the hugest groans and pain points. I remember saying, like, near the start of this podcast, it's gonna get better. There's no reason why we should have to be writing this every single time we started an application. And it definitely has gotten gotten way easier. Even what pack itself is moving towards the sort of zero config thing where you don't necessarily need to be able to write these things. I'm so excited to just look back and say, like, wow, this stuff is so much easier than it used to be. And it's only getting easier, even like Babel with the preset envy. No, that's probably not this year. But that makes it really, really, really simple parcel parcel is just over a year old now. And it's making things really simple. They're doing some really cool code splitting stuff with parcel two that is going to be coming out. So I think even looking forward into 2019, this stuff is just going to get more powerful. Because I think they've they've reached the easy, and now they're looking at like what can we do to make things more more powerful, because I know, Dan Abramov has been tweeting some stuff with the what was it his like hot reloading, and whatnot. He's He's reworking how that stuff works to work with react hooks. So it's a good time to be alive, Scott?
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, I know. And then, man, everything. It's almost like you wake up every day, and it gets better, better and better and better. And by the end of the year, you look back, and you're like, Wow, I can't believe how many things have improved or grown. I mean, as even as we're talking or whatever, I'm adding things to this list that we have here already. Because it's like something else pops into my brain, right? I mean, things are just constantly getting better. And one of those things, I think that got better in 2018 was graph QL. Overall, I mean, yeah, it got easier, it got more accessible to pick up and just start experimenting with more graph qL API's exist now. So there's more that you can can play with, if you just want to try it out. platforms like Apollo just continue to evolve and impress like, Apollo has just continued to see growth. And and that's one of those things I'm excited for this year is to see even, you know, the continued growth there. And then that world, but also, I mean, you mentioned that you're doing a Gatsby site, I did a lot of Gatsby, this this year, Gatsby really made graph qL accessible, I could imagine that a Gatsby sites were maybe a lot of people's first experience with graph qL because he to build a Gatsby site, you don't need to use graph qL at all, you can do use it with the React stuffs and some static data, whatever is in there, and it works and build your site. But maybe you want to try out querying on a graph qL API with a markdown file or something like that. And Gatsby makes it super duper easy to get started with that. So these kind of tools, I think, just made Gatsby, you know, into the or not Gatsby graph qL into sort of a more usable space for a lot of people.
Wes Bos: Yeah, absolutely. I think because Gatsby doesn't require you to implement the API yourself, or implement resolvers or have to tangle with authentication. Yeah, it's it's just a query, you're just pulling data. I think that's really cool. I also have become a big fan of the graph. qL playground. Yeah. Which is like, it's like graph qL graph. Cool. How do you say that, like the graphical graph, graphical. It's like the graphical interface that you get with any graph qL instance. But this has a much nicer interface to work with it. You can have tabs, so you can save older queries. It's just such a nice little I have a desktop app installed. Anytime I'm working with graph QL. I boot that thing up? And
Scott Tolinski: yeah, I don't like the off off piece of that, though. Like with graphical. Yeah, in Apollo it like, had my auth tokens set up automatically. And like, No, I have to do it manually. And then, like, I have to do it each time I open graph. Oh, yeah. The only downside for me the interface and the saving all that stuff is great. But I wish it auto had my auth token in there just like graphical did.
Wes Bos: Yeah, that would be That's true. Because anytime I have to do that, I have to take my tokens and paste them into the HTTP headers, which is annoying. Yeah, if you want to do that,
Scott Tolinski: Yep. Yep. One of the other cool things in this space has been graph qL companies, especially ones that are doing maybe like API's as a service, and making this data available via graph. QL. So then, just like we mentioned before, with like Gatsby, you don't have to write your resolvers and mutations and stuff like that. You don't have to set up some sort of graph qL API. So these services like Hasura Prisma, take shape graph, CMS content vault has a graph qL API coming out. A lot of this stuff. I think this space is has been growing and you know, in my predictions for 2019 I think it's gonna continue to grow in this space, but really just making it super easy. We're easy to set up sort of a back end for these modern sites, and even maybe just like build a Gatsby site or something like that. So yeah, these these services have all evolved. And yeah,
Wes Bos: yeah, I had a note little later on. And then I was gonna talk about it now. But I think this whole, like headless space is so hot right now, a lot of people are taking a look at all of the different platforms, even if it's not like a, like a paid platform. There's lots of open source platforms out there. You hear a lot of people talking about headless WordPress right now as well.
Scott Tolinski: Yep. There's a WordPress graph qL API plugin.
Wes Bos: Yeah. And it works well with advanced custom fields, which is a plugin that a lot of WordPress developers use to create the interfaces and have existing data stuck in it. So it's just like a really cool space. Because I think people are, it's no longer that you build your app in like a server rendered. And then you use react to just like, kind of add additional things are starting to see people say like, I really like this experience of building in view, or in react or whatever. And I'm going to move totally over to the headless, which is, you write your front end in react or view or whatever. And then you just talk to an API on the back end. It's any number of these the headless spaces, even just from the sponsors on our podcast, you can tell that there are plenty of companies that know that this this area is becoming a real hot.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, absolutely. Also, I mean, another thing that, you know, has gotten evolved is CSS. I mean, CSS is always evolving. And I think in the last episode, you mentioned about that CSS is awesome mug, that's actually correct. Instead of the one where it's out of the thing. I think CSS got more more awesome. I mean, more awesome inside of the actual box. I mean, for one more people are using grid than ever before, which is no surprise, considering grid just continues to sort of become more and more useful as the browser support becomes, you know, more acceptable to be using grid. Now, I've been using grid significantly in 2018. And I personally, I just, I look forward to the day where every single person can reach for grid as the main tool and not even think about anything else other than maybe Flexbox for when Flexbox is appropriate. But I think grid is one of those things that grew in 2018. And every single subsequent year until, you know,
Wes Bos: yeah, yeah, I
Scott Tolinski: think grid is just gonna keep keep on that rise.
Wes Bos: Yeah, I can add some context to this just because in like, November, December of last year, I was finishing up my grid course. And then I released my grid course in January of this year. And when I was building it, it was mostly like a future tech kind of thing. When I released it, at that time, it was still a lot of people saying like, Okay, this is great. I can't wait to use it. I learned it, but I'm not like using it in production. And then now at the end of the year, I'm seeing lots of websites, lots of people say, Okay, I'm using this in production. Now this is actually something I'm able to move ahead. It's totally based on on browser support, I guess as well as people learning it as well. Being able to, to move away from we talked about the people using existing grids based on bootstrap, or people that have had been using Flexbox as a sort of stopgap until we got full grid support.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah. And I would imagine, once you get a taste of grid, if you are able to use it, you're gonna be using it because it is imminent, that positive of a developer experience that once you use it, and you're able to continue to use it. I think it's hard to put it down.
Wes Bos: Yeah, totally. I think like if you were to sum up the hotness words of 2018, I would probably say grid isn't there. I would probably say graph qL is in there. I probably say Gatsby is in there,
Scott Tolinski: dude. Geez, were his deed out. 20 feet out. Graph QL. Gatsby grid.
Wes Bos: The GTE out 2018. That's exciting.
Scott Tolinski: So just like a grid. Another thing that once you try it, you're not going to want to stop using it is sentry@sentry.io. Now Wes and I both use Sentry to track all of our bugs. And let me tell you why. Because once you have that visibility into the things that are happening in your code, it's hard to live without it. In fact, Sentry gives me so many visuals is like what's happening? What are the bugs? What do I need to resolve? What do I need to keep track of Sentry has it all right there for you in a big table showing you when these bugs last occurred, you can look at the last bugs in the last few hours or even the last couple of days and stuff like that, and really get an amazing glimpse into what's happening in your application. And so much so that, well once you start having things published without a system like century, then you start worrying about all of the things that could potentially be happening. Maybe it's these bugs here or there that you're going under the rug. And while the last thing you want is your customers to be the first ones to tell you about a bug so if you want to check out century and we highly recommend you do head on over to century dot o and sign up using the coupon code tasty treat all one word, all lowercase, and you will get two months free. So please do that those two months are enough to convince you trust me. So sign up sentry.io tasty treat as the coupon code, get those two months free and see why we can't live without century letting us know where our bugs are. So okay, so this was the CSS world. What are some more stuff that happened in 2018? Specifically react because react had a big year in 2018?
Wes Bos: Yeah, I was just looking back at the React blog to see what fell in in 2018. And what was before that, because even if you look at things like, we got fragments was that in this year, I
Scott Tolinski: think it was, I don't I don't even know at this point. I know, React is just been a steady stream of improvements totally a couple of years.
Wes Bos: I'm gonna say we got fragments just because we got Babel Babel seven this year. And that's when the easy use of fragments came out. That was great, the big two that we got. And as of recording, this, the hooks is currently being approved. So it's going to come to react. So it's not, it's kind of just a tail end thing. We'll probably talk about this next year on our year in review of, we finally got hooks, and now we are actually using it. And then the other one that was announced, but it's still not rolled out yet still being cooked is suspense. So hooks was the new API that allows you to use state allows you to use contacts, it allows you to do side effects and things like component will mount component did update and component will unmount without having to use a class. So you can just use a regular function, it allows you to sort of disassociate a lot of your stateful logic from your classes and just put them into their own own little hooks, which is nice. It makes sharing things like stateless stateful logic and any any other logic that you have, it makes it sharing it with the other components much easier. What that means is that we are going to see a lot less of high order components, and a lot less of render props. And of course, a lot less of actually seeing classes.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, and I don't know how much you got to use hooks this year, but I've been using them. And I love them, I absolutely love them. And it doesn't seem like a huge change on the surface. But I would say the cleanliness and just the visual of my code, the readability of my code, the organization of it, the ability to break things out, and things like that have just gotten so much better. I am just I'm totally sold. I'm very, very much.
Wes Bos: I've used them in probably three or four different situations. And I wrote one little custom hook that was listening for a web socket on Mount, updating the WebSocket when change and listening when it was unmounted and had its own internal state inside of that hook. And I just all tightened it up into this nice little thing called use socket. And then that gave me that just pipe to me state whenever the data changed. And I was like, This is tidy. I like this a lot.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, it's like Lego pieces for functionality, like totally like components where or, you know, just structure and things like that.
Wes Bos: suspense, maybe we should explain what that is, we haven't even had a show on react suspense just yet, because it's still I've had a talk twice on react suspense. And both times I've had to have some major updates to how it works. But the idea behind suspense was or is that you're able to suspend the render of a component based on fetching a synchronous data, as well as being able to disassociate where you fetch data from where you show your loading screen. So generally, your loaders and your fetching data tend to happen in the same place unless you have some weird pub sub set up. And suspense is going to allow higher components to be able to know when its children are fetching data, loading images, loading code, split bundles, it's pretty neat. I haven't used it's still like very, very early days for this, I would I would expect that we probably will get suspense in March, April of 2019.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah. And I'm really excited for server side rendering with it, because that's the that's the one piece, you know, I can't touch any of this stuff on the level up codebase until, you know, full server side rendering picture is there and stuff like that. So I'm really excited for the full release of all these things, and, and really interested to see is how they make server side rendering different or easier or whatever. I mean, things like suspense with code splitting, plus hooks. I'm just feeling like, yeah, this was a pretty sweet year for react announcements.
Wes Bos: Yeah, I'm excited to see what it's going to do to next j s. Because next .js currently has this get initial props lifecycle method that you can fetch on the server, and that's in a sink, but it's only at the page level and if you have a component that is seven, eight, levels deep that you need to like fetch data in for server side rendering, it's a bit of a pain, you have to walk the entire component tree and find any promises inside of that. And suspense is going to do that for you under the hood. So I expect that get initial props is going to be greatly simplified and much more powerful in next. Yes,
Scott Tolinski: yeah, cool. Another thing that we saw was a lot of improvement in the React dev tools, which is, it's a low key underrated thing. You know, when when something has very good dev tools, it always makes your life so much easier. And the fact that the React Dev Tools aren't like stagnating on sort of staying the same as the React dev tools are sort of constantly finding ways to make themselves more useful to you. And one of those things that that came out in that regard was the profiler, which is sort of like a way that you can look more deeply into how your react components are performing how they're taking a time, the sort of hold tree, what that kind of graph called is that called a flame flame. Yeah, flame chart. So the flame chart, just like you have in sort of Chrome dev tools to check the performance of your site in general, but it's all react based, React specific and really, really gives you just an insane amount of visibility to solve maybe one of those lingering slowdowns or something that you're trying to figure out where the heck, this slowdown or this issue is happening. So I'm, I'm just, I don't know, I'm so happy with how the React ecosystem has evolved in all sorts of ways. And again, the dev tools have just made it easier and easier and easier to that was
Wes Bos: so cool, I was looking into what they do, and they show you what caused a trigger. So it'll tell you which piece of state or which problem triggers a rerender, and how long that took. And it's not something you're going to use every day. But you better bet when you hit a really weird bug that's crashing your app, or is causing a leggy interface that's gonna really help you out. We also got the new context API. So context API was solidified in 2018, meaning that we no longer have the older context API that we have, we have the new context API, which allows you to define data in updaters. And anything you want higher, and then access it lower, along with react hooks, this is going to make accessing data anywhere throughout your application much easier. So I think it's funny because we look at all of these things, hooks, suspense, Dev Tools and Contacts API, and they all are focused on both, I guess they're focused both on developer experience, they make our lives easier, but also it makes things better applications at the end of the day, because you're gonna have better performance and better UI specifically in the suspense stuff.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, better applications easier. If one of those changes to hooks, well, not changes to hooks, but part of the thing with hooks in the context API, I think that's gonna make way more likely for me to use the context API because well, it's a little bit more, I don't know, it's a little bit more succinct than the render prop method and stuff like that. Not to mention, I was doing most of my state in Apollo. But this actually kind of looks very, very streamlined with with the new hooks context. So let's talk about JavaScript frameworks overall. Now, because we do primarily talk about react on the show. But there's been a lot of involvement, or even evolution in a lot of these other frameworks. For instance, svelte, in particular, I think, has been making a lot of noise, you saw it on the state of JS survey, where it showed up as the number one JavaScript framework that didn't like that was the write in candidate. So it was written in and it had the most votes. So speld, I think, is one of these cool things, if you don't know about it, it's basically a JavaScript front end framework that disappears on compilation. So instead of shipping the library every single time, you just ship a code. And the framework itself compiles away. And this is like, compounded when you do things like code splitting, because now when you have a new bundle coming in, it's just that that bundle and not the bundle with the library and all sorts of stuff. So spelt, I think, is one of those ones to keep an eye on in the future. But I think the noise that it made in 2018, is enough to definitely pay attention.
Wes Bos: Yeah, I think also view continue to impress and evolve, it's just getting more and more popular is seeing people that are just like betting their careers on it, which is really cool. It's It's It's I think, like the two big frameworks, now our reactive view, at the moment that might change in a year from now, obviously, there's still lots of other frameworks out there, a lot of people still using Ember, Angular, things like that, but view really, they like sort of came out of nowhere last year, and then this year, it's just like, super strong, super, super evolving. And you see a lot of like, really competent developers putting their weight behind it. What else happened in JavaScript frameworks, I'm just thinking about what the server side look like. And I think it stayed like fairly tame. A lot of there's a lot, no tools around graph qL, but a lot of the stuff is still just based on express that was kind of cool to see not not a whole lot of thrashing. In that we'll talk a little bit more about this. server side stuff in our predictions, though, for coming years.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, there's a few look sort of oddball things that happened just recently, even well, Microsoft, who was impressing with the Edge browser as well, they just announced that well, they're going to be moving to Chrome based engine instead of what was the one previously called, I forget what it was called. I'm blanking on it. But they're moving to a chromium based system now making it so that essentially, Firefox is really the only player who's not. And for better or for worse, you know, it's gonna make things maybe a little bit easier to think about maybe compatibility wise. But in the same regard, it's definitely said that there's less competition.
Wes Bos: Yeah, that was a bit of a weird one that I didn't see that coming at all. And it's interesting. So for those who maybe didn't hear is that they're going to take the engine out of Microsoft Internet Explorer, and just use the engine from Chrome, which is what happened to opera, what maybe like five or six years ago, and then just couldn't couldn't compete or couldn't keep up with it. And like the like, I don't know, web developer in me is goes, like Scott said, I'm a bit sad that there's less competition. But also, all of the browsers will still take part in the standards progress. It's not like everything is just going to be chrome and Google has, Google has the control over what the web does. Now, there still is a full standards process for that. And all of the browsers are still like, Microsoft still cares about what happens to the internet and what happens to web browsers because it's a major building block of their operating system. So they they care that I don't know, like web payments, make it in or they care that web USB makes it in or whatever it is, is going to be happening. So I don't sweating at all that much. Like part of me is like, Hi, yeah, that sucks. That it there's less competition, but like the actual like, person who writes code in me is going like, Alright, this is good, because now I can finally move ahead and some of these things.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, I had that I had the same reaction in that regard. There's some Microsoft actually did a lot this year. I mean, besides VS code, which we'll talk about a little bit, Microsoft did so much stuff. They bought GitHub, which is a big deal. But it turns out that GitHub has, since they've been purchased by Microsoft has been steadily adding a lot of really great features. I mean, every time I open GitHub there, it seems like there's something new, that's something that I feel like people have been asking for whether or not it's referencing issues, sticking issues, that sort of thing, and actions and all sorts of just like new updates. It's actually amazing. So I think a lot of people's concerns about what would happen to GitHub after Microsoft purchased, it can maybe be put to rest a little bit because they seem to be doing fairly well with GitHub so far.
Wes Bos: Yeah. And you know, one thing I'm really excited about is that like, so there's all these things like Microsoft is adopting Chrome, Microsoft bought GitHub, Microsoft has VS code. And then GitHub just bought spectrum vector is the kind of like, chat meets form for developers. And it's really aimed at figuring out why are we all in Slack, and this closed platform that deletes everything, and it's not searchable, and it's kind of a pain in the ass. And it's kind of the best thing we have right now. Other than like, using like a discord, or some Git Git or something like that. So spectrum is looking really promising. I'm still not like hundred percent sold on it. That's why I haven't moved my own slack over to it. But the fact that GitHub bottom means that they're saying, yes, there is a problem for developer communities. The old like PHP, Bolton board is dead. And for some reason, we're all on this proprietary slack platform that is terrible for open information. So looking forward to seeing what GitHub is going to be doing with that, which is pretty cool, because Microsoft bought GitHub, GitHub bought things. So maybe we're gonna have paperclip in
Scott Tolinski: spectrum Pretty soon, we can only hope. We also have in VS code also saw a ton of updates. I mean, we sort of briefly talked about this, but VS code, has she gotten better offer, I look forward to the monthly updates, and I'm on the insiders build. So I'm getting them very frequently. But every single time that that changelog comes out, I think everybody is like psyched to see all of the improvements that happened to VS code constantly.
Wes Bos: I cannot believe how quick they are putting it it's almost overwhelming. I'm like, Oh, it's been a month already. How are they putting out this much amazing stuff. And at the same time, the editor is getting like faster and better. It's not like they're adding more features and it's getting bogged down. It's unreal. It is
Scott Tolinski: it is very unreal. It's it's just getting better and better and better. And I think that's going to continue I think there's there's no reason to think that VS code won't just continue to grow and in 2019 and if you want to continue to evolve in 2019, you're gonna want to head on over to deals.manning.com Ford slash web dev. And what you're gonna get is 40% off every book or video course. And that includes a video course on electron intent. vs. Code is built in electron and it is one of the very best electron apps out there. So with more about this deal, this sick deal is with bots.
Wes Bos: Yeah, so they've got all of their books and courses on 40% off with the code syntax 40. I'm going to spotlight a book from Steve Kinney called electron in action, it's going to show you everything you need to know to learn how to build electron applications. It looks like you can learn how to work with multiple windows, building a notes application, using native file style dialogues and facilitating their inter process communication, testing the application having a tray module menu bar library, pretty nifty. I think it's so cool that if you know JavaScript, you can both build a server application, you can build a client side application and you can build mobile applications and now you can with electron you can build desktop applications, which is super cool. I think I'm gonna check this one out myself. Maybe over the holidays.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, you should because Steve Kinney is excellent. He's the organizer of the dinosaur JS conference, which is like one of the greatest conferences I've ever been to so Steve's a really cool guy.
Wes Bos: Oh, awesome. just sent a follow on Twitter he Steve Kenny on Twitter if you want to follow for more about electron so check that out. If you are interested in electron again as deals dot Manning comm forward slash web dev, use the code syntax 40. All one word for 40%. off at checkout. Thanks so much to Manning for sponsoring.
Scott Tolinski: Nice, cool. So let's keep this rolling into 2019. What are our predictions for 2019? We're gonna see how good we do at the end of the year, maybe? I think that a lot of these predictions, I don't know if you've listened to the rest of this episode are going to be fairly obvious. I think the headless CMS game Personally, I think this is going to get really real in 2019. I think this is one of those things that's just going to continue to evolve not only the platforms that are already existing, but I think more people will throw their hat into the ring, I think there's going to be more platforms that are built and designed for headless CMS stuff that are going to make it easy to just host an API somewhere and just fire up a static site or even a dynamic site or something like that. And I think this is just something that's going to continue to get more and more competitive.
Wes Bos: Yeah, I totally agree. I think also, we're going to see major leaps in the like rails for JavaScript, where you just like install this thing. And it comes with authentication and file uploading, or like the Laravel for for JavaScript, we're probably gonna see. So we had Sasha, on talking about Vulcan j. s, seems like Keystone is actually working on some stuff. Well, there's a couple other players in the space that are looking at the sort of like, you just like have an app with all of the things that you're most people have, like most notably authentication systems, file, uploading interfaces, rolls, you get the point, right. So I'm excited to see where that goes. Because that's been something I've been talking about on this podcast for probably a whole year where I hope that we will see it in the near future.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, and I think, from what we've seen so far in react over the past year, and what's already been announced, concerning there's just a ton of stuff that have been announced that's not going to be released until 2019. And a full capacity, I think react is obviously going to continue to see a ton of growth. And the changes that are coming in react are just going to make everyone's life better for whether that's with suspense and code splitting. And the hooks are going to make the initial onboarding and learning process easier for people, I think react is going to continue to see growth. I think, again, all of these, these additions to react are going to just show how excellent and how evolved, that continues to be.
Wes Bos: I also think developer experience will continue to get better. We're seeing this a lot, even in this year, where via build tools, as well as the API's that we're seeing and things like react are getting much easier for developers, I think we're hearing a lot more groaning or a lot less groaning sorry, we saw in the state of jazz, that people are overall happier with where JavaScript is at right now. So we'll probably see that I think that CSS and JS people will still be complaining about how CSS works. I logged on to Twitter this weekend. And it's funny, like probably three times over the last couple of months. I've logged on to Twitter and the on a weekend and people are just fighting about CSS. And they're like a huge thing, where people take time out of their weekend to talk about it, whether they hate or love, CSS and js.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, right people, people who write CSS and JS don't know CSS doesn't want to embrace the CAT scan. There's just so many stupid arguments on both. Yeah, so just do do what makes you productive.
Wes Bos: I will predict that people will still be whining about it. And I think if you Have a productive 2019. Stop whining about it and just pick one and don't fight the people on the other side.
Scott Tolinski: I think you are absolutely correct.
Wes Bos: Yes. What else do you think's gonna happen?
Scott Tolinski: I think some of the things that we talked about earlier in this year with design tools, I think, design tools are going to get more code he. And we've seen this from things like framer x, more recently, there's been a new hot one, that's a Kickstarter called modules, that is very react based. And they actually look to be more than just react based. But they're sort of these like design tools that are going to make code prototyping really easy. Maybe it's a design tool that spits out react or accept react components and allows them to be inserted into the design. Again, I think there's going to be some major advancements in this space, we did predict that it was going to get more Cody last year, and it certainly did. So I think that's just going to keep on continuing to happen. I think platforms like figma are gonna just continue to improve constantly figma in the same regard, like VS code is one of those things where every single month, there's just some crazy new feature that you've been asking for, or other platforms don't have yet. Or maybe it's some other platforms, hot new feature, and figma is just like, Oh, yeah, we can add that too. Hold on one sec, you know. So that's one of those platforms, I think that's just going to keep on evolving.
Wes Bos: That's exciting. One thing I hope we will see in 2019 is ESX modules in node. So it's probably been at least two, two and a half years of people looking at how do we get the import style from regular JavaScript into node, which is currently on common j. s. I know that there are tools out there, but there has not been a five a finalized spec of what that will look like. So I'm excited to see if that gets resolved this year.
Scott Tolinski: That's one of those things that I've always loved about Meteor is that your Babel config is the same on server and front end. So they've had imports imports forever. Yeah, forever and ever and ever. And so I've almost like not never, but in the past, I don't even know how many years I like don't write require ever just because I don't have to I think the first time I wrote requiring a long time was when I was doing my electron course. And I was just like,
Wes Bos: Oh, yeah. When you do a Gatsby site, and you write your Gatsby node, you have a transpiler on that. Oh, no, I
Scott Tolinski: use require I use require there. But that's only what you're requiring,
Wes Bos: like three or four things or it's like in the in the starter file are ready. So you don't need to require yourself you right? Yeah, yeah, totally. And Gatsby does a lot of the the requiring for you when you you just specify which plugins you want. So I'm excited. I know it's such a small thing. But it's it's such a huge decision in the industry. I'm so excited to stop accidentally importing things in my note and just stick with one forever. And then also a one thing I hope we see is the server side hot reloading. Yes, it hasn't gotten a lot of love. I think it's just technically very hard to actually do. But the fact that I need to still need to restart my server, even like I was doing some Gatsby stuff the other day, and I'm writing custom, like create pages and custom imports. And every time I change something in how that works, I manually killed the server myself. And then I was gonna write like a node mon to watch that file, and then rerun Gatsby develop. But I hope that that whole server side hot reloading gets a lot easier in the future.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, that's a good one. I think I'm also hoping for that as well. I think in 2019, I think we're going to see more wasum stuff, webassembly, whatever that looks like. I'm not quite sure yet. But I think we've seen enough of it in 2018, to know that it's just going to continue to improve and grow in all sorts of different directions. I mean, you can now have all sorts of different libraries integrated into your your JavaScript code, or your node cord, you could have a rest module or something converted to gasm. And used right in your project. I mean, I think there's going to be a lot of growth in that department as well, that should be superduper. Interesting for all of us. I also think code splitting is one of those things, that's going to get easier. And we've already seen the effort made in react. But I think overall, it's so easy to write a application right now that does not code split and serves this giant bundle. And while that isn't great, it's just so easy that so many people find themselves just doing it and not even thinking about it. So I would love to see code splitting just get easier and easier and easier. And that's one of the things that we're obviously seeing with react right now and how they're they're working with that. But dynamic imports and code splitting, just sort of just making it effortless, would be very, very nice.
Wes Bos: I think you're totally right on that. Like it comes back to the the tools that we've had, I think that we're seeing, not necessarily like developers only care so much about image compression and code splitting and offline mode and they would like these things, but you have to make sure that it's it's actually easy for the developer to implement them and we're seeing like parcel two is going to have a lot of that easy code splitting set up in They're require syntax or sorry, the import syntax will just work like that, which is really cool. It already doesn't and parcel one. Things like yeah, I know we keep saying Gatsby in this thing. But the Gatsby just like makes it work without you actually having to do a whole lot of setup, which is really cool. So no, I totally agree with you. I'm really excited about that for for the next year. I'm really excited to take a look back at this in one year, and say like, Okay, how far did we come for these tooling thing?
Scott Tolinski: Yeah. Yeah. I mean, because let me tell you, I, I have server side rendering. I have code splitting. And I have Apollo doing all of my data. And let me tell you, that was not easy. That was a lot of work. And it was a lot of frustration. To get all three of those things. It was almost like a triangle of like, you can have two of these things, but not all three. And by the time I got it working, I was just so like, I never want to touch this again, that I'm just hoping that that experience is not something that's perpetuated forward as we continue to improve our tools. Okay, so let's talk a little bit about our own personal reviews. We've done like the tech world reviews. So let's talk about our 2018 and our 2019. Yeah, so 2018 was pretty sick. For me, I released, I think I released why released at least 12 new courses. So that's a lot of videos, each one's like 20 videos long for level up Pro, I feel like I released more content than just that I had some bloggie videos on YouTube, and I had some additional content. But I released a lot of tutorials this year. And because of that my workflow got refined, my videos overall got refined, I got a new higher quality video camera, that shooting 4k, it's excellent, I'm recording screen recording in 4k, I've just overall refined my process and refined the production of my tutorials. So that's always great, because you know, each year goes by you want to continue to make that video content better and better and better if that's what you're doing for a living, right. I also saw major growth in level of tutorials as a platform from not only from how many users are on it, but from the changes to the platform itself, the code got better. using things like Sentry gave me more visibility into my code, that's not an ad, it just did all sorts of things in my platform got better in terms of code, quality code, organization, reliability testing with react testing library, I feel better about my code base right now than I ever have before. And I'm very confident once hooks and suspense and all that stuff comes down the line, it's just going to continue to be better. I also hired my first employee to work on the site. Typically, I'm the only dev on level up tutorials, I've been working on it forever and ever and ever by myself. Now I have a good friend of mine, Eric working on the code base, and he's just been doing an amazing job. So I'm just so psyched for that, because now I don't have to wait for me to be there to do every single little update on this thing, he can go ahead. And he's doing excellent work. So I'm absolutely loving that. And well, I did a lot of stuff. In person for the first time, I'm so used to being behind a video camera, or just a microphone, that I never really reached out and branch off to do conference talks. So I did both my first meetup talks this year, as well as my first conference talks this year. And we even did a live episode of syntax. So I really upped my speaking game in public, which it was actually easier than I was anticipating. Because it turns out when you spend so much time talking in front of a microphone, or just talking in general, it's really not that difficult to make that transition to talking in front of people. It's just a different backdrop that you know, so if I, I was able to improve my talking abilities or whatever. And I was really psyched, how all of my talks went this year, how our live show and this year, it made me feel very confident about doing more talks in the future, which had always been something that sort of well gave me a lot of anxiety overall.
Wes Bos: Wow, productive year for you. I'll go through my 2018 I released two major courses I released my CSS Grid course in I think January and then I also released my advanced react course in I think it was October October November I forget was about a month or two ago, the advanced react course was probably the biggest thing I've ever undertaken in a course just because it was such a new technology everything was changing very quickly. So I was very happy to to get that thing out as well as very happy how well received it's been been doing really well and people are learning a lot about react as well as graph qL and all the services around that was pretty cool. I spent a significant amount of time working on a and planning out a just a JavaScript course. So if you haven't heard yet, probably my next one will be a vanilla or not necessarily vanilla, but just an introduction to JavaScript. And that is the language itself browser API's design patterns. Lots of exercises. I've taken a lot of what I've learned, and what people have really enjoyed in my JavaScript 30 course. And I'm going to say like, Okay, what do people like about that? I've talked to like hundreds of people about like, what were your pain points when you're learning JavaScript? Or what are the holes in the things that are out there right now for beginners to JavaScript. So I spent a lot of time on that I'm still a ways away on that, just because it's, I want it to be like a, like a rock solid resource for learning JavaScript. So that will come out sometime next year, which I'm really excited about. I've delegated a lot to a contractor on my course platform, which is really exciting. And that was cool, because it's not like I'm working less on my platform. But it's just that we can get more features being pushed out. I've continued to work well as an assistant. So I've had a system for probably a year and a half. Now that's working really well. I spoke at lots of conferences, I did lots of workshops. I don't even know how many I did probably spoke at around seven or eight different conferences, I probably did five or six different workshops, which was good. Those take a lot of time. I love doing them, but they take a lot of time to prep for them and make the content. We did a live syntax at jams calm just a couple months ago. That was super fun to do I mess up for the first time. Yes. That was good. Yeah, I, I spent a lot of time this year focusing on my Instagram, continuing to see Twitter is still like the spot where web developers hang out. But I don't like putting all of my eggs in one basket. So I've sort of doubled down on what my Instagram was, I think I grew it 910 thousand people over the last year, which was good. And then I've continued to post my Hot Tips on Twitter. Twitter's still doing super well, for me growing that thing. It's it's just growing at a really good clip right now is seeing a lot of good feedback on the type of content that I've been posting. So that's been been really good. Nice. Yeah. goals for 2019. Let me know what you want me to go through mine and then go through yours? Or should we? Should we make our announcement right now?
Scott Tolinski: Yes, we each have an announcement that are somewhat Well, not somewhat. They're totally related, but not the same announcement? Well, I guess it is the same announcement. And let's just get it over with we are both having babies
Wes Bos: together. No. No, so yeah, with our respective partners, we are each expecting a new baby in 2019. Mine is coming late June and yours is coming.
Scott Tolinski: late May. Yeah, so
Wes Bos: very close together the girl. That's super exciting. We don't know yet. We're still, we still have to wait a month or two before we can figure out what we will having. But I'm super excited about it. Congratulations to you as well, Scott. Yeah, congratulations,
Scott Tolinski: man, I am I'm so excited it's gonna be, it's gonna be a fun couple of months for both of us. So we'll see what happens to those episodes of syntax around that, that time, when both of us are sleep deprived, rather than just one of us.
Wes Bos: Yeah, it's gonna be interesting, we might have to pre record a whole bunch before we get overly sleepy. So along with that, I'm planning to take some parental leave. So the one kind of neat thing about working for yourself is that I don't get parental leave from an employer. And we also don't get maternity leave from the government in Canada, I think you get eight months or something like that. I forget what it is. But we don't get either of those because we're self employed. And we don't pay into employment insurance as a choice, which means that we don't get any maternity leave. So we have been just like talking about what that's going to look like. And I think that we're going to take a couple months off myself, we're not totally sure that podcast will obviously still go on. I'm not sure. Like, obviously, I can't totally cut off because I still have a business to run. But I think that there's going to be a couple months there in the summer where where I take off and spend some time with the new family. And we'll probably do some sort of episode about that. Or I'll talk about what that looks like. If you have I know that a lot of people in our industry have taken parental leave as well. If you have any tips for what to do on that. I'd love to hear them. Yeah, what else schools I'm just gonna kind of keep doing what I'm doing over the next year. Everything is working out really well. I've sort of hit a really good spot in in what I'm doing in terms of my free stuff as well as my paid courses. So keep doing that. I've got a new website in the works I've been working on for about a month, I got this nice new logo that I'm super happy with. I am working on a new site and I'm moving over to Mark MDX which is like markdown in JSX. And I know put all of my blog posts and everything on GitHub, so people stop emailing me about spelling mistakes. I told you I'm working on a JavaScript course platform upgrades so I've had probably last like four months have been working on platform upgrades and none of that is live yet just because they are such such a huge change to the back end. It might not look like a whole lot of difference but it's a indication system is doing been reworked, the whole back end is written rewritten in react. So once that goes live, I'm going to be working on like a faster rollout where every commit is just immediately pushed out once it passes the tests, then pass that course wise, I want to do some sort of CSS course, maybe a VS code course more react. I'm not sure what I want to do after the JavaScript course. But I've got some ideas I'll probably have to after my JavaScript course I'll probably have to update my react courses as well. Once suspense and hooks are solidified. Once all the libraries know about hooks people emailed me like the day after hooks was announced and scores Yeah, is your is your course valid for hooks? And I was like, no, that came out yesterday. And it's not finished yet. But once they're all solidified off the update all my courses, so that they use the latest and the greatest, one of my goals is to publish eight YouTube videos. So I always talk about goals being smart goals, and it has to be specific, I didn't do a whole lot on YouTube this year, other than automatically push out my my free courses every every week, as well as I did like a couple little code alongs. But I really like doing that stuff on YouTube. I love doing that sort of informal off the cuff stuff on YouTube, people really like it. And that that's a huge, like growth opportunity for me. I'm at 60,000 followers right now, which is not great. So I'd love to, to grow that into something a little bit more significant. So I think I'll probably spend a little bit more time on on YouTube videos, as well as Instagram. These are like different platforms that I even though I'm comfy. In my Twitter, it's important to know that at some point, and I think even already, people are sick of Twitter, especially with a lot of the the negativity that surrounds Twitter, I know there's a lot of amazing people on Twitter. But there's also just a lot of like arguments and bots and negativity out there and bots. So and just like a lot of like politics and stuff, which you have to pay attention to, but not necessarily your entire day. So I'm going to spend a lot of time focusing on those other platforms to make sure that I still have a bit of a hold on them. Should Twitter go away at some point. So those are my goals, we'll see where they go. I was looking back at my goals for last year. And I definitely didn't hit all of them. But I definitely did have a fantastic year, and I'm very proud of, of what I accomplished.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, I mean, if my 2019 can be as productive as my 2018, then I'm doing the right thing. So Mighty 2019 is going to continue to see a lot more courses for me, I mean, that's sort of my bread and butter is making and releasing courses. I probably already have enough courses planned for next year that I could fill out the whole year. But you know me, I like to keep those open ended and evolve as we evolve as we go. So I'm going to be releasing a lot of courses, they're going to continue to get better, just like as they always have. That's the sort of the plan. I think in addition to that you're going to see, I have no like major announcements right now. But you're going to see so none Scott level up tutorials courses, and I think they're going to blow you away, because I am very, very excited about them. And I have no announcements at this second. But when I can announce something, I'm going to be very excited. And maybe one of those is going to line up when I'm on parental leave myself so that I'm not trying to record a course and plan of course, while a newborn is here. So that's going to that's going to happen in 20 2019, I'm going to be releasing some courses that aren't based off of my work, which is going to be really, really exciting for me and also terrifying because the only people who have ever released content for level up tutorials is me and the CO creator of level up tutorials who has since not been active in level tutorials since maybe 2012. So the new territory for me, there's gonna be a ton of platform updates to my code base, there's so many updates that we've been working on that are they're like sort of at a bottleneck that need a little bit more. So there's like maybe like five or six major features that are coming to the level of tutorials code base that are just sort of waiting on a couple of small things to get out. And so I think the early part of 2019 is going to see just an incredible amount of new things and level up tutorials comm I would like to hire more people to work on this site, both front end back end. However, if you are a inexperienced noted developer and if you have even more if you have experience with brain trees API in particular, I'm looking to lighten the amount of stuff that I'm working on server side just because I'd like to focus more on on course content, reach out because I am looking to hire a contractor who's a excellent no developer. Also more free content. I've been you know, I built level tutorials on free content, and it stinks when I don't have the time to do it. So I want to do more free content, both courses, both blog videos, both learning things, stuff that I've picked up here and there, maybe some code bloggie stuff, maybe some you know, level up talks about the news of JavaScript stuff, who knows it's totally open ended, but I'd love to do more frequent That's, that's really part of it more real world teaching sort of stuff. And I'd love to see my code base using hooks and suspense in a real way that make things even better. Because you know, me, I love evolving my codebase. That's pretty much it for me, I'm gonna have a very productive 2019 I'm going to have a new baby girl. And I'm very excited about all of that.
Wes Bos: Like it. Yeah. So hopefully you enjoyed this, hopefully you have a very productive and exciting 2019 as well. I'd love to hear what you are hoping to both see in our industry, as well as what you are hoping to do, personally and professionally in 2019. Make sure you tweet at syntax FM, let us know that. I think it's just good to hold yourself accountable, put them out there, and then come back to that tweet a year later and see how you've done. Yeah, if you want more info on setting goals, we have a really good podcast episode number 67. It's called goal setting. And that goes into how we actually set our goals and how we figure out how we're doing and course correction and all that good stuff. So go back to that if you want a little bit a year end your start motivation. Nice. What about sick Peck CMA sick picks, today,
Scott Tolinski: I have a sick pick. It's this TV show I've been obsessed with. I'm sure a lot of our listeners in the UK are familiar with this show already. But we just got it on Netflix here in the States. And it's only one season on the Netflix. But I have gone out and sought out a lot of the other seasons, because they're available on YouTube very easily. If you just Google it, this show is called fake or fortune. And it is all about art. Someone has a piece of art, and they're trying to figure out whether or not this thing is legit. Maybe it's a famous artist, or maybe it's someone like popular figure, like there's one that I think that was there trying to see if it was painted by Winston Churchill. And what's amazing about this is that this show keeps you on your toes. Regardless of what you think halfway through the show, you might not think that by the end of it, because they do all these different testing methods. They basically approach these works of art that they don't know who created them, or they're not confirmed who created them. And they use all of these different investigative techniques to figure out if this was this particular artist, or maybe it was a fake, or maybe it was someone else entirely. Or maybe it was an assistant who made it or something like that. But the whole point of the show is like forensic techniques, they're doing like science where they're looking at even like the chemicals used in the paint, they're looking at the context, they're looking at just under layers of the paintings to see you know, where the potential origins are, what country was made in, and I'm just like, constantly blown away by the show, because they'll just be like, Okay, well, the paint was this type of chemical and the canvas was this type of Canvas. And the style is this, therefore it must have been painted in this year in Venice. And they're like dead on every single time. It's so good. It's extremely interesting. And I love this show Faker fortune, check it out.
Wes Bos: Like it. I'm gonna pick the heavyweight podcast, it's from gimlet. So you may have heard of it, it's pretty popular. And I was trying to explain it to my wife about like, what it is, it's just goes into people's lives at different point where they had something in their lives that changed their life forever. And whether it's being bullied as a child, or whether it's falling in love. And it's just really interesting. It's so hard for me to describe what it is. But they're just stories of people's lives. And the Jonathan Goldstein, who's the host of the show, does a fantastic job. He's hilarious. So if you're looking for something that is a little bit lighter, even though it's called heavyweight, but just like kind of a light listening, kind of interesting. Check it out. It's called heavyweight.
Scott Tolinski: If you were to sick pick that first. Before I did mine, I would have picked the movie heavy weights, because that's an awesome movie as well.
Wes Bos: Awesome. Any shameless plugs?
Scott Tolinski: I have a course coming out. Well, okay, well, this is January, I had of course come out in December on styled components and design system. So if you are interested in potentially arguing about CSS and JS online, you should fire up my my course I don't have a name for it at this point, because we're recording this ahead of time. But again, it's on CSS and j s style components specifically designed systems organization, all that good stuff about what are the benefits, why you might want to use them and how to use them and how to use them organized and well. So check it out, level up tutorials, comm you can sign up at level up tutorials.com forward slash pro and get 25% off that whole year of level up Pro. Thank you so much. So check it out. Sweet.
Wes Bos: I'm sick pick all of my courses at Wes bos.com forward slash courses. If you want to learn anything about JavaScript kick the year off, right? Check it out. And that's it for today. Anything else that's got nothing. Awesome. Thanks so much for tuning in. Have a fantastic year and we will see you in the next one you face.
Scott Tolinski: Head on over to syntax.fm for a full archive of all of our shows. And don't forget to subscribe in your podcast player. Drop a review if you like this show