Unknown: Monday, Monday Monday open wide dev fans yet ready to stuff your face with JavaScript CSS node module BBQ Tip Get workflow breakdancing soft skill web development hasty as crazy as tasty as web development treats coming in hot here is Sarah CUDA, Bob and Scott Taylor.
Totally at ski.
Oh, welcome
Scott Tolinski: to syntax in this Monday hasty treat. We're gonna be talking all about how Wes Bos became a sticker mogul. Taking over the sticker game, like a hurricane non stop like that. So this episode is gonna be all about what's his process for, it's gonna be a nice little inside look into the sticker biz. Of those of you who don't know, Wes is an absolute monster. When it comes to these stickers, he sold an insane amount of which we're going to get into in very little time. So we'll be talking all about the process that went along there. And how this thing went down to sort of a nice little how to here. So this episode is sponsored by Log Rocket. Now Log Rocket is an amazing service that helps you better find bugs and understand them in your code. This one is really, really cool, because not only does it integrate with some of your other services, of which we talked about Sentry on this podcast, Log Rocket actually works with Sentry, to help you better understand your code. But Log Rocket itself is basically a tool to help you better understand the bugs that are happening in your front end code. What it does is it gives you this really awesome what's called a session replay, which gives you a pixel perfect replay of what the user saw when they were actually manipulating their site and actually using your site, how many times you get an error message. And you're looking at this message in the code and you say how the heck did the user manage to do this, I don't quite know what they were doing. But I understand where the error is in the code and maybe understand who did it and what page they were on or something like that. But you don't have that full visibility, you're not saying what they're saying. So Log Rocket is a perfect way to not only get access to the video of the session, but you also get access to the council log and errors, you get access to the network activity, basically just giving you full visibility to solve some bugs. Now, that sounds extremely appealing to me. Because again, so many times in these situations, you've been given visibility through some of these tools, you know, what the bug is, who the user is, and all that sort of stuff, but you don't have full visibility. And this again, works with those tools, any of the air tools that you might already be using, whether that's something like century that we talk about on syntax here, or something like robar bugsnag, New Relic, JIRA, Zendesk, Salesforce, Trello, GitHub, it integrates with all of these tools that you know, and love to just make your processes that much better. Not only that it works with any of the front end frameworks or front end code in your stack, whether it's react Angular, just plain JavaScript, Redux, Ember, or Vue js, pretty much anything you could possibly be building your site in with JavaScript works with Log Rocket. So Log Rocket, in my mind is just one of these amazing tools that just going to help you figure out bugs, solve them faster, and gain visibility to what your what your users are seeing. And really just take your skills as a bug finder to the next level. So if you want to check out Log Rocket, head on over to Log rocket.com, forward slash syntax, and you will get 14 days free to check out Log Rocket. And I think you're gonna be pretty dang impressed with the service they have gone on over there. So check it out, Log rocket.com forward slash syntax get 14 days for free. So now let's get into our regularly scheduled program where we get to learn about how to become a sticker mogul from Wes Bos.
Wes Bos: All right. So this is something I get questions about all the time. So it's kind of weird to do a whole podcast on how to make stickers. But I thought I would just detail every single step in here so that when people ask me questions, I don't have to spend 20 minutes writing an email to them, I can just point them to this podcast, because it's something that a lot of people want to do. And it's a fun thing to do. So I encourage you to to become your own sticker mogul. So stickers and it's like merchant in web development general are kind of a funny thing, because people go absolutely nuts for a 30 cents sticker. Whereas if you were just walk over to a developer and hand them like a $20. Bill, the bill thank thanks. That's fun. But a sticker is like the best thing ever. So it's like the currency of web developers. And sometimes I feel a little bit silly doing all of this sticker stuff, but people absolutely they love it. They love putting the stickers on their laptop. It's like a sense of identity. You can like see other web developers at a coffee shop and sort of give them a heads up. I myself have talked to just random people at coffee shops. Just Based on the stickers that were on their laptop,
Scott Tolinski: yeah, I'm pretty sure if I saw a West boss sticker at a local coffee shop, I would, I would definitely go introduce myself to that person. So I think it's it is it's like a little tattoo for your computer or something like that.
Wes Bos: Exactly. So for those who don't know, I have run probably for like five or six years I've been like printing stickers and just kind of giving them away. And about three years ago, I got serious about it because I was like, these stickers are so expensive, I want to be able to to give them to everybody or I want to be able to sell them for a couple bucks. So I did a whole bunch of research into how to get stickers affordably how to package them, how to ship them around the world, how to sell them what to do with the envelopes all that stuff. So that's what we're gonna be going through a couple times a year, maybe once or twice a year at boss dot A f I print out a huge batch of stickers and then sell them and then once they're done selling I ship them all over the world night just finished I got back the other day from shipping out the last batch so it's all fresh in my mind I thought I thought I would just go through it all so first we're gonna start with designs first if you want to print stickers, you need some sort of designs. Most of the stickers I've designed to myself either in in Photoshop in for some reason I I've just done them in sketches. I'm not like a great designer but I'm not like comfortable in Illustrator which is the tool that you should be using. But I have designed most of them myself and then just convert them over to ups or PDF or something like that and give them to the printer. This last last batch I had Patrick deployant de PU y DT I don't know how to say his last name but he is an awesome designer and hot sauce brother and he he did a whole bunch of the latest ones which is pretty funny to the what the full snack dev he did the code love one he did the bug hunter one there's a couple of the CSS holographic one. And I did the React one I did the idle hands build nothing one the syntax Lacroix Can I did myself. So there's all kinds of like fun ones that were in the last one. A lot of people ask me what about licensing for these logos because I often will print like a react logo or the .js logo or a few logo, those logos, you have to make sure that they are licensed that you can re reprint, distribute and sell them. So all of the RAC logo, the view logo, the J s logo, those are all licensed on GitHub, you can look it up don't parody logos I've learned in the last. So I printed a popular outdoors outfitter, I kind of made like a parody logo, because I love I love the company. And they did not like that. And I got some some legal letters from them, which I was a huge bummer because I printed 10,000 packs, and every one of those 10,000 packs had one of these offending stickers. Luckily they had, they're really cool about it, and they let me know before I sold them. So it cost me a couple thousand bucks in just labor alone of having someone cut them open, pull the offending sticker out, and I had to buy a sealer. And I had to reseal the entire package. So I thought I was like covered under parody because everybody does it. But think about copyright is that if you don't defend your copyright, then you lose it. So these companies are obligated to do it. So it was stupid. But luckily, I hadn't hadn't sent them out or anything like that. And the company was pretty cool about it. So don't use parody logo of anything like that.
Scott Tolinski: I think that's an important point. Because people sometimes get mad at the companies for these things when companies go like it's especially true and all sorts of little things where companies will go after a small time person making a small time thing with their logo. And you're thinking yeah, there's big mega corporation is infringing on my thing here. But no, it's it. If they do not protect their IP, then they cannot protect it in the future. They are required essentially that if they know that this is going on, they're required to do something about it. Otherwise, it hurts them in the future if they're ever trying to defend their IP from someone else. So it's not the company's fault. Well, it would be cool if they were cool about it. I like yeah, I billion times understand the situation. I think most people need to be a little bit more educated in that department. Yeah,
Wes Bos: everyone was all mad when I said that I had to take them out because everyone was excited to get them but it's their job and I was wrong in that. So lesson learned there. Next one is printing the actual stickers. So once you have your designs done, you need to find a printer so I in the past have used sticker mule for all of my stickers, they are sticker meals awesome. They do most most of the stickers that you get are probably printed at sticker meal, the quality is extremely high. They look really good. The printing and shipping to your house is extremely fast. So for most people I recommend just go ahead and use sticker meal. I know that the owner is like a huge Trump supporter and and people are boycotting them along with like all the other businesses there. So there's that which like the Do you remember that like on Twitter a couple of years ago,
Scott Tolinski: I didn't know that, to be honest.
Wes Bos: Like odor went off on some like massive rant about Trump supporting and making jobs and everyone freaked out and was was banning them. So that was a, that was a huge thing. I'm not gonna cast any judgment either way, because I don't use them anymore. I know their their quality, their product quality is really good. But I took about a year to do a whole bunch of samples on Alibaba. So if you've never used Alibaba before, it's this website where you can source manufacturers of anything. So if you want to get some fishing rods made, or you want to build a scale, or if you want to build your own microphone, or most of the stuff that you buy on Amazon, that is this like weird brand, what people are doing there is like, let's say if you go buy like a cell phone mount for your car, you're gonna notice that there's eight different kinds of cell phone mounts on Amazon, they all look exactly the same, and they just have their own brand printed on them. That's because people are going to Alibaba ordering up 10,000 of them getting their logo screen printed on them, and then selling them on Amazon.
Scott Tolinski: I have a funny story about this.
Unknown: Yeah, go ahead.
Scott Tolinski: So my my parents at one point, they started a Green Tea Company because my dad wasn't sure of his situation with the his job. So like, oh, we're going to start this Green Tea Company, he was going to China a lot. He had a really good idea for these blooming teas that would, they weren't really popular in the United States or anything. So hey, we're going to introduce these blooming teas into the United States essentially, like a T ball that blooms into a flower in a tea pot. It's like a really nice, decorative thing. So we were like, okay, we're gonna make a tea set to go along with this. And my dad had some Starbucks, like, it would come with some mugs and stuff like that. And so he had this Starbucks mug he really liked he went to the source on Alibaba, and was basically like, I really liked this mug. Can we do something similar to this? And they're like, yes, no problem. So then they send us a huge box of test mugs, big box, and all of the mugs came back with the Starbucks logo. We're just like, oh.
Wes Bos: Oh, man. So what did you have to destroy them then? Yeah,
Scott Tolinski: we destroyed that. Yeah.
Wes Bos: Oh, wow.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah,
Wes Bos: that's so Alibaba, there's lots of Chinese manufacturers on there. And what a lot of people don't know is that most of your printing, if you go to store and get like a paper bag, or if you get a box with a product, and all of that stuff is most likely printed in China. And there is a whole city in China that is like a special specific area of China that is just the like packaging industry of China. And there's like thousands and thousands of factories that do everything from bags, and stickers and, and notebooks and anything that is surrounds paper. So I went on there and I looked up like I don't know, seven or eight suppliers that do labels and adhesive things. And I said, Hey, send me send me a whole bunch of samples, give me everything you want. This is the kind of stuff that I'm working on. And usually what would happen is you'd pay like 70 bucks for a FedEx envelope overnighted to you. So I spent 70 bucks a couple times over for a different a whole bunch of different suppliers. And then they would FedEx you just this huge envelope full of stickers that they want. And then what I did is I took each of those stickers, the ones that I liked, I put them on a laptop, I put them on like just like kind of like wearing surfaces that that I would have put them on my phone, things like that. And I just like saw, like what's the quality? What is it like when you peel the sticker off because there's like you can get really cheap stickers that are like paper based. But as soon as they get wet, or as soon as you rip it off, it doesn't rip off nicely, things like that. So I did that. I also got quotes I said, Okay, if I order 6000 stickers from you, how much is it going to be and you get a kind of an idea of what the prices are. From there. I settled on one printer that had been using now which is zigge pack. And it's funny if you go to their Alibaba, all of my stickers are are on display as they're like, this is what we can do for you. Just funny funny, I was just looking at it. There's a whole bunch of like GitHub and Amazon stickers on there now so I've been telling people what printer I use for a couple years now and it seems that a couple other tech folk have picked up on it and also use this to get stickers printed, which is pretty cool. So the pricing of these stickers is much cheaper than something like sticker mule. I think it's like a third or a fourth of the actual cost of doing something like like sticker mule, so quite a bit cheaper. I have noticed that as I last time, I think I ordered 180,000 stickers, the price is significantly cheaper than when you order like 1000 packs versus 10,000 packs. So the more you order the way much cheaper it gets. You do need to make sure that the quality you really got to keep your thumb on the quality. So I've had lots of quality issues in the past where I always print my mat and there's another option to print them shiny. What sticker mule does is they print the mat so I made sure that they were matte and then I one time a whole bunch of them came back shiny and they had to read print them and send them. I've in my last batch, not this batch, but my last batch I had a bunch of the little ones are really hard to cut because they're so small, and the machine that punches down and cuts them was off by a few millimeters. But that meant like some of the stickers were just totally cut wrong. So that's something that I had to deal with. And make sure that this time around, the way that you communicate with these printers is via Skype, so you gotta like make sure you're on Skype late, late at night or early early in the morning. Because I think that a lot of these like Chinese manufacturers, they'll just do it. And if you're not like on them about the quality and making sure that you get everything, everything absolutely right, then they don't care, right, they're just gonna gonna ship it off to you What else is there there's import costs. So you're obviously shipping things from China into I ship them into Canada, which there is no trade agreement with China. So the border will see what the value is of the stickers and then they will charge you I don't know what the how it works. But usually it's a couple hundred, a couple thousand bucks on import charges alone just on these things coming into the country just because that's the way it works. If I were to print them locally, they wouldn't. What else we got here type of stickers. So most stickers that I print are this thing called PVC. Most people refer to them as vinyl stickers, but they are PVC. But the kind of cool thing about going with a printer in China is that they have access to absolutely everything because they live in this city where the entire printing industry of China is from. So the first time around, I asked them to do gold foil stickers. And then they went to like a different printer and got them done and brought them back and they were great except that they're not waterproof, because they were they were like a paper foil. And I saw a lot of people like put them on a water bottle and then they threw it in the wash and then the whole thing sort of came off. So I also noticed that they they do security stickers, which is really cool. You know, like if you buy like a laptop, they put like a little security sticker on if you peel it off or something yeah. Or if you buy like a nice shirt and on the on the label. It'll have like a holographic one. So I said like, Can you just print like a really big holographic sticker for me and like of course we can do anything you want. So I they say you send us three layers. And we will print a holographic sticker with that. So the first time I did a JavaScript sticker the second time I did a CSS sticker and it's really cool because the angle that you you do this holographic thing, you see different things in it depending on on what you have in there. So I thought that was really cool. They also sell like these epoxy stickers, which are kind of like a bubble label. They sell those remember those puffy stickers from when you were a kid? Yeah, yeah. nobody's doing puffy dev stickers, JavaScript puffy stickers, if
Scott Tolinski: you if you don't have your dot tech domain, puffy dev stickers, that tech.
Wes Bos: That would be amazing. They've got all kinds of different things, they can pretty much do anything that you want, they can do huge one that can do tattoos, anything you can think of. Whereas if you go with a normal like sticker mule printer, they have one type of sticker they all they have like circle stickers and clear stickers, they had a couple different kinds. But the sky's the limit when when you go with one of these types of printers, because you can you can pick whatever you want. Once you have the actual stickers printed and you kind of crank down on the quality, I have them bag them as well. They give me a what are called poly bags, they have a whole kinds of different bags, what I did is they just went to the dollar store. And I took pictures of all the different kinds of bags like you can buy crayons for your kids and these like foil bags, but they're not very recyclable. So I was kind of aware of that they have like these like plastic bags as well. So I ended up on the polybag. So it's nice and clear, they print a cardboard header and then fold it, they pay some poor soul to stuffed them into bags and staple the top. The first time I ever did it, there was a miscommunication. And they shipped me the tops and the bags and a bunch of staplers and not the actual packed and I it took hours and hours like I think I only printed 2000 packs that time and it took like 40 hours to pack them all. So I make sure that they pack them themselves into all of these bags just because it's funny that the scale that I'm doing that now is just everything takes so long and you can't just like oh, whatever, I'll pack them myself because the 10,000 packs probably would have taken me like 200 hours or something like that. I think they also have like some sort of machine that will pack them for you as well. Once they're packed into the bags, they get shipped over to me I get they get FedEx over it takes about a week to get here from China depends on the customs and all that stuff as well. And then some poor guy in a FedEx man shows up with like 400 boxes of stickers, and I have to spend an afternoon schlepping them up to my office. Then I go ahead and sell them so I put them up on my website and I sell them all at once just because of the logistics that is shipping. It's not something that I can just simply do like every day dip into it dip out and send a few off. So what I do is I'll just sell them all at once. I'll have a limited amount of stickers. This time I had 7500 packs and they sold out way faster than I had hoped. It's sold out in eight hours which is blows my mind how quickly went Are you My own course platform, so that's free, you can use something Shopify or whatever, I use stripe and PayPal, they take about 50 cents. So that's one thing I didn't really consider is that when you're selling something for such a low value, like $5, PACA, stickers, stripe and PayPal still take their cut, which is 2939 cents plus whatever percent, like 2.9% on top of it. So that's 5060 cents at the end of the day for that one, though, which is why I think like, you go to the, you go to the store, the corner store to buy a pop, and they, they,
Scott Tolinski: they say no credit cards under $5, because or they just get really, really passive aggressively mad at you and roll your eyes when you have done a credit card, just like
Wes Bos: so knowing the other thing you need to be worried about is that selling something so cheap is a magnet for people to test stolen credit cards, because usually when someone has a stolen credit card, they want to test it on something cheap. And then if it works, and they go buy like a TV and a $5 pack of stickers is a really good way to test if a card is good or not. So I haven't had too much of an issue because they don't have this open ended sale. It's just a very pointed sale and I email people and they sell really quickly. But every now and then people still do buy it with a stolen credit card. In that case, you lose your five bucks, you lose your $15 for the dispute fee, as well as sometimes they still I don't know why they gave me their address, I shipped a guy a bag of garbage once when he used the stolen credit card to do
Scott Tolinski: so services, they'll let you send like poop in a box.
Wes Bos: So yeah, or like a glitter send glitter to your enemies in glitter.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah.
Wes Bos: Then once they're all sold, it's time to to pack them and put them into envelopes. So the first time I ever did this, I thought oh, just I'll just run some envelopes through my own. I have like a pretty nice laser printer. And it has an envelope feed so you can put them in. But I have I figured out that you can only put 10 envelopes in at a time and like one every 20 it would jam. And then you'd have to reprint that specific one. And it was just a nightmare. So what I figured out is I wrote a script, it's actually a jade file in my own course platform that takes everyone's address, and it just automatically generates all of the envelopes for the people that need to ship them to it figures out how much postage needs to be put on in the top right hand corner, puts my return address in the top left hand corner, and then I get this PDF of 5500 envelopes doesn't wasn't what it was last time. And then I send that to a printer. And then the printer takes this time it was a couple days last time it was a couple hours a whole week, it takes them a whole week to print them on to actual number 10 envelopes. And that's about 10 to 20 cents per envelope depending on how many are actually ordering. So that's a 10 20% cut into the $5 that it is because I sell them $5 with free shipping anywhere in the world. A lot of people ask me like, why don't you just use like a dynamo printer where you can like print the labels. And the answer to that is that that would take way too long, because you have to peel them and stick them onto every single envelope. So I rather just print it directly onto the envelope that we'd have there. And also that's a huge added cost as well those those labels, those Dynamo labels are sometimes like 20 cents, 30 cents an actual envelope and and when you have $5 to ship a pack of stickers around the world, I like to do them cheap, right like there's a lot of people selling stickers online, you get like two or three for eight or 10 bucks. But I love the idea that I can sell 18 stickers for five bucks shipped anywhere in the world. Because it's it's not something you have to like sweat about, everyone can have a $5 pack of stickers. Next up is stamping. So once they're in the envelopes, I have my assistant she takes the number of packs on the envelope itself, I print the number of packs that are needs to go in that envelope, I sell them in packs of one three or six, pack them into the envelope, then you take a cloth, run it against or liquid, I don't think you can look too many of them though. So we stick them in envelopes, you seal it up, and you flip it over. And then it's time to actually stamp the envelope once they've all been packed into the envelopes that's takes between stamping and unpacking the envelopes. I think last time it took us about 50 hours, which is a huge amount of time when it comes to stamping, you need to figure out how heavy is the thing. So I have like a scale here. And you also need to figure out the weight of it. So if you stack the stickers on top of each other, the it can get really thick. And once you pass the thickness of it, then you go into a different mail class. So I shipped them via US Postal Service mostly. And I've been on their website because you have to make sure you're well within the weight as well as within the thickness. So I have like these digital calipers that measures the thickness of the envelope tank. It's so involved in aeration, all of the stuff that I've figured out. So based on the thickness and the weight, we know how many stamps to put on the envelope every time we've done it so far, we've just manually stamped them. So we go to the post office and we buy or you go online, you buy 5000 this time was almost $5,000 worth of stamps alone, which I've been trying to automate. So here I'll talk about all the different options. Everyone says use stamps calm, you idiot. So I signed up for stamps.com and pass it
Scott Tolinski: on to this podcast and then you might use how they
Wes Bos: share it because it's garbage service. So the way that it works is that you, you find this there sheets of stamps, which is 30. And then you have to upload all of your addresses to their like crappy desktop software, and then it will like print out 30 at a time. So that's the same, it's extra work to upload them all. It's extra cost to buy their custom stamps, comm sheets, and then you're still peeling them off this like sheet and sticking them on yourself. Or as with the stamps, you can get into a really good rhythm where you just peel stick, peel stick, peel stick, and you can do them like real real quick. So there's that My dream is to use some sort of API to ping the API with the thickness, the weight and the address, and the API will come back to me with like a barcode that I will include in my printing, and a couple options for that. There's like endicia.com, which had a phone call with them in Disha. That's, I think that's right. I
Scott Tolinski: don't use that I use the service for sending t shirts. That's what I use.
Wes Bos: Okay, good. So I like basically got on the phone with them. And I said, Okay, I want to do it, but not for shipping. I want to do it for stamps. And they're like, that's what stamps.com was for, but I'm like, but that sucks. But
Scott Tolinski: stamps.com please sponsor this podcast, by the way, please, please don't
Wes Bos: it sucks. Yes. So my other my other way was, I got a message from Sarah cope or co pay, who said she did all the merge for CSS tricks, and code pen and all of Chris coiour stuff. And she says we use shipstation. So I looked into shipstation. And it actually seems to be exactly what I want. And shipstation has an API that you can ping, and you can create an order. And then apparently, you can get back an actual label, which I'm assuming I can save that label and then put it into my printing. So that's what I'm going to try next. Because it's cheaper. If you have like a corporate account with these post offices, you can you can just print the exact amount of postage that you you need. Because sometimes you go over on the postage, because it's only $1 15 for an international stamp. And if you need like $1 80 you just have to go over it because you can buy like one there 10 cent stamps, then that's it's too much work. That's what my next little thing is is trying to figure out how do I integrate the shipstation API? And also like I'm Canadian as well, I drive across the border to Buffalo to ship all of these because Canadian postage is is so expensive, and they're on strike right now, which
Scott Tolinski: is the border. When you do this in you have like boxes full of stickers in your car. Yeah. Really scrutinized anytime we used to go to Windsor to drink. Because when you were like 19, you could drink in Canada, right? Yeah, if you went to Windsor, and it was only like, you know, an hour long drive or something. And so we would, we would just pop over the bridge. And they would be like, so why are you coming to Windsor? And we'd be like, visiting family? And they'd be like, okay, you kids. Okay, sure. And they would, they would always go through the car to make sure that you we weren't like bringing in a bunch of bunch of stuff.
Wes Bos: Yeah, no, it's so it's totally allowed. I made sure of that before I, I did it. There's many companies in Canada that do this exact thing. There's a lot of eBay sellers that will just print us postage, and then they'll throw it on this truck. And the truck will drive across the border and dump all the mail because it's such a common thing to do. So it's totally allowed. The only thing is that some entries make you go through the commercial line because you are business so you have to go with the trucks in the commercial line and pay like there's a fee to use the bridge but that has nothing to do that's just the bridge that has nothing to do with like being able to cross into into it. So every time I cross we say hey, like what are you doing? I'm like I'm shipping a whole bunch of letters they see it that you rolled on your Windows the entire car is full boxes. And he said he said oh yeah, people do this all the time. It's totally allowed just sometimes you'll be asked to go through the commercial line instead of the just the regular line so surprising to me that that it was allowed as well. But I made sure that it was before I I tried it. Yeah, what else you need to make sure that the thickness and weight does not get at a certain point I used to sell 10 packs, and I accidentally I didn't know that when you ship a 10 pack. It's big enough to be considered a parcel there's letter there's flat and there's parcel and you can send it via parcel no problem. You pay the postage, it's okay when bundling. What is what is that?
Scott Tolinski: Talking about the parcel? Oh, parcel
Wes Bos: contract and web dev. I had to fill out a whole bunch of customs forms for the 10 packs. So now I only have six packs, which is the very depending on how many stickers I print. The six pack this time was the maximum I could put in an envelope without be declared a parcel sitting having to fill out customs forms. mailing I drove to Buffalo ship on there I met all the Canadian ones out of Canada just because it's cheaper to do that still. And then finally you wait a couple days they start showing up at everyone's home because I mail them all around the world. This time I had 92 countries that ordered them, especially India and Colombia they take for forever to show up because the mail system is just like not good in those countries, I guess. So sometimes they don't show up at all. Sometimes they take up to two months to show up.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, I shipped a Shi t shirt I wanted that took two months. And then arrived back at my door in the package, it looked like it had been around the world. So yeah,
Wes Bos: I still get them back like 11 months later, I still get them returned. Or sometimes I see people, Hey, I got them 11 months later, that's in the minority, most people get them within a couple days. But sometimes they do. That's just how it is because of the way I send them, I send them very cheaply via stamps. If I were to do them as parcels and have a tracking number, it would be much more expensive to actually do that. So it's not really something I'm interested in getting into. I've thought about closing sales to countries like India, and Colombia, and even Mexico takes a long time. But where I'm at right now is they just tell people, hey, this might take forever to get to you, I'll give you your money back if they never shows up. But they'll probably show up at some point. And that's kind of what I've been, I've been sticking with lots of them get returned, maybe like 1%. But 1% of 5000 is yes, 50 of them come back. So now you have this added burden. So I have a peel box, which I pay a couple hundred bucks a month for those come up on my peel box. And then I have to pay my assistant to contact these people and tell them hey, it came back. And most cases people goof up their email address, or they go goof up their address or they have an auto fill that was incorrect. So I will have these hilarious checkboxes when you buy the stickers that say, I did not put in the wrong address, I will not email you, when I realized put in the wrong address. I actually read the two above boxes, because people were just buying them and then emailing me being like, Oh, no, I screwed it up. here's here's the update. And I should probably code something in my back end that allows people to update their address. But what happens is that they sell. And by the time that I'm done selling them, within a couple hours, I have the envelopes off to the printer to be printed. And at that point, it's too late. So if that's the case, I just refund the person's money and I eat the eat the shipping costs and the stickers cost. So you have to eat the cost a lot with people goofing it up. But even though it's their problem, you kind of have to be cool about it. I think that's about it. The other thing is some of them have to be mailed out of Canada, specifically Iran, you cannot send mail from Iran to their from us to Iran, because there's some sort of block on and there's like there's a whole bunch of countries that have like a what's it called like embargo or something like that where you cannot send mail, so you have to make sure that the ones that are addressed to those countries are sent out of Canada instead. So it's a huge thing of all of this stuff. But that is how I do stickers, all of the stuff I've talked about, I've learned over the last three years. And at this point, it's a very efficient operation. I probably in the last package of stickers between doing the designs talking to the printer and driving to Buffalo, I probably only put about 10 hours of my own time into it. And the rest of it is just a process that I've built up over the time, which is kind of fun. Future I'm wanting to do like more stuff, just because it's fun to every now and then like you're sick of coding, you want to do something else. But also like it's fun to like, try to solve the problem of all of this logistics with code. Like that's what developers are right? So I want to figure out how to do a little bit more I've been thinking about like, we want to do syntax t shirts at some point. Yeah, a couple of times. I have a friend that has the actual clothing company, and he does cut and sew in Peru. So I'm talking to him about doing some like kind of cool stuff, because everyone has 1000 like gildan t shirts with the logo screen printed on it. But what I really want is like cool, nice hoodies and nice t shirts and like proper fitting shirts that are like modern and stuff like that right stuff
Unknown: that you want to wear that you
Wes Bos: would want to wear. Yeah, cuz there's a there's a lot of web developer stuff out there that just says like, drink coffee all day. And it's just like blasted. And like that's not something I would ever were. And I know that most of web developers, I don't know, some people like cheesy t shirts, but I've never been a fan of, of cheesy t shirts. So I want to do something that's that's really nice. I'm talking to him like that. Right now. Yeah, we
Scott Tolinski: got a style on him.
Wes Bos: Yeah, I just ordered some pencils. Because I was like on this website, and for like 500 pencils. It's like $100 or $150. I forget what I put on it. It's just like, never stop learning or something like that. Or never stop making things. That's what it says. I'm gonna have some pencils coming my way. I just working on some some like Christmas gifts for some of my web developer friends that I'm going to give them,
Scott Tolinski: man. It's sick. It's a great idea.
Wes Bos: Yeah, I like it. So that's kind of something that I'm interested in. Hopefully that clears up any questions you have about how all the stickers work. Obviously, it is a huge logistical hurdle. I didn't know it going in. But I think about like, what do people that actually have ecommerce companies do? They must have like amazing processes for handling all of the stuff because I'm just a guy with one pack of sticker, one single skew trying to mail them around the world whereas people have returns in different amounts and things that are in stock and things that need to be shipped later. And the logistics that goes into actually getting a physical product to someone is is amazing. It takes a lot of work.
Scott Tolinski: It takes so much work that I think we just broke our record for the longest tasty treat.
Wes Bos: It's not very hasty. Alright, well that's it today. Hopefully you enjoyed it. Again, all of the links To my printer and everything will be at bas dot A AF that is the link so you can you can get in touch with the the printer and all that sick, sick bass please
Scott Tolinski: head on over to syntax.fm for a full archive of all of our shows. And don't forget to subscribe in your podcast player or drop a review if you like this show.