Announcer: Monday, Monday, Monday, open wide dev fans yet ready to stuff your face with JavaScript CSS node modules, barbecue tip workflow breakdancing, soft skill web development hasty as crazy as tasty as web development treats coming in hot here is Sarah CUDA, Bob and Scott Tolinksi ski.
Wes Bos: Oh, welcome to syntax. This is the podcast with the tastiest web development treats. And today is a hasty treat, which is a short version, we usually try to keep it I don't know, between 15 and 22 minutes long. 22.5 minutes is kind of our ceiling on that thing. So we better get going. Today's hasee tree is sponsored by century century is one of the best air tracking services out there. I use century myself I have for a long time. And I actually have teamed up with Sentry previously in my learned Redux course, if you remember if you've ever taken that, and they're back to sponsor a little bit more, so what Sentry does is that it it catches errors on any of your platform. So whether you're running a Python or PHP server or whatever, I specifically use Sentry both on the back end in my node API, and that catches any errors that happen on my server. And then I also run it on the client side, which is extremely helpful to know when errors are happening in my users browsers and and then when an error actually happens, I'm able to aggregate all of those things together, take a look at Oh, okay, it seems like I specifically had a problem once where a whole bunch of users were complaining about not being able to download something on on a download page. And we actually narrowed it down to only users on an iPad. That was two versions old because we're using an outdated version of some library. And it was really easy to figure it out. Because there was, I don't know, 300 people that in the last month have had the same issue. And they were all like 98% of them were on the specific version of an iPad iOS system on it. So it gives you all kinds of like really good insight and allows you just to dig in really quickly and figure out what is the actual error. Some other stuff that they do is they integrate with GitHub, Bitbucket, get lab, all of that stuff, tight integration with Slack, JIRA, pager duty. So if all of a sudden, you're getting all kinds of errors happening, then you can ping off your pager duty and someone can jump in and fix it. Probably my favorite part about Sentry is that it's totally open source, meaning that it's obviously a service that you go and pay for. And you can just drop it into your application in I think it's like three minutes it takes to get up and running in your own application. But if you really want it to host your own, or if you're afraid of a service going away after a certain amount of time and all of your your your data being in there, you'll know that this thing is 100% open source, so you could just spin up your own version of it and, and run your own service for it. So check it out@sentry.io they obviously have a free tier. But what they're going to be doing is if you use the code, tasty treat, which is my favorite promo code ever, they'll give you a two month credit, which is awesome. So if you have like a bit of a bigger web app, the free plan, you can burn through the stuff pretty quickly. So you can get like two full months of a paid plan. And you can really give it a run to see it. That's how I did it my own app. And then after two months, I was like, Oh, this is this is great. It's extremely helpful well worth the price that you pay for it. And also, this is really cool of them as well. It's just such a cool company. They're open source. But if you are already a century user, you can still use the code tasty treat to get two free months, which is awesome. Because I hate was like, oh, but I already have an account. Thanks for thinking of your existing users. Right? Yeah, so check it out@sentry.io forward slash sign up and use the code tasty treat when you are signing on up. Thanks so much to Sentry for sponsoring. Cool. Alright, so let's talk about setting goals. Sticking to goals. Why do you would you set goals, we've touched a little bit upon this back on our like New Year's episode maybe almost a year ago. But now we're gonna kind of get into it a bit more. So you want to kick it off there, Scott? Yeah, let's
Scott Tolinski: get talking about goals. I'm a big goal setter, I set a lot of goals, I set goals for everything. And a lot of times, the cool thing about setting goals is that you don't have to hit them all. And you can aim wherever you want to aim. So if I set goals in life to do X, Y, and Z for everything and different aspects of my life, you know, even if I only hit 50% of those goals in life, or over the cross the next year or something like that, it's still probably more than I would have done then if I didn't set those goals anyway. So really setting goals is just such a powerful way to grow yourself to get things done to move forward to advance yourself and to really just take control of understanding where you're at. So one of the things that we like to talk about here, we I always talk about setting SMART goals. And now you have this smart capitalize. Now I understand the concept. Is this actually an acronym here?
Wes Bos: Yes, it's business school West coming out of the woodwork here. A smart goals stands for specific, measurable, attainable, relevant and time based. So let's give a quick example of that if you're trying to learn to code, and you're specifically focused on CSS right now, a lot of times people say, Okay, my, my goal is to get better at CSS. And that's not a goal. That's a hope. That's a wish, right? And there's no there's no meat on how you're going to attain that or anything like that. So specific, let's go through Smart Passive, so smartest, it's a specific goal goal, meaning that I don't want to get better at CSS, your goal should be, I want to build six things that are based on CSS animation in the next four, four months. Right? So that's a specific, it's measurable. And can you measure if your goal was successful or not? Did you build six things? Yes. Then you pass it? Did you build five things? You almost got there. But at least you can measure it right? It's it's not really good. If you look back after a year, and like, Am I better at CSS? Or like, yeah, Yes, I think so. Kind of there's, there's nothing you can really, you can really prove for that attainable? Is this something that you can actually, like, realistically get done, right? Sometimes you see people come out and say, I'm starting up a YouTube channel, I'm gonna do three a day, right? And then they peter out after a week, right? Because it's just not attainable, right? You have to be you have to be realistic with yourself and in how you're setting your goals relevant. This is about getting real with yourself, whether it's something that you are serious about spending time on in and making it a priority in your life, and then the t is time bound? How long do you have to get the school, right, I'm going to get better at CSS, when what are you going to do about it, right? If you say, I want to build six code pins in the next four months. And that's a really good goal to have, because you know exactly what you're going to be or what you the type of thing you want to build, and how many you're going to make and when that goal actually is going to come due. So you can sort of pace yourself and work backwards from there. So huge fan of smart goals. It's kind of a business II thing. If you do any googling, you're probably going to find lots of like MBA websites that may make you cringe, but I've been a big fan of it in my life.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, I pretty much only deal in this kind of goal. And I do I set this goes for everything in my life. Right? And they always have to be attainable, they have to be measurable. They have to be everything that you just mentioned there. So I guess, what kind of stuff do you set goals for in particular? And maybe we can dive into some of these and talk a little bit maybe what what our goals are for these kind of things? Is that does that a set? Yeah, we're for you.
Wes Bos: Cool. So I generally have just goals around creating content. So how much content I would like to get out the type of content that I would like to create. And generally that is these, those are very high level goals, because they these courses take so long. So generally, it's about a year ago that I have, and I say this year, I would love to put out two new courses or three new courses, and then I'd like to re record one of them. And I'd also like to matter, I'll make a whole bunch of tweets, maybe 20 Hot Tips on Twitter, and I'd like to put out six YouTube videos, right? So I take a look at this is the type of content that I make. And these are, these are the kind of the amount of content that I think I would like to, to make. And then I also have goals specifically around exercise. And it's more about for me, it's more about just how often I will go and for how long I will go because that just makes sure that it gets me out to the gym, or it gets me out on a run or going out for a walk or things like that. And that's just so that I have sort of a compass that will point me in the direction that I need to go. And and almost like a rule so when I when I should be going and how often I should be going.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, those are those are things that I am always setting goals for to in fact, when I was doing all the YouTube 100% I had very specific like content number goals, like I need to hit 320 some videos a year or something like that. And I would keep track of to see what what kind of progress and pace I was on. And again, these are attainable. These are things I can do. They're measurable, I know what I'm doing for exercise, I do the same thing. I have goals and things I would like to accomplish. And then once I hit those goals, you know what I reworked my goals. So for instance, one of my big goals was well, I had two big goals and I have a I have like a moleskin of like life goals, which are these big, big goals of stuff I would like to do at some point in my life, right? And then I had much more smaller goals and so some of these things in my life goals was like you know what in life I would like to be able to at least at some point deadlift 300 pounds. I would like to be able to benchpress 250 pounds. You know, these are like things that but some point I would like to be able to do. But then and I'm a smaller level, I would say I'd like to be able to add five pounds to my, you know, workout for this or that every single week. And here's what I have to do to attain that. And you know what I hit both of those I did a 250 benchpress. I did 300 deadlift, and it was like, huge for me. And you know what, I haven't even attempted those numbers since because after I hit those goals, my goals have changed. Now my goals are more about you know, working better to to make myself a more, I don't know, less breakable while I'm breakdancing, which is definitely a thing I get hurt so much, I'm trying to limit the amount I get hurt by really just like sort of padding, those those those things, but I'm also making goals constantly for things like business, right? So we both run our own business levelup tutorials, is my full time business. That's what I do full time I develop I write these, these, the tutorials, I do all the production. And now I'm starting to work with more people and hire on developers and contractors and this and that. But I have very real growth metrics, I use something called profit well as a service to track my subscription metrics and my growth percentages and stuff like that. And I'm hardcore about it, I'm looking at it, I'm always thinking about how I can obtain my goals, how I can reach them, and what these goals are month over month over month. And it's pretty good. It's one of those things that it drives you, right? If I were to make weak goals, and untrackable goals, you're never going to hit them and you're never going to get there. So for my business in particular, it's like I set lofty goals, and I'm I'm heading out to hit them. You know, that's, that's why I'm doing it. So
Wes Bos: totally, I actually, as you say that I just wrote down a whole bunch of mine, as well as, like business goals are a huge one. And I specifically don't have like monetary goals in the business. Because I feel like if I were to say, Okay, I want to, I want to be making X amount of dollars per day. I don't think that like I would know, like what to do to sit down and actually make that happen. But I do know that if I have goals in terms of content and quality, and how many courses I want to put out and frequency and stuff like that, and even doing this podcast, I do know that that will make the the money actually start start rolling in. So I tend to make my my goals more like I one of them that I successfully reached was I wanted 200,000 people on my newsletter. And and I hit that a couple months ago. And I was I was really happy at that. And that's funny because now I don't spend a whole lot of time focusing on the whole newsletter marketing part of my business because I've hit that goal. And I'm happy with the process that I have in place. And it's sort of like lives on itself. And I can move over to again, like last year, I said, I want to have I think 50 affiliates under my belt. So I want 50 people from around the world that are recommending like courses via whatever means that they have and, and I hit that goal that we have there or platform improvement. So every three or six months, I'll go through my own course platform, and I'll look through all of my GitHub issues, because every time I have an idea of something might want to fix or add to it. And I'll say, in the next six months or next three months, these five major things need to be implemented into into the platform. And I like what you said about like you hit those goals, and that's exactly because you're steering towards that. And then as soon as you get there, then you you look up. Okay, okay. Okay, what next? And I think that's really important in moving forward, both in your personal development as well as in a business.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, yeah. And it's, so again, I have my I have a ton of goals, overall. But one of the things that I've really, really helped me like, realize these goals is this, I'll see if I can link it. There, there was a site that I don't know if it's still being worked on, but was called forever jobless. And they had this worksheet that you could get just by subscribing to their mailing lists. And this worksheet, my wife and I, Courtney, we both did this worksheet. Oh, man, it looks like it might be out I'm gonna see if there's any way you can access that still. But this these worksheets that came out there were like 12 pages and you do things and we would we would redo them every single year, not like as a resolution kind of thing. But we would do them every single year. And these are like big life goals. And so they'll be like, what is the one thing you want to accomplish this year, and then I'll put like 25 smaller sub tasks for that. But either way it was this like huge brainstorming exercise that you could just like, really dive into some of these big, big goals that are these things that you want to accomplish and to refocus yourself every single time you do these worksheets is just such a good good thing to have in your brain. So I'll see if I can find that it's forever jobless. It's a it's the goal. That worksheet. So it's definitely like financially based, but it's definitely a good goals worksheet in general. And we set a ton of goals around things like budgeting, right? Like, budgeting was really big for us when I didn't have a job because I was in between things and level up was still just starting. And, you know, we had a mortgage, we had student loan payments, we had all this stuff, and we got really super into budgeting because we had to, and we were really trying to hit these goals, right, we're gonna spend this much this month on this, and this and this, and this, and we would have to reevaluate every single month what those goals look like, but yeah, we, we, you need these goals, you need these things that are attainable, and measurable, you need to have them, you need to know where you're going.
Wes Bos: Totally. And on the flip side of that, I think it's also and you can tell me, if you have these, it's, it's really nice to have these like kinda like far off goals of where you want to be in life. And whether that's like a house that you want to live in, or some people that you want to help or the amount of work that you'd like to do every single day, everyone has different like, sort of like, oh, man, if I could do anything in life, or if I could have, or if I could live anywhere in life, it would be or if I could visit this as a vacation anywhere in life. And I find it really helpful, and me and my wife both do this is just to actually talk about those goals as if they were they were to happen one day, and it seems kind of hokey, to talk about that. Because sometimes you see people with like, mood boards with a Ferrari on them and stuff like that. And that makes me cringe just as much as it probably makes you all cringe. But I do find it is helpful, if it's something that is very much personal to you, and whoever it is that you're sharing these goals with, I think it's well worth sort of visualizing them actually happening, because I think that helps see them to flourish. And
Scott Tolinski: I think it's a huge thing. visualizing is just, it's one of the most important aspects of this. And it's funny, because I would consider myself an optimist. And so it's really easy for me to be like, yeah, this is happening, even though there's like really no indication that is actually happening. But I think that, that optimism and that that like look at this, like I understand that this is not really happening. But I understand that I'm capable of making this happen. So I'm capable of producing this, this work in this type of work. I'm capable of doing these things. And I have to execute to make it happen. If I don't execute, none of this is going to happen. So you need to be able to visualize and say like, yes, this is happening, I can see it, this is what it's going to look like this is what's going to be like, that pushes me more than absolutely anything else. Now, what's funny about this is that it stresses corny out. Like when I want I'll refer to like, like houses that I wanted to get or like it will be walking and it'll be like, oh, that'd be like a nice house. Obviously, it's way out of our budget way out of our price range. Right? Like she she's warmed up to it now because I think she she sort of gets where, where it's coming from. But for a while, I think it was just stressing her out. She was just like, well, we were never gonna get there. And I'm just like, well, it's it's not that that's like the wrong attitude. But like, if you want it to happen, you have to have it sitting in front of you at all times. And it's funny because now she's she's all about that we're going on walks and we do a daily walk around our little neighborhood. And we're talking about stuff in anytime there's like a house right now that's being built like two blocks up from us. And it's probably like double the price of our house. And she's just like, so like, what would it take for us to be able to move into this house, I'm like, well, you need to take that out of your mind. Because that house is going on market in like a week. Maybe if this is like you know, 10 years down the road, maybe we can live in that house in 10 years, right, but still being able to visualize that. So she's definitely come around in that. And we get to talk about these, these goals as if they're actual potential realities, because that's the only way they're the realities.
Wes Bos: I'll give you another example of that. I think it's really important that you said like, you actually have to like put steps in place to actually make it happen. Because for the longest time, me and my wife, watch, we watch HGTV all the time. And we always watch the like income property one where Yeah, someone buys a house and rents it out and somebody else pays their mortgage. And then 25 years later, you have a free house, right? And we always talk about like, oh, that'd be awesome to get an income property. And we just talked about and one day I was like, let's effin do it. Like let's actually do it like so let's stop talking about it. Stop watching the show. And and dreaming about it actually happening. Like, let's run the numbers. Here's a spreadsheet, how, what are our steps in three or four years, we actually want to go ahead and buy one. And actually that happened, I think it was after we had that talk, probably about four years later, we went out and bought a little income property. And it was really cool to see that like, don't just dream about it and stuff like that, like go we went to open houses all the time, just like we had no intention of buying it. But then I would go to the open house, I would run the numbers about what it would cost I would figure out how much there would be for a rental property and things like that and just by being in it and Figuring out the the actual nuts and bolts to making something happen made it so much more real to us.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, yeah, I know. And so Courtney has her her doctor, right? She has her PhD. And we had a mountain of student loans from that, right? And I told her that we're gonna get them paid off by this date, right? And she was like, there's no way that's going to happen, because we have that, that that would require this, this and this. And I was thinking, Okay, well, what we need to do is we need to determine, you know, what a monthly contribution, we need to look like to get them paid off by that date, right, you need to then figure out how you can attain that amount of money to make that monthly contribution. And then you just need to go out and do it. But if you were to just say, hey, I want to pay these off this year, or something like that, and there's no, there's no steps, you've not created any steps there. So you need to create those smaller steps and need to figure out how to attain those steps. And then you need to go off and do it. And I'd say today, we're actually we're, we're working at the her loans. I mean, they're almost gone. So I'm, I'm thrilled that I think we're gonna hit that goal. So it's one of those things amazing, it's just, you have to set these mini steps, and you got to make it happen. I really, there's there's one thing in life that I've always really wanted to do. And if you have YouTube, there's this move called the air flare, which is a B boy move. It's really superduper hard. And I went through, and I determined every single micro movement to getting this move, like every single micro movement, it is extremely difficult. And I practice all of the I broke down all the things I built like a helper, which was like an attire inner inner tube from a tire and hung it from the ceiling so that I could hang upside down and try this thing over and over again, I worked my butt off for this goal. And I did it all correctly. And guess what, I never accomplished that goal because things get in the way, right? I yeah, I mentioned my wrists, I got a concussion or this or that. I never hit that goal. But I still hit all of the steps that I needed to get there. And I still did the work and I still put time into it. And I don't feel bad that I didn't get to do it. Because I made as solid of an effort as I could have to do that thing.
Wes Bos: Yeah, totally. I think that's that's really important cuz life, life happens. Like specifically, some of my fitness goals have been derailed for the last couple months. And that's because my kids don't go to sleep. And I've been like, up all night exhausted. You know, like, you're a parent as well. And it's it's frustrating, but it's it's okay to have those setbacks because like Mike, I still I'm still on the right course, I'm still pointed in the right direction. And I know that I will be able to get back on these goals and whatever. And it's important to me that I know that this is this is the direction that I'm heading. And any anything where you you come short of those goals, you know that it's okay, as long as you're pointed in the same direction.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, absolutely. So when do you personally go about setting your goals because I like to do goals frequently. Again, we mentioned I do that yearly that yearly worksheet, but when do you personally like to set goals, I have a little thing here I like to do is a little trick or a little a little thing I like to do. But uh,
Wes Bos: yeah, most most stuff for me is, is on the shorter term. Because anything bigger than, I don't know, a year, even I, most of my goals are like, weekly, this is what I'd like to get done at the end of this week, like, right this week, my recording my butt off, and I have, I want to record, I think like 22 videos this week, I have it all laid out. And that's my goal for today. And and then I work backwards, I need to do this many per day. And that's kind of what I'm working at. But then I also have like three months goals things for courses that I want to work on courses that I want to put out in the next three months course platform improvements, I don't want to do delegation is another big one for me, where I wanted to this is about a year ago, but I wanted to delegate all of my support to somebody else. And now I'm working on delegating a lot of the the feature development of my platform to somebody else and and then obviously, I do have yearly goals as well. Those are very high level. And they're more like, like I talked about earlier how many courses I want to put out and kind of what's things that I really want to focus in on my time on for for that week. Or that sorry that year.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah. So I do that I do. I do sort of the yearly thing we do these daily worksheets I do definitely weekly goals I go through is usually Sunday night, I take my to do list and then I see what I didn't get done from the previous week. I reassign them to different dates and times. I like really nailed down the things that I'm going to try to accomplish and actually put days and times and things to them not like hardcore scheduled, like, I'm going to do this between nine to 930 on Friday, but more like here, I'm gonna do this on Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday, Friday or whatever and have that list ready for me to go for the week. And then I sit down at the beginning of each day and sort of assess that list and see if that's like accurate to how things are I get through it right. But I also do this thing I like to call monthly resolutions. And I approach resolutions like a new year's resolution every single month. And I sort of evaluate things and I look back are the things that were important to me last month still important to me this month? And if so, what kind of progress Have I made on them? And this is like less concrete and more like more like realigning yourself, because you often feel that way, with yearly resolutions, right? You say, Okay, I need to realign myself for this year. But I like to really approach that in a month to month basis is like, this is what's working, this is what's not working, let's change course here. Or maybe my goal of recording a whole albums worth of songs isn't really happening. And I'm not feeling that right now. I feel more like let's do some JavaScript stuff instead, right? So maybe I'm gonna focus more that way. So these monthly resolutions are hugely important to me. And then also at that point, I occasionally will break down smaller goals and within those, and those are actually my smart goals within those monthly resolutions. So if my resolution is for this month is to get, you know, 100 new subscribers on level of Pro, then my monthly goal will be to record this series, do this kind of advertising, do this kind of outreach, do this kind of free content, or whatever, as steps to obtain that goal. Right. So yeah, I love these little monthly resolutions. It's something I've been doing for a little while now. And
Wes Bos: that's really cool. I like that actually, I kind of maybe will adapt that myself. Do you do it on the first of the month, every month? Or? I how do you do that I
Scott Tolinski: sort of do it right at the end of each month. Okay, so just towards the end, whenever I, I prefer to do a lot of this stuff on it's funny, I prefer to do a lot of this stuff on like, Sunday, Sunday evening, after the Landon has gone to bed, and I can just Yeah, really have some time to myself, that's not, you know, scheduled in any sort of way. And just yeah, sure, and take some time to just marinate on it a little bit.
Wes Bos: My wife and I actually have a, we've got one more week of vacation coming up the end of August, and we are bringing her like we're going to the cottage with her mom and her sister. And part of the deal is that they're going to take care of the kids like noon or something like that. So what we're doing is me and my wife are doing professional development from 6am to noon every single day. And we're really looking forward to that, because it's gonna be time that's not for like working on the business or whatever. But it's going to be time just for thinking like setting goals, professional development, my wife has a whole bunch of audio books she's going to do, I haven't yet figured out what I'm going to do yet. But it's just that set aside time. That's, that's for this kind of this kind of thing.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, it's important to set aside the time make it happen and, and just let it let it permeate into you and all that sort of good stuff. So I guess last thing we want to talk about is accountability. And what are some ways that you can hold yourself accountable? I mean, I think even just the process of creating these smart, obtainable goals, attainable goals, whatever these things that are in lists, the things that you can look at, and the things you can track your progress on. I think right there is like such the biggest barrier for accountability in general. Because if you have this ethereal goal that just sort of like out there, right? And you Well, I didn't hit it. Okay. That's like a sure sign that you didn't have the proper steps set up to hit it. So I think keeping yourself accountable is partly and just creating excellent smart trackable goals.
Wes Bos: Yeah, exactly. Just being able to measure them, like we've said, right, it's very easy to tell if you have a goal or not. Another way is I like to just tell people about goals that I'm working on. And it's kind of a benefit, like, I can talk about them on this podcast and lots of people will will follow up like a couple about a month or two ago, I mentioned that I would love to learn a little bit more about solar and every now and then someone Hey, how's the solar going like anything like this or I'm doing it myself? The I always talk about what course I'm working on and it's coming up and that gets people excited about it. And that also kind of holds me to it because people are constantly asking about it. Right now my advanced react ones a little bit overdue because of a whole bunch of reasons but people they really hold you to it and I'm working my butt off right now because people really really want this thing so it's it's nice to have other people tend to hold you accountable to these things otherwise they're they're just gone wishy washy. Yeah,
Scott Tolinski: absolutely. Another thing I really like for accountability is this saying that we always say in the B boy world is like the don't talk about it, be about it. Like you don't want to talk and say that you're the best at what you do. You want to show it right in like if you're an A B boy battle, and you're in a competition, right? You talking in letting the other people know that you're the best is not going to win you that competition. So there's no point in talking about it. You just have to shut up and get your work done and make it happen. Right. And then you can talk about it afterwards. You can you know, if you you're the greatest after you won the greatest thing in the world, you can say that I'm the greatest but like until it happens, don't talk about it. And even I think that goes for a lot of things, right? Like, so many people, they just express their their plans, and they talk about their plans. And as if it's already happened, I'm, I'm the CEO, I'm the boss or whatever on Instagram and stuff like that. And like the people who are actually doing that stuff aren't out there talking about it and are out there saying that I'm the boss and CEO, they're getting it done, right? Unless, yes, they're like selling a book on the subject. And then maybe that's just part of their branding. But like, for the most part, the people who are working out there and doing the real work aren't out there bragging about it, you know,
Wes Bos: totally agree. So I think we're over our 22 and a half minutes. Oh, no, we're
Scott Tolinski: at 32 and a half. Yeah, clock.
Wes Bos: Yeah, me too. But whatever. This is our show. We're like Netflix, we can make it as long as we possibly want and hopefully you're still listening. If Wait, we should do a hashtag. I always like that when people if you reach the end of this podcast, do hashtag syntax goals. And and tag Scott and I.
Scott Tolinski: Nice.
Wes Bos: Nice. So anything else to add for today?
Scott Tolinski: I don't have anything else to add. Make goals. It's important if you want to, like people always ask, like, seriously, I hit somebody in the level of slack room, which by the way, if you're not on, there's a little tutorial, slack room, it's on. There's a slack link at the footer of level up tutorials. COMM I hit somebody in there be like, I don't understand how Scott gets so much done. I'm convinced he's a machine. And I'm like, I'm not a machine. I'm not I don't get that much done. I'm like not that efficient. But I do make really goal. Like I make strong goals. I track them and I work on them. And I work hard. So I think that is the key to getting a lot done is to make these goals and to work at it. So that's all I got. That's the last thing I have to add. Yeah, that's it.
Wes Bos: Awesome. That's it for today. We'll see on Wednesday, already.
Unknown: Who's we what are we talking about on Wednesday was a little hint
Wes Bos: on piece. We are talking about design tips for developers. I'm really excited about that. So like these are things that you as a developer who might not necessarily be a great designer can put in place and make your stuff look better and work better.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, so good hype about that. It's a good episode we just recorded and I'm a big fan.
Wes Bos: So Alright, let's see on Wednesday, peace.
Scott Tolinski: Head on over to syntax.fm for
Unknown: a full archive of all of our
Scott Tolinski: shows. And don't forget to subscribe in your podcast player or drop a review if you like this show.