Unknown: You're listening to syntax the podcast with the tastiest web
development treats out there,
Scott Tolinski: strap yourself in and get ready to live ski and West boss. So welcome to syntax. In this episode, we are going to be doing a another potluck like we do every single month where we answer listener submitted questions. So if you have questions of your own, and you'd like to hear them on a potluck episode, First, make sure it's a good question. Second, head on over to syntax FM, and submit this question that we have a I think it's a button in the top right that just says ask a potluck question. So go ahead and click on that button, ask your question there, it gets submitted to our sheet. And then we go ahead and pick the ones that we think are going to be very good for everyone else to listen to. My name is Scott to Lenski and with me as always is West boss.
Wes Bos: I am hungry for some tasty treats today. Scott, I can't tell you that Oh, yeah, I'm hungry
Scott Tolinski: to this episode is sponsored by as Wes said before the show two types of books, fresh books in Manning books, which is the joke I think we made before. So there we go. When we want to get further on in the episode, we'll give our sponsors a little bit more time talking a little bit about fresh books and Manning books. So let's get into this potluck where we have a whole bunch of fun questions lined up for you here. I think it's gonna be really good one. Do you want to take this first one? Yes,
Wes Bos: I do. So the question is from Aaron Kessler, how do you distinguish between normal and virtual pixels on high DPI devices? How do you call pixels? Which tools do you use for optimizing images? So interesting question. So real quick, if you're not familiar, device, screen resolutions are getting really high. So the way it used to be is you'd get like a 19 inch monitor, it would be 1080 P, and you'd have 1920 pixels by 10 ADP pixels. And the actual pixels in the monitor are the actual pixels that show up on the screen. Now we start to get higher DPI devices. So think of a 4k TV, a 4k TV or a 4k monitor has four times the amount of pixels. But if you were to run it at those pixels just get much smaller, because they can still you can still get a 4k 19 inch monitor. It's just that the pixels are much smaller and everything is much crisper. And the problem with that is if you were just to run it at, like however many pixels 4000 pixels wide, everything would be extremely tiny. And you can't necessarily do that. So what high DPI does is that it will scale up the content like your phone, for example is not the first retina iPhone was not 320 pixels wide, it was 640 pixels wide. And then it just doubled everything up. So you you as the developer still thought it was 320, but everything was just twice as crisp. So that's the whole idea behind high DPI, I recently upgraded to a 32 inch 4k display. And this is really good because you can everything. It's not totally retina but everything is very nice and crisp. So the question is how do you handle this way back when the first retina iPhone came out? What happened is that everyone was still using like PNGs for like icons and stuff like that. And you still see it on websites, you'll you'll see a company's logo, and it'll look pixelated, and everything else will look nice and crisp. And that's because they are using a raster based logo or raster based images for that. So what are the solutions, I almost don't care about this at all, because it's Yeah, the devices problem to figure out what the resolution is, whether that's your Mac, and you're changing the resolution for more space or less space, or whether that's a phone where they are scaling up the pixels, you should mostly be using things that are vector base like type is vector based SVG is vector base, all of CSS is vector based. So you don't have to worry about any of that you don't have to worry about sizing or anything. Really the only spot you do have to care about is raster base images. And if that's the case, I will almost for logos, I'll just export it at twice the size for JPEGs. I mostly don't care about it, I just I don't want to people were exporting like double the JPEG for a long time. And then that just caused your your download size to bloat because now you're serving it, you can use things like was this source set on an image tag to provide different images for different resolutions if you want, but I mostly just lean on using vector based things and for raster based just make them a little bit bigger than they have to be so that they do look fairly crisp on high DPI devices. Yeah,
Scott Tolinski: I mean, my answers the exact same really, I don't think about it. And then the only time I do think about it is with my like course thumbnails, which are raster images, and even then it's like just a hold out of an older website. So I think though, those are gonna be going away. And the idea here is that well, now you can do shapes with CSS, you can do shapes with SVG. I mean, you can do so much. So between CSS and SVG, there's really not a whole lot of reasons to really care about this too much more other than just to be aware of that. It's a Cool. So next one we have is from AJ. He told us just to pronounce his name AJ, which is nice. And this question is, what are your thoughts on TypeScript? And selfishly I'd like to be learning about using it with react, any temptation to try it out if you're not already doing so why why not any sources you'd like to share on TypeScript? I recently released a course in November called level one TypeScript. So I have quite a bit of little experience here lately, picking up TypeScript and using in practical ways and things like that. And for a long time, I know we both sort of had been talking about some of these type systems for JavaScript as being like sort of a little bit of the Wild Wild West right now in terms of, there's a bunch of different ones. And you know, what are the best ones which are going to arise and which ones are going to really take care of the market share and things like that, if you've been paying attention, or looking at this stuff at all, you really see TypeScript and reason, both getting a lot of push lately, and I think TypeScript in particular is really sort of like the the popular solution. So I've become a big fan of TypeScript. And over the course of using it, and diving in deeper while making a tutorial series on TypeScript. There are things I don't necessarily like about it. But there, there are so many things to like about having types in JavaScript, in general. So I got used to types. The, I think, mostly just via one back end sort of programming, but also the graph, qL, and Apollo, I mean, everything's typed there. And if everything is typed there, it's going to be really nice to have your whole system be typed, because you can see the benefits of a type system immediately. And TypeScript In my opinion, does have the most to give you a straight up type system with getting in the way the least. And so that's personally why I like TypeScript, I think it's a good thing to learn, it's the thing that you're going to start seeing a lot on job applications and stuff like that. So I would personally add it to your list of skills, it's not a huge time sink to learn it, I don't think it's a huge investment to learn it. So if you're looking to learn in you know, you can subscribe to level up pro or by whatever not intending this to be an ad, you can find videos on YouTube as well just go ahead and at least at least get a basic understanding of what it is and how to use it.
Wes Bos: I'm pretty much of the same way. I think it's really neat. Doing graph qL has made me realize that types are awesome. And it would be great, I don't think I'd recommend it for someone who is brand new to JavaScript to learn it, I think is first learn regular JavaScript and then sort of move up to that it has this there's this really interesting tweet by Devin COVID, who's the the dev behind parcel, that amazing developer and he said, why he's not using TypeScript and people got spicy about that, I thought it was really interesting. And like, you're obviously free to use whatever it looks like he's using flow, which is a another way to do typed JavaScript. It's not its own language. It's just a syntax syntax that you add to your existing JavaScript to get types in it. But it's kind of one of these things like CrossFit, where people start using it. And they're just like, this is amazing. To tell everyone, I think people come off a little bit heavy sometimes. But I think there's a reason behind is that it's, it is awesome. So I'm really looking forward to to picking up a project in it in the future, because I've used it in a couple little demos here or there. But I haven't done anything like significant in it. And it's on my list of highly requested tutorials. So yeah, pretty cool. I think you should definitely check out TypeScript. If you are wondering, I don't think it's going anywhere, especially with the tooling of VS code. Now as well, word next question we have from Luke, I have heard you guys say good things about Digital Ocean before, but I am reading a lot of bad reviews about them on various websites. Are these just frustrated developers? Are there any merit to these claims? So Digital Ocean for those who don't know is like virtual private server, meaning that you can pay five bucks a month and you get a server quote, unquote, and a dedicated IP address, and you get some dedicated RAM and you get some space, put your stuff in, it's just a raw Linux box that you can log into and install all your stuff. They also have this idea of like droplets, your install is a droplet, but they have this idea of like pre made droplet. So you can you can grab like a Rails droplet or a node droplet and just get up and running immediately. The downside to that is that you it's still a Linux box, and you still are managing the box yourself. You're responsible for security updates you're responsible for if you just nuke the whole thing, and it doesn't work. It's not like when your WordPress goes down, you can just call GoDaddy and ask them why is my WordPress broken? Because at the end of the day, this is just it's just a resource. It's just a service that you you can buy. So I think when people the Digital Ocean is amazing, one of my favorite companies ever they are making some amazing stuff. I love everything they do. I think people who are frustrated with digitalocean are frustrated because it's not the handholding that they may have been expecting. Right And the reason it's cheap is because it's a raw box and you Gotta do it yourself. If you do need a little bit more hand holding, you need to go for some sort of managed service like like a Heroku, or now.sh, or WP engine or something like that, where these are services that are meant for hosting your, like Netlify or, or anything like that, where these are services that are meant for specifically hosting specific types of content. And it's going to be easier, but it's just probably going to be a little bit more expensive as well, the the more low level you go, the cheaper it gets, like the the very low level, you get like AWS lambda, which is impossible to configure, but the very cheapest, you could run your website on three cents a month, probably. And then the very expensive is the easiest.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, I remember when I signed up for digitalocean. And I was just like, oh my god, I can't believe how cheap This is. And then I learned everything I had to do myself, which I had never had the experience of managing a VPS before then actually, I guess I had with a media temple. But I don't know, for some reason digitalocean just felt a little bit different. And I really loved it simplicity and the documentation. I agree. I think most people guys are amazing. Yeah, that would get upset with that maybe it got in a little over their head without knowing what they were expected to be doing themselves on this platform. Or maybe they don't have the DevOps training or something like that. I personally didn't. But I have such a fondness of hacking away at those little things and gaining that Yeah, like little knowledge, you're experimenting that way. It's like a fun thing for me to figure out. And digitalocean One of the things that they do better than anybody is in their docks they like they really always have security first. And so they're always telling you to do like best practices and in configuring and you know how to how to do this and how to change the port and which you SSH on and stuff like that. And, and all sorts of like little things that I think that other platforms might just overlook showing you the bare minimum. And so I'm just a huge fan of digitalocean because of that. But again, it is a custom platform, and it requires a lot of work in that regard. So if you don't have that knowledge, by all means, take something that's a little bit more suitable for you.
Wes Bos: Yeah, like I had to figure out how to install swap memory. Have you ever heard of what that is? No,
Scott Tolinski: I've heard of swap memory. But I have not, I'm not going to work with it,
Wes Bos: you only get like half a gig of memory on your like $5 box. And if you want to npm install that will most likely like rollover, because 512 Meg's is not enough memory to do an npm install. So if that's the case, you need to use some other hard drive on the box as temporary memory. That's what swap memory is. And you have to you have to like dedicate part of the hard drive to it. And it'll it'll temporarily put those things on the hard drive as memory and read them back. And I was like, why do I know this? I'm a JavaScript developer, but it worked. So it was good.
Scott Tolinski: Nice. Alright, so the next question is from amo. And this question is really interesting, because we both run our own e commerce platforms, I thought this would be a good fit for both of us. So if you were to build an e commerce store, given that your business requirements specify that custom functionality is needed? Would it be smart to roll your own service? Or use Magento? Shopify WooCommerce? If if the latter what is the development experience like, which is shown a greater ability to implement custom functionality for server and client side code? Assume and time and budget is somewhat favorable? This is a tough question. And this is a question I think a lot of people might I think a lot of people might struggle with the e commerce is not a whole lot of fun in this territory. I know Shopify is is pretty flexible. I haven't used it myself. I have used Magento. extensively. Those of you who have been following level up tutorials for some time knows that Magento tutorials have been around for a long time. I don't want to say I hate Magento. I don't like Magento. Yeah, it's slow. It's incredibly annoying to develop on. And I don't know if Magento two has gotten that much better. But Magento one for the time that I spent with it was never any fun to work with. And we had projects with a huge amounts of skews and stuff like that, and, and the flexibility is fine. If you're good PHP developer, I'm sure you can can make sense of everything. I don't know, I just never loved working in it. I think one of the options here that is missing is a platform called reaction, commerce. And if you check out reaction commerce, they're gonna you're gonna like their website. It's a cute website. I'm going to tell you that right now. They have really nice little design here. But reaction commerce is maybe more of a modern stack of things where it has react on the front end and stuff like that. It's it's quote unquote, a developer's playground. This is the only e commerce platform that I considered when I was building level up tutorials. This is the only one I considered because it's the only one I felt like I could hack together. The things I wanted to do. In fact, the I think the original version of the level AppStore was on reaction commerce that just never went live. So I like reaction commerce for this kind of thing. At some point, you have to ask yourself, Is it really that difficult to build your own thing? We have one of our sponsors snip cart is a really good option to, I guess it depends on what your needs are snip carts really great because they take some of the back end sort of some of the the structure. So to get out of the way. Yeah, it's for jam stack, but I wouldn't necessarily limited to jam stack, I think it just makes the process a little bit easier of building a custom cart. So it's somewhat in between an e commerce platform and a custom cart. So yeah, I think there's a lot of options here. And I don't necessarily have a great answer for you. I'm interested to hear what other people on Twitter or whatever saying about these platforms, I know Shopify is really heavily used. But I would check out reaction commerce.
Wes Bos: I think it really like Scott says it depends on what you're trying to do. If you're just if you are trying to get up a store up and running as fast as possible, I would definitely reach for something like Shopify, but Shopify, I know I have friends who run clothing companies on Shopify, it can get expensive really quickly, where you have all of these different add ons every time you want to add a new feature either to build something or pay monthly for one of these specific special add ons that go onto your website. And if you have like multiple currencies, then sometimes they have to run to different stores at the same time. So it can get really expensive really quickly. But that said, the reason why so many people use it is because it just works. You don't really have to sweat it all that much. But if not, I think I go for something like a WooCommerce or any of these other ones that that that Scott has mentioned, I for sure would not build something from scratch myself. Because shopping carts are one of these types of things like, obviously, is my own course platform, I can do that. Because I'm just selling courses and there's like, like 12 different skews, and they don't have shipping. And they don't have shirt sizes and all that stuff. But if I was actual selling physical goods that needed fulfillment, and returns and yeah, there's a lot of discount codes. And there's, it's it's huge, how much logic goes into building an online store. And I would definitely not build something from scratch myself, I would either reach for a service and get up and running, I probably would just reach for a service. And then as I find like, Man, this thing's costing me like 1000 bucks a month, let me just put the time into actually building something out myself reach for something like a WooCommerce, or one of these other open source solutions. That would work better for me.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, that custom functionality is like really sort of the kicker is like, what is that custom functionality? And like, how custom is that functionality? You know, because there could be like little things, right? Like, let's go ahead. And when they purchase this, we can do this and this and this for them. And then maybe there's bigger things where it's tying in user accounts to subscriptions and attaching them to course purchases and stuff like sort of we have going on in some of our sites. But if you want to learn some of this stuff to be able to build some custom front end stuff. Well, we have a solution for you, which is Manning books has a really nice book that has was the release date on this thing.
Wes Bos: September 2018. That's fresh
Scott Tolinski: in my mind, someone say it's a fresh book. I wouldn't say that. So
Wes Bos: that would have been a turnaround. Imagine if we did the Freshbooks sponsor here instead. Oh, yeah, that would have been quite the turnaround. Yeah, quite the turnaround. This book is called a view j s in action. And it's on Manning publications. This book was just published a couple months ago. And it looks like just like two months ago. So it is brand new is from Eric Han chat. And Benjamin list one. That's a cool, last name. Last one. So this is the book that I need. Because if you're looking for a book that is going to teach you how to learn Vue js, this looks like a really good one. So it's includes everything introducing Vue js, adding interactivity, working less forms and inputs, conditionals, looping over your data component design, all the way through to testing, which is one thing that a lot of places don't include, which is pretty cool. So if you want to learn view, j s, check out Manning publications view j, s and action, they've got a special URL, where you it's a bit of a get your pen out, this is a bit of a long URL, or just click it in the show notes, but it's deals.manage.com forward slash web dev. And this is a special landing page just for syntax and it's gonna get you 40% off every book or video course@manning.com use the code syntax 40 to save 40% out they've got a bunch of recommendations that they've got here as well. If you're not interested in view, maybe you want to learn react or Redux or express or anything like that. They got something on everything. So I know a lot of people don't do video courses that's gone I produce if you just want a book, check out Manning stuff. That's great.
Scott Tolinski: Cool. All right. Nice.
Wes Bos: Next question is from Matt Greg. I feel pretty boss and he did bpos I think that's a little head nod to me at starting projects, but so Terry Pull at finishing them as people who finish courses and projects all the time. What is your advice to getting to that finish line? And I will tell you, what is it the the path to? What's that saying? The path tell is littered with good intentions or something?
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, something like that I yeah, yeah, I'm wrong all the time. So I'm not even gonna try.
Wes Bos: This line has good intentions. That's not the saying that I want to say I say the path to finishing a project is littered with unfinished projects. And while I definitely am a big proponent of actually finishing stuff, because like, I think that that's a problem that a lot of people have is that they they start a project and that last 10% is so hard to actually push through it. So my first advice is, just know that that last 10% is going to be the hardest, because that's when imposter syndrome sets in, that's when the hard part that you didn't necessarily think about specific things that you need to put into a project, that's when you're, you're scared to put it out to the world. But if that's the case, then for sure, make sure you push through that last 10%, because that's where I've sort of gained a lot of my momentum in my career is actually finishing the damn thing. But at the same time, for every one thing that I finished, I probably have 10 little silly projects that I've started up and have gone nowhere, but it was just me sort of poking around hacking around at something. And that's really where I've done most of my learning is in these little kind of hacky projects that don't really get anywhere. But I was telling Scott, I was like, you know, Scott, the learning is in the adventure, and he started laughing at me. But I think that's true. A lot of your learning is in just in the adventure if it doesn't necessarily finish something. That's not a total loss. You can learn along the way.
Scott Tolinski: It's not a total loss of if it's just like a for fun project. But like, yeah, imagine it's a project for a client. Well, finishing isn't a total loss. I didn't finish this project. But I still learned Oh, yes,
Wes Bos: I did a whole bunch. I appreciate the money client. No, I mean, that's like personal projects. But for for client projects, that's the best way to actually finish things is to have your ass on the line where you have to finish this thing because someone's paid you to do it. And you likely have a deadline that you're facing. Yeah,
Scott Tolinski: I think I think there's a big distinction there. I'm not good at finishing projects myself, which is one of the reasons that I level up tutorials is such a good project for me, because it's never finished. Like there's there's no end in sight. And I think those kind of projects are good, too. I mean, there doesn't have to be an end of a project Unless, of course, it is a client project. And if this is a client project, I think you do need to work better at like setting micro goals and things like that, making sure everything that is possibly in your to do list for this project is explicitly stated, use to do lists, check yourself off that way. And then that way, you never have this sort of situation where you're like, Oh, this project is dragging. And I don't know where I am or what I'm doing on it anymore, even though it needs to get finished. If you have a very defined list of things to get done, you can always feel that sort of validation of checking stuff off your list. So if you're looking for inspiration and those sort of things, I personally feel validated by checking stuff off my list and maybe give myself a system rewards or something that can take a break after I finished this features, something like that. And so I think that is an important thing. If the project needs to be finished. You do need to find some way to motivate yourself to keep accountable set deadlines for yourself. Even if your client or whoever is not setting deadlines for you have those deadlines and work towards them. Imagine that your butt is on the line, even if it isn't cool. So next one is from a man a man. You really
Unknown: man. Yeah, amen.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah. Amen. Amen.
Wes Bos: Hey, man. Hey, man. Don't say man. Say folks. Carry on.
Scott Tolinski: Hello, guys. Thanks for the great podcast. You're very welcome. Amen. Could you please explain how do you organize your files? What is your file structure for you? And both of your projects and other documents had videos and stuff? How do you structure your projects? This one is a question that I think a lot of people ask for a lot of different systems, especially in like react land, because react doesn't have like a way of doing things like some other frameworks would. And this could be, you know, really nice. For some people and other people. It can be absolutely terrifying. They're sort of just like, but without a structure, how do I know where to put things, we put them wherever you want. Whatever works for you, You do you. Me personally, since my platform is the full stack platform, like I have my back end and my front end in the same repo. And it's all very interconnected, and your twinkle there. And what we have in my structure is I have basically a UI folder, an API folder, and a startup folder. The startup folder tells things what to do, whether or not that is, you know, server side rendering, that sort of thing of registering my API and getting all set up that way, telling the front end how to rehydrate data and stuff like that start in the startup. It basically handles things that are going to be taking place both client Or server side on startup, the API folder is really just going to be all of my graph, qL, resolvers, and mutations, anything that's working with my database connecting that way, and any sort of initial setup I need for that API. And the UI folder is just all react components, a big old list of react components, I have one folder for elements, which includes all of my styled components that are, I should say, like root level, block level styled components, things that are highly reusable cards, headings, colors, stuff like that. I have a Utilities folder that includes things like breakpoints and other functions for CSS stuff that are used in styled components. And then I have everything else in a feature based folder. So I have things like, let's for instance, I have tutorial like the tutorial page. So that's in a folder, name tutorials, and everything in there is tutorial page, tutorial player, blah, blah, blah, anything that's related to that all of my tests, and all that good stuff live inside of there as well. And if I need like a one off styled component, it lives in the same file as the React component that's using it, instead of being in any sort of higher structure or anything like that. But for the most part, its UI folder has elements has utilities, and then feature folder straight out of that. And I don't do any nesting deeper than that. All of my react components are named while the files are all named after the component itself. I think that's pretty much it. The test just live right there. And everything is nice and easy.
Wes Bos: Awesome. I like this question, because I've spent a lot of time thinking about mine. And the way I do it for every project is that I have a folder in my computer in my like Dropbox, or in my websites folder that has a number, and every project gets a new number that is incremented by one and that way, anytime I know I need to jump into my wife's website, I just type z 45. And then it goes into like project number 45. And that way, I can either reference the project by its number or by the project by his name. So like the the name of the folder will be like 102 dash, Caitlin, and that will be her specific folder inside of that, I will always have a design folder. And that will contain all of the sketch files, anything that I got from the client or whatever or anything that like, like the logo or anything needs to stay in there, I put that in there. In the root, I often usually have like a project.md, or ideas that MD or whatever, like a markdown file that I use just to collect ideas of things that need to land somewhere inside of there. And that way, anytime I have a phone call with somebody, or anytime I have a quick idea, I pop that markdown file open and just start typing into it. And then also in the root of that depends on like the project. If it's just a like a single application, I'll just have like a code folder and in that and there will live the actual the code base. But for most of my projects, I usually have a front end folder and a back end folder. Inside of the back end folder. If it's an express app, I'll have a controllers folder, a routes folder, a models folder, a views folder, if I'm doing a server rendered application, and then I'll have like a lib folder, or a helpers folder, as I like to call it. And anything that is like not a node module, but is still foundational code to that code base will generally go in the lib folder. And then on the front end, I'll also have a lib folder that will contain the same kind of thing of a components and a pages folder if it's an ext JS application. And I usually like to keep like Scott said, I usually like to keep my component, my styles and my tests all in a feature folder. And then if it's a shared style, I'll move that out into its own styles folder that gets reused through multiple style components. So like every project I do is a little bit different than the last one, which is frustrating to some people because they want to they want to be told, this is where these go. And this is the best folder structure. But whether you're using react or not, whether you're using style components or not, or whether you're using like bem or sass or anything, it really depends on like what your application actually tends to tends to look like but I've really have like just the high idea of having a numbered project with a front end back end design and then just a markdown file though collect any other thoughts that I have.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, this is one of those ones. That's an always evolving sort of thing and it always changes how you like it. I've redone the organizational structure of my application a lot of times I mean it's changed so many times So again, this is there's there's no like the way to do it. find something that works for you find something that makes sense for you find something that you and your team enjoy and I'm sorry if if we can't hold your hand too much on that one because that's just that's just how it is. I can
Wes Bos: tell you one thing I don't like it's when people use feature folders and use it index dot j s so that you can just require the the folder I do I don't like that because it's then you have like eight index dot j s is open at once. No VS code will allow you to see the folder name in there. But I found that really frustrating, especially for my tutorial takers. Yeah, in sometimes people just export the component and then import it into index js and then immediately export it again, there's too much overhead for me. So I don't use, I try to avoid index j s as much as possible.
Scott Tolinski: So here is where I use index j s, there's only one situation where I use index j s. And it's almost when I want something to be sort of like a package. And I don't, I just don't want to keep this package in its own repo because it makes more sense to keep it more intertwined with my application. So for instance, my styled components library is has an index js. So in my own personal design system, for level up tutorials, in my elements folder is an index.js that collects all of them. That way I can import any component, whether it's a car, or whatever, and it's only for CSS based components. And I do the same thing with utilities but only because the stuff that lives in utilities just things like breakpoints or maybe like a transition function or something like that. So I don't do a with react components. I do it with my stub components. And I found that makes it nice because then it like typically you're importing like I don't want to import a card from cards and then a header from heading you know, I mean, it's like that's that's a little extra to me for Yeah, imports on I'd prefer to just import them all like it's from a library or something. But
Wes Bos: we should do one of those change my mind podcasts is that we don't disagree on anything. Except what we just changed my mind.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah. Next one. This is an easy name. Collin. Thank you, Colin, for having an easy name here. Colin asks, you guys mentioned working for agencies in the past, as a freelance web developer, what is the best way to find those agencies and to be employed by them? Also, can you explain what agencies are? I love the show. Thanks. So I've worked for agencies for most of my career. And basically, you could think of it as like a company. That's the idea of a design agency or Development Agency, or any of that stuff, it comes out of this sort of this print world history where more people would hire a print company to design a logo to design a pamphlet to do some print to do some, that sort of stuff, designed posters, whatever, right? And so the print companies, they they hired graphic designers who did logos, who did all that stuff, make things look nice. And the world changed as the world changed. We got computers, and then phones and the internet and all sorts of stuff. And now those agencies do more than just print. Typically. I mean, maybe if you're the best print agency in the world, maybe even now it's like hipstery to start a print agency or something. But typically, these agencies to survive these, they're just companies right that do design as a service. It's like a freelancer but a company, right. And so these companies now have branched off. This is not like a new thing. This has been going on since the web to do websites and web design and app design and app sites and all sorts of stuff, app sites, that's a new thing. So they basically were print shops that have transformed to be digital. their clients are typically companies A lot of it is like b2b stuff, because they're they're fairly expensive. Instead of getting a single freelancer, you get a team, or you get maybe a project manager, you get a couple designers, you get more than one design idea, or developers really
Wes Bos: popular in like, like consumer products like working for Pepsi or doing a big marketing agency, or when I did, a lot of it was working in with like VH sauces. I worked with Pepsi, all these kind of companies, right?
Scott Tolinski: Well, so I've been on a lot of ends of the spectrum. So my three agency jobs were very different sizes. My first job was like a small 12 to a 16 person agency. And in that in that agency, most of our clients were local companies. So we wouldn't use a local medical supplies company who needs a website. There's a Yeah, you know, one of the concert venues has an annual concert, and they need like a specialized website for that annual concert along with screen printed posters and logos and stuff like that. One of our big clients was, I think the biggest client for that was just a conference, right? It's a yearly conference. And so those kind of gigs they they keep the company alive, they keep the company open, and they hire, you know, any 12 to 15 people. I had another agency job at the University of Michigan where all we did was internal sites to the University of Michigan. Every single department there, like needs a website with custom needs and stuff like that. So they the clients were even though they were internal, they were all sort of their own own individual projects. And then like you mentioned, I also worked at a big agency where our client was Ford, and with Ford, the agency did all of their, their video, they did their print, they did marketing campaigns, they did a whole lot of stuff, in addition to web work. So it was just like one small component of it. So quote, unquote, finding an agency job, it's just applying for a company that does work for clients. That's it and you'll look at them. I don't know if they'll be like so and so design agency, maybe they will, but you'll see a ton of them around any any major city that you live in or anything like that. I don't know how to Explain it other than their design companies, development companies, that sort of thing. Yeah, yeah.
Wes Bos: So Colin asked, he's a freelance web developer, and how do I work with these companies, because that's how I got a lot of my work is that I was like subcontracted from an agency for the larger client. And the way that I did it was I just really got to know, developers. So the kind of the way in is not through emailing every single one that certainly might work. But what worked for me is that I was just like, friends with the developers or, like, I would do workshops on the weekend with ladies learning code. And there would be often project managers from these agencies coming in, not to learn how to code but just so they can learn how to like talk to talk, and be able to talk to their own developers. And I would say, Hey, I'm also available for hire, if you ever need me. So it would either be the project manager or the developer, they need help. Oh, Wes is really good at x, y, and z. Let's get him in. And he can help us out with this specific JavaScript project or this WordPress products that we had. So that was sort of my way to infiltrate as you, you don't get in at the top, you get on the lower level, because usually, when the developers or the project managers need help, they go to their own network first.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, I would say almost anytime we needed outside help from freelancers, we would hire one a specialist, someone who was really good at one particular thing. And then maybe we had seen them on message boards or like if we needed a an expert for this one particular Drupal feature, we would find the person who made the plugin and asked them if they could do it, too, we would hire within the like you said, our network, but also the network of the company, maybe past developers who had left to go do another gig, but were still really good and had that specific knowledge. Or maybe they would want to pick up some extra money. So we would almost go to people that had to work at the company experts. And then I guess after that it is all personal network who you've met at meetups, who you know, can get the job done and who you know, is going to do a good job for that. As a freelancer, that's how to get in, in my opinion, as well. And one of the things you want to make sure if you are a freelancer trying to get some of these gigs, you're gonna want to make sure that you have excellent bookkeeping. And by having excellent bookkeeping, you're gonna make sure that not only do you get paid on time from these agencies come tax time, at the end of the year, you're going to have a clear picture about all that fat cash you're rolling in from these agency gigs he picked up. So the way to do that is with fresh books.
Wes Bos: Yes, you do. So when I worked with agencies, a lot of time, I would bill hourly. And what's interesting about that is because they need to know the breakdown of your hourly work so that they can then push that to the client as well and Bill them hourly for the stuff. So I had to keep really close logs of exactly what I was working on, and what different features because they build client different rates for different types of stuff. So if you use Freshbooks, you can use their time tracking tool right inside of Freshbooks. You can set up a client, you can set up different types of jobs. I know some some agencies charge different for design and different for development, and different for back end front end development. So you can log what type of work you've been doing. And then simply just send off that invoice off to the client. So check it out, if you are going to be working with agencies or just running your own freelance show@freshbooks.com forward slash syntax for 30 day unrestricted free trial. Don't forget to use syntax in the How did you hear about a section sick? Next question we have here is from Peter, I once read an interview Wes gave in which you mentioned that frequently changing jobs is the best way to get a salary increase. Do you believe that to be true is job hopping a bad thing is a criticism justified? So I forget where I gave that interview. But this is coming from me who had taught at boot camps. And I've seen hundreds of students go through boot camps. And I do agree that this sounds terrible that you should just be dropping companies and moving jobs every six months, because that's what everybody complains about millennials doing already. But just from the sheer amount of seeing people who have started off as junior developers, and over the course of four years, trying to become senior developers, I have seen people get extremely well paying salaries by doing exactly this. And it is just job hopping from one to another. So I agree with Wes. Yeah,
Scott Tolinski: it's a tough one. Because I don't want to make it seem like loyalty is not a good thing. Because loyal totally company is a good thing. But oftentimes you have to wonder, is this company loyal to you as a person as well, like sometimes you're working for a company for a long time, and you don't necessarily get that same sort of respect back? Maybe the company's not doing well. Maybe you're the first one to go. And you could say, well, I had this other job offer, you know, and I should have taken it. And some of that stuff is is hard to plan out that said every single time I've jumped from job to job, I've gotten my largest pay increases. And it is sometimes even applying for a job and getting a new job or being accepted into a job is a great way to get a pay bump at your current place. And I don't I don't want to say to weaponize that but I personally have had a situation where someone was trying to poach me into a new company, I did the interview process just because they promised to pay me a lot more. I did the whole interview process expecting my current company not to, you know, match or anything like that, because they already told me they couldn't afford to pay me anymore, right. So I did the whole interview process got accepted for the job. And it was a good, good, good pay increase. So I went back to my employer to give them my two weeks, and they basically flat out told me no, they were just like, doesn't matter. Whatever it is, we're covering it. We can't lose you at this point in time. We need you right now. And so I said, Okay, well, let me go back to this other company and turn them down. And I was not trying to play the companies off each other. There was no intention. hardball there.
Unknown: Yeah.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, I wasn't even trying to do that. Because it was a good pay increase at that point in time. And then this company is like, Okay, well, we're gonna give you this much more now. And I was like, uh, okay, so my other job already told me that they would give me a pay bump. So I was like, well, they're gonna give me this much more now. And I don't want to play this off you guys. But they're, you know, you're
Unknown: a shrewd negotiator, right,
Scott Tolinski: back and forth. And because of that, they were like, if you say, you'll stay right now, we'll give you that what they just said. And I was like, Yes, I'll stay there. And sometimes, like that could blow up in your face, I felt like if I was trying to play them off each other, then it probably wouldn't have ended well, but the idea here is that like, your current organization might not value or know your value until you're leaving, necessarily, they might not know what you got until it's gone, that sort of thing. So I have always gotten my biggest pay bumps from changing jobs. That said, I do respect loyalty. And I do all respect all that stuff. And I think if a company is treating you really well, you should treat them really well. But in the same regard, it's a high paying industry, if you got the skills to get those bills paid, and all that stuff like that you should take the money, and don't worry about it too much.
Wes Bos: Next question we have for Mark volkman. If I choose next jass. Does that mean I won't be able to use a new react feature like hooks and suspense until slash if next JS team implements it? And maybe we should swap out next is with Gatsby as well? Because this question applies to any sort of framework where react kind of comes along baked in with that? And the answer to that is yes, you have to wait until these frameworks support your updated version of react. But that said, there almost always is a I always am like, I want to use hooks, I want to use suspense. And anytime I've wanted to use these cutting edge features. There's always a canary version of next Jess available. There's Tim nucleons, who is one of the team members on next Jess is always pushing out tons of updates for this stuff. So the answer is yes. But you almost we'll never have to wait because the teams behind these things are excited to use these features as well.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, also the stuffs in alpha still so yeah,
Wes Bos: yes. That's funny. Like sometimes people are like really gung ho about these new things. But you have to wait until they they get like hooks and suspense are not in at the time recording this podcast. They're not in production. Yeah, they're not. They're not solidified just yet. So hold your horses just
Scott Tolinski: chill. Yeah, chill. Okay. Next one is from Tyler and Schuster Schuster. It. There's no age, Nick could be Schuster could be
Wes Bos: sudo. Su stir. Sure. Star sister.
Scott Tolinski: Okay, got this one. When do you use react dot fragment? And when would you use a div to wrap many return components from render? Okay, so for those of you don't know, at some point last year, I think 2017 2018 I don't remember at this point when react fragment was introduced. But react fragment basically allowed you to output things without a wrapping HTML element. Now for a long time, this was one of the weirdest pain points in react, people would go ahead and they'd have the one to return essentially several different things. And then react would freak out because you need to have those in an array instead of just returning them right. And there's good reasons for this technically, right there, why you need an array for each of those. But it was a giant pain point. Because of the way a lot of developers solved this. Instead of returning an array. They returned a div to wrap around their code, which turned react into sort of like, div hell just divs populating just sprinkled out throughout register a div wrap a div around it, right. That's the only way I'm going to get it to render. And so when react dot fragment was released, along with the shorthand for it, which is like an open bracket, close bracket is my favorite little shorthand. When react fragment was released, you could now use that react fragment or that shorthand to wrap your code and have it work instead of outputting it as array or wrapping it in a div and to me, this is one of the nicest little HTML improvements in react. So when would you use this? I would use it any time you need to not have your code be wrapped in a div, like the decision should not be based on a react sort of situation. For me the decision is a structural HTM Yo thing, right? Like, do you need a div wrapped around this thing if you do, then use a div. If you don't use react fragment, don't use it if you know,
Wes Bos: totally, the biggest use case for using react fragment is grid Flexbox sibling and feature selectors in CSS where the parent child of elements are, are required, like grid, you can't set your grid items to be items that are lower than the grid container, they have to be direct children of the the grid container. So that is extremely helpful when you have one container that is your grid and another component that produces the children the grid items. And previously, you would have to wrap a div around it and then you broke, you broke the grid layout. And now we can just use react dot fragment. I like to call them ghost elements because they render out to nothing at the end of the day.
Scott Tolinski: That's a way cooler name. That's Yeah, like I want to alias that to be the ghost emoji and then I tried it.
Wes Bos: I tried it. It doesn't work. I have a tweet about it. It was hilarious. You could probably write a Babel plugin for it though.
Scott Tolinski: That sounds sick. I love the name, Ghost.
Wes Bos: Ghost. Ghost ghost fragments.
Scott Tolinski: That is dope. Uh, but yeah, no, again, I this is one of my my favorite features. Just because you know, one of those things. It's like, should the framework get in the way of writing the HTML you want to write? No, I don't think so. So react fragment for the win here. All right, let's
Wes Bos: jump into the section that is sick picks. This is where Scott and I are sick. Pick an item that is something that is sick in our lives. And we would like to tell you all about it. Alright, my sick pick today is a designer that goes under the handle ghostly pixels. So you know, I'm designing my own redesigning my website right now because it's much needed. And I'm going with a bit of a grungy textured feel, as I do with a lot of my courses has come as a surprise, surprise, surprise. It's funny because like I've sort of just embrace the whole punk grew up as a punk hardcore kid sort of thing. And I just I don't think I'll ever let the grunge Enos go especially now that we are on such a high DPI screens, the very subtle grunge just looks so good to me on these things. So I usually go to True Grit texture supply. They're sort of like the big the big dog in the space. And they have like Adobe procreate extensions, and whatnot, but they're pretty expensive. And they don't give you a transparent PNG. So you have to do that yourself with all that either. Select the black color and take it out yourself. So I found this other designer called ghostly pixels. And he's got all kinds of grunge textures, grit map, wood grain, and they're all like nine bucks. 10 bucks, I think I bought like the entire thing for like 60 bucks. And they just look so good in all of my designs. So big fan of that. Check it out. If you want to support another designer, this is one of those our design episode we talked about little tricks that you you can have and the adding a little bit of texture or a little bit of, I don't know, just finesse and in a day that we talked we talked earlier about these everything's going vector but in an age where everything is going vector, I feel like if you add a little bit of grit and grain as long as you're doing it at two x so it doesn't look pixelated thing. It adds a little something, something to your designs.
Scott Tolinski: Nice, gritty, gritty to your site.
Wes Bos: It's gritty.
Scott Tolinski: She's Google gritty.
Wes Bos: It's a efficient course planning software. No.
Unknown: It's the mascot of the Philadelphia Flyers. Oh,
I got it now. Yeah, I said goodie. He is outrageous. That's funny.
Scott Tolinski: So my sick pick is Undertale, which is video game. So I occasionally sick pic video games here. And this one is I have it for the Nintendo Switch you can find I think it's on most platforms at this point. This is a weird, weird game. I don't even know what to think about this game. It's made me feel things in weird ways. I don't know how to express it other than I don't want to spoil anything. It sort of has RPG elements here playing as a child. Again, I don't want to give away too much about this. But all I can say is that this game is like very heavy and unlike anything I've ever played before. And it like put me in some situations where you're making some choices, and a video game that maybe the game is choosing for you or you know, whatever. And it like really invokes some sort of odd emotion and stuff like that. It's a very bizarre situation. I would maybe watch a YouTube video on it or something. Don't watch anything that spoils anything. Because again, the part of the experience with this game is this that you're going in cold. So if you if you are interested in like sort of odd games that are going to sort of have a totally different experience than something you've ever had before, maybe RPG elements, stuff like that, check out Undertale I know it's probably old at this point, but it's really, really cool game.
Wes Bos: Awesome. What about shameless plugs,
Scott Tolinski: shameless plugs, levelup Pro. There's so many courses on level of pro that if you sign up for one year of level up pro right now you'll get like over 700 video tutorials by the end of your subscriptions. So that's like newish tutorials, I mean, in the past two years or whatever, and those are all premium tutorials. So level up tutorials.com forward slash pro setup for the year save 25%. If you are listening to this before January one, this is your last chance to get this price, the price is gonna be going up January one. So keep your eyes if you want to sign up for the year and lock into that price Lock and load lock into that thing. level of doors.com forward slash pro
Wes Bos: awesome. I'm gonna shamelessly plug my YouTube channel. I haven't posted a video in a couple of weeks yet, but I have a new one coming up working with IBM, they sent me this little drone. And I'm going to learn how to fly it with JavaScript. So if you want to see that I'm not doing like a tutorial, but I'm kind of just like kind of like this is me I'm I'm showing the code that I write and I'm like pausing every couple of minutes explaining what I've been doing. And it's kind of interesting new take on on doing a YouTube video. So I'm excited to have that up. It will probably be up by the time you listen to this. So check it out. youtube.com forward slash Wes Bos
Scott Tolinski: doe. Well, that's all I got. I hope you got some great information on this potluck. These are always so much fun.
Wes Bos: I always look forward to doing these. Awesome. Alright, thanks for tuning in. And we'll see you next week. Please
Scott Tolinski: head on over to syntax.fm for a full archive of all of our shows. And don't forget to subscribe in your podcast player or drop a review if you like this show.