Unknown: Monday,
Monday Monday, open wide
Announcer: dev fans yet ready to stuff your face with JavaScript CSS node
module BBQ Tip Get
workflow breakdancing soft skill web development hasty as crazy as tasty as web development treats coming in hot here is Sarah CUDA,
Bob and Scott Taylor.
Unknown: Totally in ski.
Oh, welcome
Scott Tolinski: to syntax in this Monday tasty treat, we're gonna be talking about rural and mobile internet revisited. We're going to be talking all about some of Wess trials and tribulations to get his mobile internet up and running. I guess you can't really call mobile, but your internet I should say up and running in the Chateau de boss. So my name is Scott Tolinksi. I'm a full stack developer from Denver, Colorado. And with me, as always, from the full stack shack is Wes Bos. I like that I actually hung up the sign behind me can't see me. So I got my video off right now. But because you're now says, Yes, because the internet is slow. I made this like cool sign with a router. It says the full stack shack. Nice. So this episode is sponsored by one of our super cool sponsors, and that is Log Rocket. Now Log Rocket is the service that allows you to see how and why bugs are happening on your site is very, very cool. It's one of those things you're running on checkout to actually see just how cool it is. Because what they do is they give you a full video scrubbable replay of what's going on in your application, when the user click the thing and how the thing happened that led to a bug, which means that you get to actually see what happened. It's like you suddenly become it'd be like a detective with the brain power to see in the past and see how somebody committed the crime so that you could solve it very easily, right? I mean, that's exactly what Log Rocket is doing. It's giving you that superpower to be able to see back in time and see what happened when the user click that thing. And the thing broke. And it integrates with all the tools you know, and love, such as just about any framework. I mean, it doesn't really matter. But it also connects to your Redux store, in case you're using Redux. And it connects to a lot of other tools, like some of our other sponsors, or other tools that you use. It's a very, very, very cool platform. And you can now host it in the cloud, or you can host it on your own servers. So a lot of cool stuff going on with Log Rocket, check it out with Log rocket.com forward slash syntax. Let's get into it. So a quick primer. For those who didn't listen to the last one. About a year ago, we did a show on getting Rural Internet and I
Wes Bos: realized man, Well, not exactly a year ago, probably like 10 months ago. But yeah, it was it was a long time ago. So I've been playing with this stuff for probably a year and a half. And just because like my wife and I about a year ago, we bought a cottage in Northern Ontario. And there's not a whole lot of options for internet yet. And I've done all the research and played with all the things I've spent a bunch of money on different antennas and modems and routers, and different ways to go about it. And I get questions all the time of like, how do I do this, because like, one of the cool things about being web developers, you probably can work from anywhere. And especially now that we have this pandemic going on, people are like just being able to go wherever they want and be able to work from that as long as you have a good solid internet connection. So I think that's pretty cool. I really think that having like fast internet is a bit of a human right. It's obviously not like food and water. But certainly I see people out here that are locals struggle with getting fast internet. And it certainly gets in their way, especially now that we're trying to do school from from being online. So what I'm going to do in this episode is sort of break down the different options, and then go into my setup as to how I've made it work out here. So I'll go through the options real quick. You've got Satellite Internet, you've got wisps, and you've got sale cellular LTE for different options for getting internet. So there are no phone lines that reach out or I am as well as many rural places. They have phone lines, but they don't have DSL. So most people say oh, just get DSL. But you can't do that. Because the way that DSL works is that they run a fiber line and they have a box somewhere in your neighborhood and then they they run the last leg of the internet over the phone lines. And if you don't have a box anywhere near your house, then there's no way you can get any any speeds past dial up over your phone lines. There's also no cable connections out in most rural places. So you can't that's a hard word to say rural.
Unknown: It is it's really hard for me to say rural, rural, rural. Yeah, so that can be an option there right there. Because that's trying to They roll
Wes Bos: someone out to the soundboard. So satellite has been an option for a long time in Canada, we have one called explore net in the States, the big one is Hughes nets, these companies have one or two satellites up in up in the air. And they have very high latency like over a second latency, which is really bad. Like, if Scott were to run a speed test right now, go go run a speed test and tell me what your your ping is. If you open up your terminal and just type ping google.com, or ping Wes Bos calm, the amount of time it takes to send a small amount of bytes, or the amount of time it takes for my voice to reach Scott is what is called latency because obviously there is it takes a while for data to travel over the wire. But if you were to send a very small amount of data and just like a pulse to someone, you have some sort of latency that's generally measured in milliseconds. So at home, I have like a 20 millisecond. And that's on a fast cable connection. I'm tethered to my phone right now. And that's a 60 millisecond latency. And then once you get on to satellite, they often get into hundreds if not a seconds of latency. What do you have?
Unknown: I'm on my Wi Fi connection, and I have four millisecond. Yeah. That's like nothing. I bet if you were wired, you'd get you'd get even less than that. Yeah, because I mean, I'm getting a quarter of my speeds right now.
Wes Bos: Wow. Yeah, yeah, I've seen people with fiber post one millisecond. And I'm getting 60 on an LTE connection right now. And that just goes up from there. So satellite was not really an option for me just because of the high latency as well as the congestion. And then the speeds as well. The upload speeds or download and upload speeds are pretty awful for that. We are I've been watching a lot lately is starlink, which is Elon Musk's SpaceX company, they are they have been launching low orbit satellites. There's also another company called one Webb that's working on this as well. And they are launching satellites that are much lower than hughesnet and explore net. And they're saying that you'll be able to get 400 megabits down and about 30 milliseconds latency, which is still not fiber. But that's extremely fast for people who are in a lot of rural location. So that's what they're they're aiming for. It looks like at the time recording, we're recording on June 1. And they're about two months out from private beta testing, and four months out from public beta testing. Hopefully, in I don't know, six, eight months from now, this entire podcast will be obsolete, because especially in in all of Canada and northern us, there is going to be a satellite internet via starlink. So that's what they're saying. Obviously, proof is in the pudding, whether they can actually deliver it or not. But I'm very much excited to to get that out here.
Unknown: That's all fascinating to me, because it is it does seem like something's going to change very quickly. But it's kind of seen that way for a while. The whole satellite internet thing is sort of been teased, or whether that's internet via balloons, or all sorts of these different strategies for bringing internet to underserved areas, whether that is rural areas, or just in the middle of Africa or something, right. So it's such an interesting topic that I wonder what the actual timeline looks like, you know,
Wes Bos: yeah, I've been watching it like crazy. And they're obviously going going quick, but like they still have to test it. Once all that like all the satellites are not even up they still have at the time recording, they've still 15 more rocket ship launches before they can for the end of the year before they can get all these satellites in the air. So looking forward to that. The next one we have here. I won't spend too long on these because these are not the options that I went with. The next one is a Wisp stands for wireless internet service provider. What happens is that somebody in the community and these are generally very small internet service providers, not like a Comcast or something but I'm part of a Facebook group and sort of just watching and it's generally somebody that has a little bit of land or a place to put a tower they'll throw up a tower, they'll pay to get fiber run from the local city or they'll be made in from the local city if they can have line of sight and then they will broadcast on generally they broadcast them on unlicensed spectrum so your cell phone will often run on a 700 megahertz or like five G is going to be running at 30 3030 megahertz. Whoa, hold on let me look at Did you know what is that five
Unknown: G's? It runs at the exact megahertz that will scramble your brain according to some people. Did you see that? That whole scam there was like some five USB dongle.
Yeah, the USB dongles. So for those of you who don't know, there was like a town hall meeting. I think it was in England. Basically these people saying Well, we've used this item to block the five g that harmful five g rays that are penetrating our brains, as well Coronavirus. came from. Yeah, that is where Coronavirus came from and it's been very effective using this dongle. And then somebody found out it was just like a 512 megabyte USB dongle with the sticker on it. And they were charging an insane amount of money for it oh my gosh, makes me feel bad for a lot of people because they make me feel bad about the education system for people that fall for that kind of stuff.
Wes Bos: So 5g is 25 to 39 gigahertz that is pretty high in the spectrum, obviously depends on your local government and who sells the spectrum, generally us and in Canada are, are the same as well, we're getting 5g as well, there are places in the spectrum that are unlicensed, meaning anybody can run them. And that's why if you buy a walkie talkie or a baby monitor or something like that, you're allowed to just broadcast the signal over that. Whereas if you want to run a ham radio, you're not allowed to do that without a license because different megahertz and gigahertz of the spectrum are license. So generally, the way that these widths work is that I didn't even know this until there was rumors of a Wisp going up in our location. They run basically a massive Wi Fi router, they put up a tower that's about they try to stay under 100 feet in Canada, because then you don't need a license to put up a tower or a permit or anything. And then they just rebroadcast the internet signal on 2.45 and five gigahertz, which is the same frequency that your your Wi Fi router runs on. And because those are unlicensed, it seems pretty cowboy. But it definitely is the way that a lot of smaller communities work. And there's been rumors, I've been talking to the local ISP that they're putting up a tower on our Lake, but every time I ask them about it, they're like, yeah, hopefully soon, maybe next week, and it's been like a couple of months of that. So unsure if that will actually ever happen. But with seem to be like that's what I would look for if you live in a rural place. There's generally someone that invests 10 $15,000 into a tower and trenching fiber all the way there.
Unknown: That's wild.
Wes Bos: And then the final one, which is what I've gone with is just using the cellular networks in your area. So if you have good cell phone signal, which often lot of rural areas will have a good cell phone signal or good enough to reach their area, you can try to use that to get your internet and I'll talk about the plans in just a second. But that certainly is a good option. Some of the wisps do use LTE as well. But it's not like a cell phone provider LTE, it's just a localized, so they'll throw up one tower with LTE signals that broadcast out of it. That's sort of another option versus the five and 2.5 gigahertz. So let's talk about routers and modems. If you want to use cellular LTE, you need to go off and get a router that will support that as well as a modem card that will support that. So popular routers that are out there, they you can pretty much run any router that will run this OS that's called golden orb or router it's called. What that is, is it's a version of open WRT so open WRT is like a custom modem firmware that you can throw on. I don't know there's a list of like 100 different routers that you can go buy for hundred bucks and they all run on that as long as your router has enough like RAM and has the different chipsets in it, then it will be able to run in the difference between open WRT and golden orb or router or the one I've used is called why fix they're all based on the same thing. They have added code in order to communicate and configure LTE modems because generally your router doesn't care about being a modem. your router just takes in a like an ethernet cable from whatever your cable or DSL or fiber connection is this custom I'll just call it router will run on you can go and buy like a Netgear modem and hack it to run that on the pretty popular one out there is called the W e 826 dash T two and you can just google this it's something like 40 bucks on eBay it's nice and small it runs on 12 volt which is important because that means you can plug it into your car as well or you can just go ahead and buy it comes with
Unknown: a 12 volt plug like the DC the the cigarette jack yeah right yeah, cuz exactly USBs are only five volts as far as I'm aware, right? Or maybe they're more now but I think in the past they've only been five.
Wes Bos: Generally it's dependent on the little nub. So the knob that you plug into your car or the knob that you plug into your wall will either take DC to DC stepped down so your car voltage is DC and that will take 12 volt and step it down into generally five or 2.1 or your the wall one will take one to one In North America and step it down into what you want and they certainly can go much higher though and that's why you get these bigger blocks when you buy an iPad or even bigger when you buy the one that comes with your MacBook now so it's definitely depend on that as well as like the spec, there's a limit to how many volts can go over a USB cable. So that's like a super popular one. That is just a router. They generally don't come with modems installed. I'll talk about that in just a second. And then other option good options are and very popular right now is the Nighthawk m one.
Unknown: Oh, yeah, that looks cool.
Wes Bos: Yeah, it looks very cool. DMR 1100. Ever since the pandemic came out, they went from I bought mine for about 200 bucks. It's great. It's got a little screen on it. that'll tell you what's going on has a nice battery on it that lasts quite a long time. So it's it's pretty portable, you can throw it in your, in your bag, something like that. So that's, that's a really nice option. It comes with a comes with a modem inside of it, it will do up to like 10 different devices or something like that. And then it also has an Ethernet out that you can plug into your your regular home networking setup, which is pretty cool. The only downside to that is it's not super hackable, because like they don't give you full control over absolutely all your IP tables and everything like that, like you would with open WRT or router, but it's pretty popular, and I really like it as well. In the last podcast we did, I said I'm using the Zed te mf 288. And that is a good very good router. But it doesn't it's not the khamba custom firmware on it, you can't put your own modems in it. So if that works for what you're using, that works great. There's a local carrier bell that uses those. So we have a plan with them and I threw that SIM card in there. So those are sort of the the three big routers that are out there. There's certainly lots of other options. But if you want something that's easy go with probably the 826 T two or the Nighthawk m one. We'll talk about modems. So modems are the things that take an actual SIM card and convert that into a data connection. And there's two types of modems, you have a host modem, which is like if you've ever seen like these little plug in USB things that you plug into your laptop and it has a SIM card in it, that's a host modem. And there are more popular the PCIe cards, or they're actually mini PCIe. Or they're this other thing called an m two card. And generally these modems are tiny little cards that you can generally slap into your laptop or into one of these modems. And then it will read the SIM card data from either an adapter or from your your modem. The Wi Fi 26 comes with a SIM card slot in it that it will read that data from popular modems out there. The most popular ones are from Sierra wireless, which is owned by Netgear. So if you buy the Nighthawk, it comes with Sierra wireless, or you can just go buy these cards, there is a popular modem that is on Amazon. That is you can look up these things if you're really into it, I won't bore you with the the details of it. But there's a popular one that were pulled out of old Dell laptops that can be flashed as a very popular shear wireless card. So those are probably the best I went through a whole bunch. There's also another company quiz out qu EC L, they made popular ones, but in in my experience, they don't work as well. And they're not as configurable as the Sierra wireless ones. Once you have a modem, you can start playing with it by by communicating to the modem via what are called app commands. So you generally telnet into your router, or the router will have an interface to send these commands to your router. And you can do things like what's very popular is called band locking. So if you turn your phone on your iPhone, it'll just connect to whatever band it thinks and bands are the different different megahertz and gigahertz spectrums. And there's like band two and band four and band 10. And different carriers are on different bands. And it will try to connect to the best one. But what people have found is that if you lock it to a certain band, especially some of these new, higher frequency bands, if you're nice and close to a tower, then you can get faster speeds. Or if you're further away from a tower, you can lock it to a lower band and make sure that it always stays on that. So I did a bunch of testing on the cell towers in my area and I realized that band 10 is where I get the fastest speeds. So I locked it to that band. And then you can also enable carrier aggregate aggregation so your iPhone will do this by default, but it will lock to multiple bands at once. It'll say like, I'm gonna use band 10 and band two and put those together and that will allow me to get like 150 megabits down and 150 megabits up by sort of aggregating them together. Unfortunately, it doesn't work in my area just because the towers don't support carrier aggregation. But I found in when I'm in Hamilton, the towers do support that. So that's another thing you can kind of go with. Mm hmm. What else by issuing commands to these modems, you get detailed values on power. So one thing I had to do is point an antenna around my property to find where I was getting the best reception. And by issuing commands to these modems, you can get the raw data instead of like two bars, because like what is two bars mean? And under the hood, you can get actual raw data on different values, rssi signal signal to noise ratio, it's a little bit geeky, but you can do a little bit of research into it and figure out what values should you be looking at getting higher or lower. And then finally, you can get cell tower IDs. So it's important to know which South cell tower you're locked into. And each tower has an ID on it. And those ideas are not readily available it either in Canada or in the US. So you sort of have to find them yourself or use an app I'll talk about in just a second.
Unknown: Geez, what would you do if you weren't a computer person? Like this is interesting. But like, I can't imagine any normal human being No offense, Wes, I can't imagine Yeah, normal people going through any of this hassle just to get internet.
Wes Bos: I'm hoping what happens is that and we're starting to see this is that cell carriers start to roll out, like just a box, you can buy in a SIM card, you can put it and it will just work. But if you are very remote, or if the sort of thing of like using this cell, a cell card in an LTE modem is sort of frowned upon by the cell carriers are not supported or anything like that, then you do have to get a little bit hacky. So it's sort of interesting, because it feels like very early days, there's huge communities of people doing this on Facebook and in the forums and things like that. And it is too bad because like I get people messaged me all the time. And say like, hey, like, I would love to do this, like, what what do I buy? And I'm just like, well, first of all, do you have putty installed on your Windows computer? And like, can you because like, I've totally broke them like a $200 modem before?
Unknown: How good are you at soldering? Yeah, exactly. Like, that's literally something you have to do is if you brick a modem, you have to solder USB connections to some of the pads on the modem in order to reflash some of these devices, right? Yeah, that's funny, cuz that was a joke. And I didn't even realize how accurate it was.
Wes Bos: Yeah, yeah, it's, uh, it is too bad. And honestly, I think it will get better in the coming years, especially as like, even in Canada, there's, the government has said in by 2030, which is way too long, 10 years, that every person in Canada should be able to get, I think 50 down and 20 up in 10 years, which is a joke because like, yeah, that's right now.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah,
Wes Bos: next up antennas, where I live, the service that I'm using only operate on Rogers, and I we don't have Rogers reception where we are. So in order to get reception, we have put antennas up in the air. And there's kind of two different types of antennas, you get omnidirectional antennas, but you just throw in the air and you don't have to point them. And those are good in most cases that you get like an okay signal, but you want better. And then if you have, if you really want to get a good signal, and you know what you're doing, you can get these things called the Yagi antennas. And they are pointed, and you have to run two of them each at a 45 degree angle. And then you got to point them directly at the cell tower and get them as high as you possibly can. We had them on top of our house and they were working last last year. And we came back this year and they just just stopped working entirely I don't know if it has some corrosion in the connections or, or something happened. So we just and I'm not about to climb on a roof we paid in painting, I got my brother in law to climb on the roof who's crazy, but I'm not about to climb on the roof and take them down. So I just bought more. And I put them on a 20 foot piece of wood. And then we went to the very highest porch spot at our cottage. So it's probably 40 feet in the air, and I'm devising a plan to get even higher, but that was good enough to get me back online man. So now you gotta you gotta solder. You gotta climb. You gotta hack. I literally climbed it. I climbed a tree. And I was just like, I just coded a thing in the browser that would speak the signal strength to me every five seconds and then I climbed a tree and I was just pointing it around and I was getting some weird reception because I The signal was bouncing off like we're in a very hilly area. So the signal is bouncing off of the hill and back at us. So when if I turned it around as working better and just the like, you have to, like be somewhat curious to do this because, like who's gonna climb a tree and start soldering things? Right? Like it's not for everybody, but
Scott Tolinski: certainly, it's the hacker mentality though. It's definitely the hacker mentality. And if you needed me to climb trees West, I would climb lots of trees for you, because I'm definitely a tree climber. You know, that's, that's definitely Atlanta. Landon started early. He's already climbing our peach tree and Courtney's really excited about it. Oh, yeah. All right, well, I'm gonna come down when the borders reopen, you come down and get get that one off of our house. All right,
I'm down.
Wes Bos: What else boosters. So there's also cell boosters, where you can throw an antenna up in the air, and then it will rebroadcast LTE signal inside the house. And those are good for metal buildings and things like that. But they do add a lot of noise. So in my case, a booster was not a good use case. Let's talk about plans. So like, how do you get a cell phone plan that does this, so a lot of plans are phone only. So they will either detect, if you take a SIM card and throw in an iPhone, it works great. And then if you put it in an LTE modem, it will stop working. And they detect that by either by the IMEI number, which is a like a unique number to your phone or to your modem, or they detect it by what's called a TTL value. I mean, TTL value is how many routers like basically, if you send a request to Scott, every time that piece of data goes through another router, the TTL value is decremented by one. And that's to stop requests from bouncing around the internet forever. And if it ever hits zero TTL then the thing will just die and never make it. I've heard and this is not in Canada, but T Mobile uses a TTL to detect people hotspotting so if you hotspot your TTL will be one less than if you make the request directly from your phone. So people have found out that if you just increase your TTL by one, it detects it as hotspot even though it's not. Alright, sorry, it detects it not as hotspot. I've never done that, because that's not available in Canada. But I've heard that that's a way to sort of get around that. Some in the States. It's pretty popular to use something called the calyx ca l y x. There's a lot of third party resellers that will sell SIM cards that work for data purposes and have unlimited so there's calyx Institute, it's very expensive. I think you have to pay $500 up front to get access to it. And then I think it's like, I don't know 50 100 bucks a month to get unlimited which is which is amazing. In Canada we have Bell which we live in a rural area so we qualify for their special pricing, which is you get 100 gigs for 80 bucks, and then after that it's $4 a gig. So our bill was $300 and I called them up I was like your criminal like my kid is trying to I'm working from home my kid is trying to do school. Yeah, you're charging four bucks a gig. So there's that it's a it's a huge rip off we have that one as sort of a backup. Because we do get good Bell we get great Bell signal out here and we just plug it in and it works but we try not to use that one because it's so expensive. Tell us in Western Canada has like a terabyte for 70 bucks a month which is awesome. And then again it's locked by tower so you have to apply for it based on your billing address or your where you live and they'll lock that modem to only work on a specific tower in your area. So like it we are seeing some change but you look at other things like I did the math on the other carriers in Canada and it would have been like 1200 dollars a month. So currently I am actually I'm not gonna say what I'm using. I'm using an American plan that is on roaming. I don't I don't want to get taken down so it's a better deal to go to the states and buy a SIM card and then bring it to Canada and use it on roaming full time which I think the company that I'm using knows that they are like doing better but I won't say too much more about that because it's a bit of a gray area. speeds depends on tower congestion. I was getting like 150 megabits down in at home up here. I'm lucky to get 15 down and one up and that is what the tower that is with it perfectly pointed I did drive around the lake and sat right next to the tower and I got 25 down and about five up so a lot of times a tower will simply just limit your speed because there's other people in the area that need to use it as well and also depends on if you're prepaid postpaid, or some people are like that ambulance drivers or cops on the forum, and they get these things called first responder accounts called FirstNet. And they are top of the line in terms of priority, which is pretty cool. But obviously regular people can't get access to those as well. Let's wrap it up here, some tools have to use, there's an app in the states called cell mapper, people put it on their Android phones, and they try to map out where the cell towers are in the States, because you need to know like, Where's the cell tower and what, who owns that cell tower and what carrier they broadcasting in Canada, they must legally tell you where the cell towers are. So there's lots of maps, or you can just look up the different cell towers, they won't tell you the cell ID of that tower. But you can just, you can just drive to it and check what the idea is on your phone, you can you can open your iPhone and hit Star 12345 pound 3001 pound star and that will open up field diagnostic mode in your iPhone. And that will give you the raw data as to what tower you're connected to and what carrier and things like that. It's pretty neat. Facebook group LTE hacks, Facebook group is awesome group of people who are trying to do this for themselves as well. And the LTE fix.com is a great website as well, that has a bunch of gear. So if you're in the states and you want to order gear LTE fix seems to be the place to get it. That's it.
That's everything I've learned about LTE internet, it's not perfect. Like I'm not even recording this with Scott right now, just because the upload is so bad. And latency is still like 150 200, sometimes 500 milliseconds, I'm still getting a latency on my LTE modem is fine for uploading a YouTube video takes a couple hours, that's okay, it's fine for downloading doing Instagram, uploading photos. But when it comes to doing video calls, it's still too slow. And that's why I have to save my 10 gigs of cellphone data a month for talking to Scott. That's crazy. I'm sorry. No, that's okay. That's like, like, like, it's hard to feel sorry for me. Because like, we're sort of on vacation here. Obviously, we're still working. But like we chose to come out here. What makes me frustrated is that the government and a lot of these companies don't care about the people that live out here and need access to these things like even simply just like being able to visit a doctor online, which is something you can do in our province now. or attend school, all of that stuff is really important for local people. And it's frustrating to see a lot of the rural residents left out
Scott Tolinski: of that. Well. I mean, I've lived in places that haven't had access to the best internet, but I've never had to deal with anything quite like what you're experiencing. Yeah, it's crazy to me. And it does, it does give you a bit of perspective in terms of like really just what people deal with all over the not only both of our countries, but I can't even imagine in other countries what it's like so it definitely it definitely opens your mind. And it is fascinating to hear what you go through to get get a good signal. You say other countries, Europe, every time I complain about it, you get a screenshot from someone. They're like, Oh, I live in I live somewhere in Europe and I pay five euro a month for like a gigabit down and like, it's just like not a thing at all.
Wes Bos: South Korea or Japan where Yeah, yeah. It's amazing. And obviously there's there's other countries as well, where it's just like, I get emails all the time from people that ask like, hey, I want to buy your course. But how big is it like they want to know the size of the download before they even buy it? Because that's a they don't know if they can take it or not because they're gonna have to spend a couple days downloading this thing before they can even take the course. Yeah, wild. All right, this is getting a little tasty. So we'll end it here. Thanks for tuning in and we'll catch you on Wednesday, please
Unknown: head on over to syntax.fm for a full archive of all of our shows. And don't forget to subscribe in your podcast player or drop a review if you like this show.