Unknown: You're listening to syntax, the podcast with the tastiest web development treats out there. strap yourself in and get ready. Here is Scott, ski and West boss.
Wes Bos: Welcome to syntax today is the tastiest podcast about blogging, we got an awesome question in our potluck, and it was super well thought out. And I thought, hey, let's do an entire episode on this because I've got a lot to say about blogging, I think blogging can be super beneficial to your career. So we're gonna dive into like, sort of the the specifics of creating content and how to make good content as well as the mechanics of like, where do you post it? Like, what's the best platform for that? How do you get traffic to it? Today, we are sponsored by two awesome companies. First one is a century they're going to do all of your error and exception tracking. And the second one is Sanity, which is going to give you a structured content, CMS, it's gonna be the backend to your front end. We'll talk about them partway through the episode. With me today. And as always, is Scott klinsky. How you doing today, Scott?
Scott Tolinski: Hey, doing good. Just hanging out ready to talk about blogging? Yeah, just uh, I've been working on a lot of fun projects lately, just on my little spare time. And it's, uh, it's been really nice, because it's so funny when you, you know, level up tutorials is, has always in it still is a fun project for me. But like, the moment it becomes your job job, it's inherently becomes a little bit less fun. So I've been working on some little little fun side projects that actually are gonna be pulled back into level up at some point, but it does a nice little trick in my brain that makes me think it's a fun project. And I'm pretty pretty into it. So yeah, no, I'm just, I'm in a good coating mindspace right now and I'm ready to talk about some blogging stuff. Because I'm, I'm actually going to be doing a form of video blogging myself. It's totally not relevant to this episode in terms of blogging, but yeah, I think at least there's some connection there and the type of content and things like that. So no, I'm just excited about talking about sharing what you know, and how to do it. How are you doing?
Wes Bos: Good. I'm doing pretty good. We are still up at our cottage. We have my wife's Caitlin's family over right now which they so kindly took our kids to the park while we can record because I realized where I had put my office in the in the cottage. The kids playroom is right above us. And have you ever lived in an apartment where like people above you are so loud? Like what could possibly be doing?
Scott Tolinski: We just weren't. They were they were people. Uh, we got a new roof over here. And there was like, yeah, six guys hammering on our roof. And I was like, I tell the car down like, this reminds me of that one apartment that we lived in. In Arbor where this guy? We actually we called him stompy because we just were like, Is he an elephant? Like what does he do? Is he an elephant. He's rolling bowling balls up there with the with stumpy doing today. And a little side story about stompy he was a learning how to play the guitar, which is cool. You know,
Unknown: it's a loud hobby.
Scott Tolinski: Maybe we should put some headphones on or something. But he was learning how to play the guitar and instead of like practicing or playing a bunch of different stuff, the dude played one song 24 seven. And that song was hit me with your best shot. And so we just had to hear that. Dun, dun dun dun just oh. So start Oh,
Wes Bos: man. Um, I think if there's any motivating factor in my life to buy a house, it was living above or below random people like I had one time when I lived in Toronto. It was like a shared vent system. So like you could hear everything through like the cold air returns everything. And this person would just decide to play drums out like one in the morning like
Scott Tolinski: full on drums like do not realize there's people here
Wes Bos: you will go down there and be like, what are you doing? Like, in the Oh, sorry, is it loud? Obviously. can't draw that one in the morning. Oh, that drives me crazy sharing sharing. So anyways, my kids are doing that right now. So I have to figure out another spot for my desk because our
Unknown: stompy I can't hear him so it you know,
Wes Bos: no, they're they're gone at the park right now which is conveniently timed. Yeah. So let's talk about blogging. We got this awesome question from Tim, who puts in quotes sticker Dev. The question was, hi gents, you frequently talk about writing blog posts as a good way to improve skills, show motivation, help others and really double down on learning something. So I have decided to write a blog post. I have started searching the internet and it is all geared towards WordPress mainly. But surely there is different ways and stacks to do this. I know your Gatsby starter course shows a blog Scott maybe an episode or a tasty treat done on the following. It's funny because he detailed out this entire show notes. And I read over it I was like this is perfect. One of the questions was like how do you outline a blog post? I'm like Tim, you you know how How to do this kind of clearly you just outlined a show for us.
Unknown: But this is the best and
Wes Bos: so we're gonna go through that and the one like sort of thing here he he put this at the end but I'm gonna put at the start is how to blog posts help you learn make a list of topics, start researching those topics for the blog post, what a better way to learn than trying to explain to someone else who doesn't know it. You guys say this all the time, but it didn't really sink in until right now this was a huge aha moment for me. So I think that is such a good thing to double down here is you, you might think like, I don't have anything to share with people, there's blog posts out about other things is that's not the point of blogging, the point of blogging is to be able to explain something well enough so that you confirm it to yourself that you know it and if you don't know it well enough, you're gonna figure it out. Same thing with talks, and podcasts. And anytime that you try to explain something to someone else, you're really doing it for selfish reasons to teach it, teach it to yourself, right?
Scott Tolinski: Totally. Yeah, I so I still very much get that especially because the things that I learned and teach the best are the things that I've just learned. Just because you you understand the pain points, you understand what exactly the things that you ran into when you were learning this technology. And then by therefore, writing these things all out, it's almost like an advanced form of like, double notes where you'd like maybe you took notes, maybe you just took mental notes. But then the blog post is sort of like an affirmed version of those notes to say, this is what this actually is in my brain. And this is how I understand it to, you know, I even like talk to coordinate sometimes. And I'm sure she absolutely loves this. I'm sure this is one of her favorite things about our relationship, when I tried to explain to her web topics, and she's just sort of like, Yeah, why are you telling me about this? So you know that just being able to explain it to people who don't know what you're talking about is is the best way to just totally get a better handle on it. And maybe you'll run into some epiphanies yourself while writing the post about the topic at hand. Mm hmm.
Wes Bos: Alright, so the first question we have here is what are some of the different platforms to publish a blog on? So I think that this is probably not the best first question to ask yourself, but it is the the first question that people ask they say, Okay, what am I going to post it on? And what is it going to look like when the reality is the meat and potatoes of blogging is what is the actual content? That's that's what matters at the end of the day. Right. But that said, I definitely think the the, where you publish your blog post is super important. So there's I guess there's a couple camps, there's, there's hosted yourself. So whether that's you're doing a Gatsby or WordPress, or something where you host it yourself, and you're coding it and doing all that, or there's the the other sort of way, which is publish it on something like probably medium is the most popular right now or wordpress.com, something like that. So what are your thoughts about both of those approaches? Scott?
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, I think there's I think there's, there's so many platforms to pick from, right you got in the hosted space, even ones that look that are outside of third of our tech industry like Tumblr that people use Tumblr as a blog, Squarespace or, or WordPress, or any medium, but medium is just so obnoxious, right? pop ups that are like little far not really gonna read the rest of that, like I really can't stand using medium at this point. You know, I'm personally because I'm a tech person, I'm going to go the self hosted route. And specifically because it is easier now than ever to get something that's very, very polished, but nice and fast. And all these things, like when I think about in the past, okay, in the past, you say I wanna I want to host my own blog, should I hosted on WordPress? Or should I develop a WordPress site? Well, then you think about, Okay, I got to get my, my XAMPP or MAMP server going or whatever, I got to get my Apache server going, I have to install WordPress, I created database, then I've got to install a theme, you got to do all of these things that take quite a bit of time. And it probably by the end of it leaves you a little exhausted. So for me, I'm gonna go self hosted. And in my opinion, I don't know if we're going to get into this just yet. But in my opinion, the fastest way to get going with the self hosted blog is with one of these new class of static site generators and markdown files. So if you're a tech person, you can write markdown files. My first instinct would go to Gatsby or grid, some if you were a view fan, and just install it get going right away because those platforms are going to allow you to do that in just seconds. Right?
Wes Bos: Yeah, especially the the hosting aspect of the static site generators is so simple things like Netlify. I think that's often a tripping point or people never want to update their own. They never want to update So like I forget how to deploy it, and then that's a huge thing. And that will deter you. So I agree as well, I think you should go that route. I even said this, like, probably six years ago, when medium was starting to become popular, I was like, they're going to pull the rug from under you, they are going to screw you. And everyone's like, no mediums way better. And there certainly is lots of like hacker noon and Free Code Camp. All of these things were like they built on the back of medium. And they guarantee they would not be nearly as popular if it were not for medium. But you starting to see people sort of turn their back on medium right now, because they're starting to do weird things with your content, they're starting to block it, they're not allowing you to do things. So I am always 100% of the the idea of just own your own content. And I would say like, it's fine to whip up a quick WordPress or medium or something like that, that's hosted just to get your ideas out there. But in the long term over over the arch of your life, this is your content, you should own it. And you should, you should ideally be sort of hosting it yourself and having control over it. Especially like, I don't know, if you want to like, let's say you've got this amazing backlog of 40 blog posts, and you've got tons of traffic going to them. And also knew you could like you could launch a course on that. And you can make a lot of money. But if you're on medium, you don't, you can't like put a banner or something up like that. And you could put a little text link at the top, but you're gonna make 100 times more money, if you're able to put a banner or a little countdown clock or anything like that, if you have control over the the source code of that it's going to be better in the long run for you. I guarantee it.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, I can totally hear what you're saying. Cuz even in even in like hacker noon, or some of those were dev two or whatever, though, where you don't own the platform itself. And you're just publishing on there. It's great for name recognition. But in the same respect, you're not able to do those things, either. And I think that is a big part about owning your content, if you're looking for this thing to, you know, advance your career in some way other than, hey, look, I wrote these blog posts, because you see that you see, oh, so and so writes, completes tutorials, if you'd like to learn about these tutorials, you know, head on over to here, but that requires a lot for the user, and it requires them to read it that read that little section. And you know, they might get to that part and see Oh, this is an ad I'm gonna just turn back now, compared to if they're seeing a banner ad or something a little bit flashy year, maybe not something obnoxious. But still, yeah, I totally hear what you're saying on that in terms of being able to own the platform. And I personally have gotten screwed, so to say, and not owning my platform in some sort of ways, when I was trying to do everything through YouTube. So before I built level up tutorials, I was really just trying to do everything through YouTube in terms of how I make money, or how I, you know, interact with the community, and I and I relied on YouTube's ad revenue. And when their revenue model changed, and my revenue dropped in half, and then in half again, I just had to sort of be like, oh, okay, well, I guess, I guess I just have to accept this because I have no power and no control over how they manage their platform. And And sure enough, they have better tools for monetization and stuff in there now. But like, it was, it was such a huge, my fire had been extinguished by the giant bucket of water that YouTube's revenue had poured on. I was just like, oh, man, like I put so much work into this. And now I'm making 500 bucks a month on 300,000. Yeah, drivers, you know, it's like, this is not worth it at all.
Wes Bos: Yeah. And on the flip side, I've always been aggressive of getting like you can use, I use YouTube. But I try very hard to take those people off of YouTube in my own course platform. And because I did that, with all of my free courses, I've had massive email lists and a massive audience to be able to sell my free stuff to, and I guarantee I wouldn't be able to do this full time if I had not tried to channel those people out of the platform. Because, again, these companies are out there to make money and they do what makes sense for them. They don't care about you, the the creator at the end of the day. Yeah, we should. We should also say like, there's also like this, like third area, which is like writing blog posts for other people. So you can go out there and write blog posts for smashing mag and CSS tricks. And web designer mag.
Scott Tolinski: You could write one for level up tutorials do if you want help, I'll publish it. We have a post section, but we don't have an official program, but I'll
Wes Bos: publish it if it's good. Yeah, I've written posts for both smashing mag CSS tricks and the the what's a web designer magazine, web designer magazine, whatever it's called. net and. NET bag that was sort of was and those are great publications. But I think with the exception of the CSS tricks when I wrote my Sublime Text article, because that was that was what gave me a huge initial push. I thought that I was gonna To get a lot more fame and recognition than actually was and I found out that in the long tail not maybe not maybe immediately when, when these big entities can push 40,000 people to an article, but in the long run over three years of just getting random Google searches. Yeah. And recognition, I think that it's better in the long run that I had put most of the stuff on my own blog.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, I think I think there is sort of, it's funny, because I think there is a matter of like, what your intention is, like, is your intention just to blog about your interests? Is that just about to share your experience it? Are you trying to do something more with it? Are you trying to have it Enhance Your Career, you have to look at as like, what's your intentions? Are you trying to get eyes and audience on this? Because there's a lot of these questions that the answer could very well be well, the right solution for me is to post on one of these sites, you know, Free Code Camp or anything, because because your piece is more likely to get read. Because if you if it's on your own thing, you're gonna have to hustle for it. I mean, it's you know, it's not if you build it, they will come situation, you have to hustle for those clicks. I can't think of how many times I've seen like a, forgive me if for saying this, but like a crappy blog post on on Reddit that got, you know, just pushed onto the web dev Reddit, and then it will like, it'll grow to the mass of two thumbs up or up. Yeah, yeah. And that's where it remains. Because, you know, people just don't don't don't care about it. Right. So yeah, without some sort of heavy name attached to it, like one of these platforms, people just flat out might not care. And that could be a big problem. Because you post it, you maybe get like 30 or 40 views and then like, like, That's it? And if that's Yeah,
Wes Bos: it's kind of deflating. You spent days but writing this thing? And then why doesn't go out to? It's hard to get that in? It's hard to get that sort of initial line in that. I think that's a really good point. You said like, like, what is your idea, like, sometimes there's people out there that maybe have like an open source project, and they just want eyes on it. And they don't, they don't necessarily care about creating, like a blog that has lots of readers and, and people behind it, because that's not their end game. They're not like me, and you or they need to capture these people, right? They just want people to be able to use their thing. So of course, in that situation, then absolutely. Or people who are big proponents for accessibility, they just want to, to get the most people ever to know about accessibility. And if that's the case, then they go to these platforms and write an article for them. And you can also get you get paid by these platforms as well. You can make some decent little pocket change there. Yeah, yeah,
Scott Tolinski: I think that's all good things to keep in mind. It's funny, because you have this idea of you publish a blog post on your own platform. And I said, You know, I might get one or two upvotes. And then nobody will, you know, care. But all of these platforms, like every platform ever, including level up tutorials. That's how it started, right? You release something nobody cares. You release it on the bottom. Here's, yeah, yeah, I started now we hear? Yeah, I don't like Drake. I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
Wes Bos: I'm either I hate Drake. I, I'm sorry, from Canada to the rest of the world for Drake.
Scott Tolinski: But yes, I mean, it is it's like if you have a longer term end game, you have to get cool with the nobody caring about any your stuff, and then just go from from there, and then something will get picked up. And then something will get picked up and something will get picked up. And who knows, maybe the first video or the first blog, you you released will eventually have a million views on it. And just people get tired too after after doing a couple of not seeing that progress. So you have to know what your long, long term end game is. And if you don't have a long term end game, that's cool. You can just sort of bounce off the walls like a ping pong ball. And until you find what that end game is, you don't have to have the plan and everything at the outset.
Unknown: I think that's the beauty of, of blogging.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah,
Wes Bos: is that just do it all, you can just try things with a blog, like, that's what I did. I was just trying blog posts, and then I hit my Sublime Text blog posts, and then took off and I said, that's my thing. You know, like, I didn't know what my thing was. I specifically done those. And that's the beauty of a blog, you can like taste test things. And you will know by the stats and the shares and the comments and the tweets as to what has hit a nerve and what is going to work for your thing.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, my thing was SAS tutorials before anybody knew it's has always been thing.
Wes Bos: Good thing. So the other questions we had here, what are the pros and cons of each of these platforms? We talked about that? What are the easiest platforms? quickstart I think Scott answered that is I would probably get a Gatsby or grid, some blog up and running. You don't
Scott Tolinski: need a database. You have no configuration. You just hit a command and the markdown files you make a new markdown file, just work. Love it.
Wes Bos: Totally busy day, you probably don't need the admin editing UI. If you're a developer like that's, I've been working on my own Gatsby website for a while now. And I don't think markdown is a good, a good solution for anyone not technical, like you're not going to ask a client to do markdown. But as a developer, it's amazing because you can just start writing a text file, deploy that sucker and it will go up on the website. And that's like, such a low barrier to actual entry.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, yeah. Now they'll get MDX MDX. Love it.
Wes Bos: Yes. And then the fourth question here is what are the best platforms for a developer to learn more skills by building so again, I'd probably go with a Gatsby or a headless WordPress, with Gatsby, something like that. Because you're also going to learn just building your own thing as well, you're gonna get better at your web development design skills by doing that,
Scott Tolinski: and you learn graph qL, you'll get better at react, you'll see just how dang fast react sites can be. The thing that bugs me is that when people like talk about some of these platforms, it'd be like, why would you want to use a front end framework for this kind of angle, because we're not shipping the frame and you are shipping it, but like the initial hit is just HTML and CSS. It's the fastest darn site on the in the planet, Gatsby sites are so dang fast, that with the amount of like pre loading and all those things that you get with a Gatsby site out of the box, like they get I could build an HTML site with all of those features that does all those things like that, but it's gonna take me longer. So like a Gatsby site, to me is really the the pinnacle of building a fast site quickly, Goodson included as well for those of you viewpoint. And we've talked a lot about markdown files and things like that. But I do want to talk or at least lead into one of our sponsors here, which is Sanity, which allows you to have an actual full on backup. Now, I did mention that I thought having to get a whole WordPress rig setup for your darn blog is kind of a pain in the rear, especially you got to do all the database stuff. But what happens if if you could just sign up for a service that allows you to build a fully extendable UI for a back end, and allows you to do it as quickly and painlessly as just simply signing up for any account anywhere, that's where Sanity comes in with sanity.io.
Wes Bos: So if you do want a UI for your blog posts, maybe maybe your website is a little bit more complex past what a markdown file. And like, though, if you, if you get complex with markdown, you start getting into what's called frontmatter, which is a bunch of like tags, and slugs and things that you put at the top of your markdown file and this kind of like hidden data. However, at a certain point, you do want, if you if your website gets a little bit more complex, you might want a UI where you can do relational data, you have a interface for uploading images, you can create your own custom inputs. And that's what Sanity does. It does structured content. So you can sign into Sanity, you can you have a UI for creating your own CMS back end. And then you can bring along your Gatsby or they have like a Great Gatsby integration, any any sort of front end that you want to build your own. With that. So I would recommend checking out sanity@sanity.io forward slash syntax, if you go to that URL, you're gonna get double the free plan than what you just get on the homepage. So make sure you go to sanity.io forward slash syntax, they also have a couple links there. On some quick getting started with a like you can get started with next or next or Gatsby, you can take a quick look at those. Thanks so much to Sanity for sponsoring. Awesome. Awesome. So the next one, I think this is something Scott and I are pretty good at how do you structure a blog post. And I don't necessarily mean just for a blog post. But like any time that we want to make a video, anytime we want to make a podcast or blog posts, we have to take this idea that is just a bunch of stuff floating around in our head and we need to like distill that down into an outline. The big question is, how do you do that? You want to tackle that?
Scott Tolinski: I don't know if I'm the right person to answer this. Because I'm so bad at reading. I like have to like listen to my blog posts a lot. I'm just dread deliberating. So in my mind, everything comes down to the same type of structure that you'd use sort of for anything right? You have your introduction, maybe the what and wise of you reading this. I don't recommend starting off with Webster's Dictionary defines testing. Oh, yeah. So stuff like that. No, don't do that.
Wes Bos: That's like every every like conference talk starts with that too. Like Brendan, I created JavaScript in 1922. Yeah. And, like, okay, you don't like it makes sense that people start with Webster's dictionary or this is the history of it, because they don't know where else to do it. But that's so boring and almost nobody cares about that. Get into that. Really, you have to start with something that will hook somebody to reading or listening to the rest.
Scott Tolinski: They called the hook for a reason, right? Yeah, it's a hook. You got to hook them in. You got to let them know why they should be reading it. I see this a lot with libraries to people, they don't they don't give you the hook, they just start getting into some of the mumbo jumbo without telling you the hook, you know, some of the best, the best libraries and blog posts have a great hook. Here, you're doing everything wrong. For these reasons, I don't know, it doesn't have to be click Beatty, but click Beatty can be a decent hook sometimes as long as it's accurate and not totally overblown. But you could say like the five linting mistakes you're making, hey, these five linting mistakes are gonna be wasting you a ton of time. So let's get into you know what they are. Yeah. And then so that gives the reader clear expectation right from the get go. It says this is what the articles about. And then also not only that, but it also gives them maybe like, Alright, here's what I can expect out of the length, because I see that there's going to be five things, they're going to hit on each of them. And then that's going to be the article, you have this intro that needs to hook and give a good idea of what they're in for. And then subheads is subtitles with sections of each thing that you're looking at before then the best blogs, do it with an anchor link so that you can link directly to those headings, and have you know who does a great job of this is scotch scotch IO. Mm hmm. They have like a little pound sign next to the logo or next to the subheading. So you can just click that and get the update the link to the page. So you can copy and paste the link really quickly from there. So again, subheadings images where they're needed, those kind of things. But for structure for me again, you need to hook the intro, the meat that's organized and structured, and then the conclusion, this is what you should have learned. And then you can do your shameless plugs. And whatever at the end.
Wes Bos: I always like to have front is described the problem that
Scott Tolinski: kind of described our episode. Sorry. Yes. That's great. It's a pretty much a syntax episode.
Wes Bos: Well, that's what we do for a syntax episode is we have a little description at the top. Why is this episode important? We did that right here. We said, because we think that blogging is important for your career, it can really put you forward. And we sort of summarize it. Today, we're going to be talking about how we actually create the mechanics of where you should host it, as well as the actual content. Right? So those are the two things that we're going to be talking about that hooks you in for the the entire episode. Another thing that bugs me is people don't provide links to demos and other important things. Like if somebody's excited about it, they might read the summary, they might scan the sub, the titles, but they just want to see a demo of what it is. So if you have like a blog post that's 7000 words on like, I hook lasers up to my cat, and no jazz, right? Like, I want to see a video of that immediately when I see it. And then then I want to get into how did you actually do it? Right, like put the demos put the links up top? Or like, if you're saying like, I researched office chairs for 60 days. And here's I decided on this one, just tell people what it is that you've decided on. And then people will go into why did you decide on that put put the important stuff up top. I think that's super important. So structuring, I think that's good, just do an outline, and then sort of fill it in. That's how I do absolutely everything in my life, including my videos, I'll just sort of dump all the info into a bunch of titles, I'll rearrange it until it makes sense. And then I'll go into each of those sections. And if you find that there's too much in one section, that's a great time to split it up into two different sections. Yeah,
Scott Tolinski: I do that too. And even for the series, I'll do an outline for the series. And then I'll do an outline for the videos that it sort of, you know, like, Alright, now I'm going to dive a little bit more in depth. And that actually could be like how you structure a blog series, you know, here is the here is the the global outline. And here's the more in depth outline. In that kind of thinking, again, it will just get you thinking about structure. Okay, thinking about the key points that you want to hit on in general, it seems stuff that you learned in middle school or high school, and they were having you write papers. And it's no wonder that I'm not doing blog posts concerning I turned in one essay in my senior year, and my teachers that think you have dyslexia. Oh, maybe that's why I'm not good at this.
Wes Bos: Next one is how do you get direct traffic to your blog post, because that's part of a frustration. With writing these blog posts, you finally finish it, and you launch it and you get like 10 hits to it, and probably five of them are from a bot. So this is a hard topic, or a hard thing to do. Because I think often people will create content in the dark. And then in this, this goes for anything. I see this all the time with people that build courses, or people that are building a YouTube video, they'll just like, stay in the dark, create all this content. And then when it's time they go, Okay, I'm done. How do I get people to it? And I think it's really important to if you do want people to go to it, you have to do what I think everybody else is doing is you have to be working on building an audience to that type of thing and unfortunately That type of thing takes a very long time. So like how do you get traffic to your blog, you blog for five years with no traffic. And slowly over time, especially because of because of Google because of backlinks because of like, one like a really good example that I have is I have a blog post about being a sole proprietor, that's, I think, probably eight or nine years old. And I in that I just sort of detail all of the things that I need to know about running a business as a sole proprietor. And in that I put a link to Freshbooks. And I still seven years later to I get 200 bucks a month in Freshbooks for affiliate referrals to it. And that that never had never in my life had had a lot of traffic, never probably, I don't know, eight to 15 hits a day, but 18 to 15 hits a day times seven years. This is sort of like longer term things. People do find it. It's got links everywhere. It's been reprinted in countless textbooks, people like a lot of the big publishers have asked to reprint it and textbooks like just stuff like that will it'll slowly gain momentum over time.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, totally. So one of the things that's hard for us is developers is that we often feel like slimy pushing our stuff, or we feel concerned that people are going to rip it apart, and they might rip it apart. But that's one of those things you kind of just got to get over at some point, the fact that people might, might just rip it apart. And you can choose how you respond to that, whether you learn in advance from it, where they're you, you just ignore it, whatever, it doesn't honestly matter as long as your response is appropriate, right. So don't, don't be rude back, just move on or address the problems and or if there are them, but you have to push your stuff out there or else no one's ever going to find it, I have a lot of friends who are musicians, who would create excellent music, and they would just expect Oh, well, if my music is the best music ever, which it's great, but it's not the best music ever. If it is great, then like, you know, people aren't just going to inherently find it, love it, and you're not going to blow up, you have to hustle for those listens, you got to hustle for those clips, you've got to work for it. It comes down to really anything that you want anyone to care about. Because at the end of the day, people are mostly thinking about themselves, how am I going to get this? You know, job? How am I going to do this? How am I gonna do that people are thinking about themselves, they're not thinking like, Oh, I have to go looking for the best blog post and the best author, they're just going to, they're gonna, you know, get hooked on your your topic, because it's been shown to them in some sort of way that's been put in front of their mind. So you, you have to work to get those clicks, you got to work to get that audience. And that's not something that's just going to happen via SEO, or automatically you got to work for it, you got to tweet out, hit him up, do all of those things. And you can learn lessons from them in literally anything I mentioned musicians or anything like that. But it's literally any art or anything, where you're having to sell yourself or whatever, in any sort of way, you gotta you got to work for it. And I think that's one of the hard lessons that developers need to learn from marketers is, you know, it feels slimy, but you got to work for it.
Wes Bos: Mm hmm. Other things you can do is submit them to weekly emails. So there's this huge Peter Cooper runs Cooper press, which has JavaScript Weekly. He's got like a weekly email for absolutely every single topic and he's looking for links all the time. He doesn't necessarily care who it's from. He just cares that as one
Scott Tolinski: of our episodes he's recently in there
Wes Bos: was in which one?
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, the foundational JavaScript one.
Unknown: Ah, that's how I got,
Scott Tolinski: I got the newsletter. I was like,
Wes Bos: Whoa, cool. That's awesome. I love that episode did super well, I saw it got got shared by a whole bunch of people. And we didn't submit it there. But he obviously saw it. But most if you don't have a big audience, then you can just submit links, he has a whole process for submitting links to this. I think that's, that's really good. And then you can also just straight up ask people to share it for you. So this is something I'm not I don't totally feel great about. Because I get emails all the time from people saying like, I wrote this thing, can you share it or the I thought your audience would enjoy, which is straight out of marketing Handbook, which I don't necessarily like all that much. So usually, I'll share stuff for for people who I'm sort of not friends with, but like, who have maybe helped me out in the past or who are sort of friendly with me, generally, like I see their Twitter avatar, I know who they are happy to do something like that if I can. My DMS are full. So I don't see all my DMS, but I'm happy to do that. But then other times you get like the first dm ever from somebody. They're just like, hey, share this, please. Like no, like, Who are you? And then I have to vet it. And sometimes you tweet something and then people get all if there's something in the article that they don't agree with. And you're in the middle of this like huge Twitter fight and like, that's not necessarily something that I want to get on. So absolutely. Ask away. Ask everybody. You want to share that thing? Nothing wrong with that? Just don't expect it to hundred percent work all the time. What do you think about that?
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, I get we get a lot of it's funny, even with the podcast, I know there's so many of these things that we can relate to the podcast, but just how many emails do we get that says, it's like the exact same script, I feel like they copied and pasted the script, but I'd be like, my CEO of the company that I work for would be a really great guest on your show, I think your audience would really enjoy the book that they published with the link to the book. Like, it's like, Where did you get this script? There is so many people who give us this and it's like, Do you honestly think that that's going to work if we've gotten that 100 other times that your CEO from some company is the perfect guest for the show just so happens to line up with the release of their book, like that is not what we do on this show. Like when we are on that on the show, it just shows that you don't listen to the show, and that your guest isn't a good fit for the show. And it's like, Yeah, I don't know that really bugs me people who have those scripts? I mean, if you're gonna do it, kind of at least do your own but more genuine than that, if you expect them to do it.
Wes Bos: Yeah, that's awful. I can't believe how many people email saying, My boss wants to be on the podcast like, Can your boss not email me themselves? First of all? Yeah,
Scott Tolinski: yeah. I want to hear I want to hear what your boss's thoughts on the podcast if they're going to be and I want to hear maybe about one or two episodes, maybe maybe some proof, maybe something from the back catalogue to show you've been a longtime fan or something. No, I don't, I don't care that much. But like, honestly, you got to, if you expect the people to share your things, you've got to have at least some sort of a connection there. And having zero connection and cold calling like that is the same as calling up some person at random and asking them to, you know, subscribe to a magazine or something, it's not going to work. And you know, what else is not going to work your website because you write bad code. And your bad code needs to be tamed with a an error and Exception Handling tool, one of which is our favorite over here at syntax and that is century. Now I say it's our favorite not because there's sponsoring us because you know, they are but I use century myself and I pay for it I this is you know, then they're not giving me century for free. I pay for it. And I love it. And I use it. And I have since before we took them on as a sponsor. Now, Sentry is an excellent service that allows you to capture a login and handle all of your errors and exceptions. For instance, I've been having a really weird bug that I've been crushing lately. And, you know, I discovered some interesting new features and tools within Sentry, for instance, I had one sort of Sentry bug that's been popping up over and over again. And it's very obviously from a user's Chrome extension, because it tells me that in the error handling, and I found that inside of my project in the project settings, I can tell it Hey, you know what, you should not log any errors that look like they might be coming from a Chrome extension, because honestly, I don't care to debug someone else's Chrome extension. That's not what I'm here for. So I can click that. And then easily No, I don't get all those errors. And my error log makes more sense to me century is just great. And they somewhat recently change their API's, it'll be a little bit more unified, you're no longer using Raven, you're no longer you know, you're using node century, you're using JavaScript century in it, it works really well. I've been a big fan of these changes. And a century is just one of these tools, I really, really couldn't run my business without because it lets me know of these bugs, how many users they're happening to when they're happening. Let me know about releases. If I screwed something up in a release, what release who made the commit, how to fix it. From there. So head on over to sentry.io use the coupon code tasty treat all lowercase all one word, and you will get two months for free. So sentry.io coupon code tasty treat all lowercase? One word, two months free. That's all you got to know. Go ahead and do it.
Wes Bos: The last question we have here is how you get content to be in depth. But second. sink
Scott Tolinski: is a typo in the in the show notes and says suck int which is I'm not judging because I would probably spell succinctly exactly the same way. But it's hilarious. It's a sucking looking. It's like a it's like a integer in JavaScript. But it's like never the value you want. That's a second it sucks. It makes your code bad.
Wes Bos: Mm hmm. I should say the answer to this is you're never gonna make everybody happy. But you should be aiming to make people equally mad on either side. That's sort of how I go on my mind tutorials. I want enough angry emails, that stuff is too hard as matching as stuff is not in depth enough. And that way if I feel that those two things are balanced, that means I know I'm hitting the spot that I want to be because you're always going to get people who like with my node course a lot of times people say like, I wish that you would just do it with pure node API's and no packages and like, like, just do low level, database stores and things like that. And then You also get the people saying like, Oh, this is too complex, I wish you just use a framework right and and and and then most of the people are sort of down the middle. So don't worry about those fringes, those are just people who are not your target audience. And I've said it many times, there's the Seth Godin quote, where he just says, like, make your thing. And if people don't like it, you just say it's not for you. Because generally, if you have this idea of something that you want to build, and you want to make, you know, who it's for, you know, it's probably for you three months ago, and and you're gonna find your sort of audience. And don't worry about those, those people. So on that, that said, I always recommend to not go long winded. Just because no one's gonna read it, you people's attention spans are really, really low. And if you can sort of catch them with being succinct and getting enough that you can. And then the last point that I have here is that the beautiful thing about a blog post, and the worst thing about video is that blog posts are living there easy to update, you can always patch things in where you need it. And if you find you're getting lots of questions or lots of comments on a specific issue, you can always go back and edit and put that in. And that sort of living document that's both good for Google juice. Google wants to see that you're sort of tending to this article over time. But it's also just good for making a really hard, beautiful blog post over time.
Scott Tolinski: Yeah, like a topiary, you got to make sure it stays nice and pruned, and looking looking nice and fresh. I mean, but for real, I think a lot of it is just knowing who that audience is, like you mentioned, if it's not for you, it's not for you. But you got to look at some blogs like overreacted right Dan aber mouths blog, he goes deep into some of these things in react, and it's the perfect thing for him to do. And it's really captured that audience because the people listening to him or reading his blog, they're gonna want to see that kind of content. And that's what makes it so good is the fact that it had a point, it nailed that, that line. So you know, you personally your audience is a little bit different in my audience to is different. And, and you know, the things that I'm going in depth on is like, here's how to do this basic thing, right, here's how to do this thing. And if you want to follow along in the next one, and the next one, I'll tell you how to take it a little bit further. Or you can just stop here and go off on your own. If you've picked up the thing that you've learned by now, you can always add on more. So I usually personally venture on the shorter side of things, and keep it shorter, keep it more succinct, and worry less about covering every single use case in one single post, you know, try to have one central idea, keep it to that idea. And then don't go further than that. Because you can always make another post that encapsulates that other idea. You can link it, you can do multi part blog post part one, part two, part three, Part Four, that kind of thing. I have no problem with that. So I usually keep it more on the sink side, I usually keep it less on the technical side and more on the here's how to big picture of everything. Here's how this thing makes your life better. Here's the things to type to get it up and running. And here's what happened because we did that. So usually that that's my my structure, my thoughts on it. But again, it depends on who your audience is. Some people really, really can go in depth and deep on things and have that really work out for them.
Wes Bos: So that is all about blogging. And I'm actually really happy with this episode. There's a lot of things that I like to say about blogging, I wish that I did more blogging myself, right now I have other avenues of sort of getting my thoughts out. And that is via the podcast via my own videos, things like that. But I think blogging is probably the lowest barrier to entry. And also sometimes I even think about, like I say all this stuff on Twitter, and then it just like it goes away. Like I should really be taking my Hot Tips and turn them into just very short blog posts. And that's another tip I have here is like, Don't think that a blog post needs to be this huge thing. It could be three sentences of ha, today learn. You can change this in this program, or today I learned you can use the JavaScript spread to do this. That's totally fine. Just document it for a later time has even if I look at my own Hot Tips, people are like, what's the archive? I don't know. They're all they're all gone by now. And I'm sure I could read them out somehow. But
Scott Tolinski: it would be worth it. One of the podcasts I listened to the one of the hosts, he always like goes on, like tweet threads. And then they were saying like, if it's more than, you know, four tweets, then just put it into a blog post, just put it into a blog post and then that way, all of those are at least a one spot it's easier to follow and it is you know, searchable and all those things and archivable and easy to find in those ways. But yeah, I don't really have anything else is the my final thoughts here. All right, let's
Wes Bos: get into some sick pics. I have a sick pic today. That is a podcast, another good one that had been been finding. And this one is called spectacular failures. It's a podcast that goes into just spectacular failures, things like that. Beer companies and how Kodak went under and the funeral industry and a Christian theme park that went under her. And it's it's not the these, the stories are just insane. I love listening to this type of thing. So I would recommend that you check it out. It's called spectacular failures.
Scott Tolinski: Well, I just I just clicked that little checkbox and just smash that like button, and I'm gonna be subscribing to that. You know, it's so funny I have my stick pic is also a podcast. And it not only is that also a podcast, but it's very kind of similar in a lot of ways. And so when you were starting, I was just like, I wonder if we're gonna have the same exact sick pick, we don't, but it's very similar. And I think there if you subscribe to both of these, you're gonna get like a ton of fun knowledge. And these kind of ways. Mine is called business wars. And it's from wondery, who's, you know, one of the big networks, they do a lot of big time shows. But business wars is really great because it tells the story of different business situations, different competitions, where companies are competing against each other. I'm currently listening to one of the ones the story's a little bit more interesting than I would have thought in the story is Netflix versus blockbuster. And I just really just assumed that Netflix came in did their thing. And you know, blockbuster didn't hang, but it goes a lot deeper than that. There's a lot of like, CEO and board members stuff. And, you know, there's people on blockbusters team that essentially had everything. And the idea is to counter Netflix, but didn't have any sort of power over their bosses. So you just think of it as like, Oh, yeah, blockbuster, they didn't adjust, they died. But there it goes so much deeper than that. And there's so much more interesting than that. And they have these things for all sorts of different ones from Hasbro, vers, Mattel, McDonald's versus Burger King. And all of these are like five or six episodes long. So they're they're really in depth, they're really good. And I personally have just been loving this podcast. So you subscribe to to business wars, subscribe to spectacular failures. And now you're gonna get a lot about corporations and how they operate, and neat ideas and epic failures. Because really business wars, a lot of the companies end up failing at the Fed. So a little common theme there. And if you want to learn more about failure, just listen to the syntax episode on failure because I thought we nailed that one. I think it's just called failure or something to that extent, one of the older runs in our back catalogue. Yeah. Shameless plugs. I yeah, I have a big shameless plug, the level up tutorials, subscription level of Pro, the prices going up in a 15th. So you don't have very long here to subscribe. And if you subscribe to the year, not only you're going to get 25% off, but you're going to get that price forever. And so it's 180 bucks a year, if you subscribe for the year, right now, when you listening to this, if it's after August 15, you missed it, I'm so sorry, this is going to be the last chance you have to get this rate forever. We have a huge catalogue that came to level up tutorials over the past year, two years here. And there's so much more content now available now than ever the latest courses gets the e commerce. And the next course that's coming is Shopify and Gatsby, both of which of these courses, you'll dive into headless e commerce and the common pitfalls you might face from building a very simple site to building a very complex site. So if you want to learn that stuff, then off to level up tutorials.com forward slash Pro, and sign up, this is your last chance to lock in at this rate for ever
Wes Bos: sick. I have all my courses as well available at Wes bos.com forward slash courses. You can learn there's a bunch of free ones bunch of paid ones, check it out. Use the coupon code syntax, you're gonna get 10 bucks off any of the paid courses. If you get a free one, I will send you 10 junk. I'm not gonna send you 10 bucks. These are still free.
Unknown: I
Wes Bos: think that is it. Thank you so much for tuning in. Make sure you follow Scott and I on Twitter. I'm at Wes Bos Scott is at St. linsky. We're also on the gram as well. So hit us up on there. Yeah. All right. Thanks for tuning in. Please.
Scott Tolinski: Head on over to syntax.fm for a full archive of all of our shows. And don't forget to subscribe in your podcast player or drop a review if you like this show.